In this video, we're gonna learn how to delete a student
in our classroom project.
So we'll cover the following topics:
first off, I'll give you a demo of the application
for deleting a student,
then we'll look at the big picture,
and then we'll also look at the sequence diagram
just to see how everything fits together.
Alright, so let's start off with a demo of the application.
Note here on the far right, we have a new column
for delete, and that's a new link here,
and each link has the actual student ID embedded.
Now when I click on this link,
the application's gonna prompt me,
"Hey, are you sure you wanna delete this student?"
In this case, I'll hit cancel, so note nothing happened
to the application, nothing happened to the data.
But now let's go ahead and actually delete a user.
So we're gonna delete Lisa Mangano,
we click on OK,
and note Lisa Mangano is no longer in the list.
She was deleted from our application,
actually deleted from the database.
Let's try it one more time.
Here's a guy at the bottom, Maxwell Zeno.
We'll hit delete, and then we'll hit OK,
and Maxwell Zeno is now gone.
So we're basically deleting users from the database.
Now let's take a look at the big picture here.
So, we're gonna have this list-students.jsp,
it has that column with the new link here for delete,
they'll select that link, go over to our controller servlet,
this person will read that delete command,
and then pass it off to our database util,
and that person will handle the low-level JDBC code
for deleting a given student from the database.
Now a little bit more about this action link.
So, each row will have a delete link,
and basically this link has the current student ID
embedded inside of it.
So, like you saw on the demo,
when you click this link, it'll prompt the user first,
it'll actually go and delete the student from the database.
Now here's the sequence diagram,
just more behind-the-scenes work here,
so this list-students.jsp, the user clicks the delete link.
It's gonna call the doGet method on our servlet,
and we'll pass over a command=DELETE.
Our servlet will take that command, say okay, now we need
to to a delete, and then it'll actually call
the deleteStudent method on our database util.
And this is very similar to what we've done
in all of the previous videos.
Alright, so I love my to-do list.
So the first thing we're gonna do is add a delete link
to the JSP,
then we'll add code to that controller servlet
to handle the processing of that delete command,
then we'll add code to our student database util
to actually do the low-level JDBC work
for deleting a student.
So that's the game plan.
I'm excited, I'm ready to write some code.
And we'll do everything from scratch.