All right, so let's go ahead
and start with our to-do list.
The first thing we're gonna work on is step number one,
adding a "Delete" link on our JSP page.
So let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
What I want to do is actually open up that file
"list-students.jsp"
and I want to add a "Delete" link on this JSP,
and we'll do small iterations on it to get us going.
So let's move down a bit in this table,
the table rows, and we're gonna add this
right next to the "Update" link.
We're actually gonna add it
in the same cell as the "Update" link.
So this is our normal table row, "firstName",
"lastName", "email", and right now we have "Update" link.
We're gonna use that same cell for the "Update" link
and we're gonna add another link here for "Delete".
But just to get us started, I just want to put
just a plain-text version of "Delete" in here right now.
So I'll do a space with a vertical bar
and then I'll hit return, and then I'll just add
the word "Delete". I'll get into the link stuff
in a second, but I just want to make sure
that this thing lays out properly.
So I just want to keep it simple, just to get us started.
But the key here is that there is one cell,
we have our "Update" link already with a vertical bar,
and then the text "Delete".
So let's save this, and let's run it,
just to make sure we have our HTML in order.
All right, so this looks really good.
So here's our "Action". We have "Update".
With a vertical bar, "Delete". So it's plain-text right now.
Don't worry about the link stuff, we'll cover that
in a second, but at least I wanted to make sure that
we could lay it out properly in HTML.
So this looks good so far.
So let's go ahead and swing back
into our "list-students.jsp".
And what I'd like to do here
is actually define a "deleteLink" for that URL.
So I want to do something very similar to what I did
for "Update", but I want to just copy that,
and actually copy-paste it, and I'll set up
a similar link here for "Delete".
So let me just write a quick comment here to myself.
So I'll just highlight these lines, and I'll copy them,
and I'll just paste them.
Okay, great. So they're pasted here.
Let me make some small mods.
So the variable name is not gonna be "tempLink" anymore.
I'll call this guy "deleteLink."
That's the name of the variable that we can use
later on in our page.
And they're gonna send it to this servlet.
I want to change the command.
So instead of the "LOAD" command,
I want to give the command name "Delete" in all-caps.
All right, so that's basically it.
That's how we can define a link to delete a student.
All right, let me clean up some extra white space here.
Now let's move down to this "Delete" section here,
and this is where I'm gonna add or make use of that link.
I'll set up an href for it.
So here I'll say, "a href="
and here, I'll make use of the "${}"
and I'll say, "deleteLink".
And I have my text, "Delete" and then "&lt;/a&gt;".
So that's the actual link.
Again, very similar to the "Update" link
but now we're using a "Delete" link.
All right, so let's save that.
Now let's test this out here and see how it works.
So I can simply go back to my browser
and I can simply just refresh this page.
All right, so I hit the "Refresh".
And whoo, yeah. Looking good here.
So here's our "Action", and we have our "Delete" link.
And if you hover over each one of those links there,
it has the embedded student ID.
But here, let me go ahead and just copy this link
and put it into a text editor, just so you can see it.
So we're calling our servlet,
and we're passing over "command=DELETE&amp;studentId=5"
or depending on whatever student ID
that we're using at that time.
The actual value for "studentId" will vary,
depending on where we're at in the list.
So this looks good so far.
So we're in pretty good shape, pretty good shape.
Now, one thing though, is that when I hit "Delete",
it doesn't do anything right now.
But I'd like to add a feature to prompt the user
before we actually do some deleting work.
So I'll prompt them up front,
"Hey, are you sure?"
before you blow up everything.
So we want to prompt the user.
And we're gonna make use of some JavaScript to do that.
Ooh, JavaScript.
Now, full disclosure: I'm not a JavaScript expert.
I know just enough JavaScript to get me by.
I like to copy a lot of JavaScript off the web.
But here, we're just gonna use JavaScript
to just prompt the user if they want to proceed or not.
So here I'll just make use of "confirm".
Basically I'll throw up a little dialog box and I'll say,
"Are you sure you want to delete this student?"
Now, what we have here in blue inside of the quotes here,
inside of the double quotes, this is all JavaScript code.
We'll prompt the user, and if they hit "cancel",
then we simply do "return false".
If they hit "OK", then we'll actually process
and go to the actual href link.
So that's the idea of making use of JavaScript
in this "onclick" handler.
So this is kind of exciting, we're actually making use
of JavaScript integrated with some jsp technology.
This is actually really, really cool.
All right, so there we go.
So that's in place, save that.
Let's go back over to our browser.
And actually, what I'm gonna do here is,
I'm actually gonna copy the URL, and I'll move it
into a real browser like Firefox.
And then I'll click "Delete", and it says,
"Are you sure you want to delete this student?"
And you can hit "OK" or "Cancel".
Again, doesn't really do anything on the back end yet,
'cause we haven't written a servlet code,
but we'll get there in a second.
All right, so that's kind of the basics here for step one.
So we went through the process
of actually adding a "Delete" link to our jsp.
In the following videos, we'll get into the servlet
and database code for actually performing the JDBC work
and actually deleting the user from the database.
We'll cover that next, so I'll see you there.