All right, so in this video
we're actually gonna add the code
for deleting the student from the controller servlet
and the database util.
We'll cover steps two and three in this one video,
we'll kind of just mash it altogether
because the code is really short
for those two operations.
All right, diving back into Eclipse,
first off, I want to take a look
at that list-students.jsp
just to get a handle on the parameters
that are being passed to our controller servlet.
So, moving on down we have this link
that we set up to actually delete a student,
that's lines 48 through 52,
so note here, there are two parameters
that are going to our student controller servlet.
We're passing over command equals delete
and then we're passing over a student ID
and that's the tempStudent.Id
and information's being passed over to our actual servlet
and then our servlet's gonna actually read that information.
So, let me go ahead and open up my servlet,
my StudentControllerServlet.
And let me move down to my doGet method
and here we're actually going to add support
for the delete command.
So, this is where we would normally read the commands
and now we need to add a new case for delete.
So, very similar to all the code
we've created so far,
so case DELETE and then I'll say deleteStudent,
pass in a request and a response
and then do a break.
All right and again, just like before,
Eclipse will say hey,
I don't know about this method called deleteStudent
and so, we simply tell Eclipse
to create that method for us,
so we just hover over,
they give us the options,
we choose the option create method deleteStudent.
And by now we're just so used to Eclipse
creating code for us,
we're just really good friends now.
All right, so here's the method
that Eclipse just created, deleteStudent.
I'll remove the auto generated code
and I'll add a throws here,
so let me move to the end of this method declaration,
right before the curly brace,
I'll hit enter, right before the curly brace
to get it down to the next line with me
and then I'll say throws Exception
and again, we're following the same pattern
that we've used for all of our other code here
in this servlet, so throws Exception.
And by now you know my procedure,
you know my process,
writing some comments here to keep me on track,
so the first thing I do is read the student ID
from the form data,
then I delete the student from the database
and then finally, I send the user back
to the list students page.
So, this is my basic game plan here
for the deleteStudent method
that's in this servlet.
All right, rolling up my sleeves here,
writing some code,
so to read theStudentId,
I simply say request.getParameter("studentId"),
I assign that accordingly.
Then to actually delete the student
from a database, I'll make use of my studentDbUtil
and I'll say studentDbUtil.deleteStudent
and then I pass in that StudentId.
And again, you're used to this part of it,
send them back to the list students page,
we simply say listStudents
and we pass the request response,
so we're kind of in the rhythm
of how we develop applications now
and again, another part of our motion or rhythm here
is that Eclipse will give us an error message
saying hey, we don't know about this method
deleteStudent in the studentDbUtil.
Well, of course, this is all new code,
so again, we'll highlight it
and then we'll go down and we'll choose the option
create the method deleteStudent
and the studentDbUtil.
All right, so there we go,
Eclipse is creating more code for us.
So, we're inside of studentDbUtil right now
and there's the method that Eclipse just created for us
and what we have to do here
is we actually have to add the JDBC code
to delete the student,
so we'll have to write the low-level code
to interact with the database.
So, up top I'll set up throws Exception
for this method signature.
Again, following the pattern that we've used before,
I'll define some of my JDBC objects up front,
so I'm gonna need a connection,
I'll say myConn equals null
and I also need a prepared statement,
I'll call it myStatement and I'll set this one to null also.
And then I'll set up a try finally block
and this time I'll actually do this first
as opposed to last time.
If you recall from one of the previous videos
I didn't write all the code properly
and I had to go back and clean up.
Got a little messy, so I'll make sure I'm on track here,
so try finally up front,
now I write the comments here,
so the first thing here is converting the student ID
to an integer,
then we get a connection to the database,
next we create the SQL to actually delete the student,
then we prepare the statement,
we set up the params
and then finally, we execute the SQL statement
and that'll actually perform the delete on the database.
And in my cleanup section here
I need to clean up those JDBC objects that I used.
All right, so this is basically the game plan here
for this deleteStudent method.
Okay, so let's go ahead and dig in.
So, the first item of business here
is converting the student ID to an int,
so here I say int studentId equals
and I make use of that Integer.parseInt
to convert from a string to an int.
Then I get a connection to the database
by using myConn equals dataSource.getConnection.
Then we just write out the SQL for doing a delete,
so here I say delete from student
where ID equals and then we use
that question mark placeholder.
That's the placeholder that we use for prepared statements.
Now let's go ahead and prepare the statement
by saying myStatement equals myConn.prepareStatement.
Then I'll go ahead and set the params here
by saying myStatement.setint,
that's the first param,
so one, the actual studentId
so they know which student to delete
and then we can get busy here,
so here I'll say myStatement.execute
and that'll actually perform the operation
on the database and actually delete the student
from the database.
And then finally, we just clean up our JDBC code,
so we close myConn, myStatement
and since we didn't have a result set here,
we just pass in the value of null
and that's basically it.
So, that's the code here for deleteStudent.
And so, you've seen this pattern before,
so you're probably really close
at being able to write all this code yourself
'cause we've gone through a number of iterations
for this already.
So, making some really good progress here.
Alrighty, so we can save this
and go ahead and move back to our servlet,
so this is our servlet code
and this is in pretty good shape for right now,
so our deleteStudent,
we read the student ID,
we delete the student from the database
and we send them back to the list students page
and that's basically everything involved here
for deleting a student from the servlet's point of view.
Okay, well, let's go ahead and run this and test it out.
So, here, right click, Run As, Run on Server
and great, so here's the output of our application.
Let's go ahead and choose the Delete link
along the far right
and I'll choose it
for this first student here, Maxwell Apples.
So, I'll click on Delete,
and the system's going to prompt me,
this is the little JavaScript prompt.
Here I'll hit Cancel
and note, nothing happened on the app
which is good 'cause we canceled that operation
but let's go ahead and really delete the person
and hit OK.
So, now Maxwell Apples is gone,
I'll list refresh and he's no longer in our list of students
which is really good.
Let's try this again.
Let's see Mary or Andrew, let's see which one,
not sure and let's go ahead and delete Mary Private.
So, let's go ahead and delete Mary Private.
We'll click Delete and then we'll hit OK.
And now let's delete Andrew Whittaker
and then we'll hit OK.
So, great, so we just deleted three students,
we only have three left and this looks really good
but again, let's check the database
just to make sure this thing is really working.
So, I'll go ahead and move into MySQL
and I will move over to my database here,
web_student_tracker, I'll choose Tables,
I'll right click on student
and boom, really good,
we only have three students in our database,
so that Apples and Mary Private and Andrew Whittaker,
they're gone, they're deleted, poof, be gone.
All right, so this is good stuff.
I'm having too much fun here.
So, anyway this works out just fine,
so we wrote the code for deleting a student
and we went through it step by step.
We built it all from scratch
and hopefully you have a good feel
for how this process works
especially after doing it for like a third or fourth time.
So, again, I'm happy, we've made some really good progress,
you can pat yourself on the back
and good job.