Hey, in this video we're going to look
at the list student feature.
So, basically in the following set of videos we're
going to write all the code to list the students.
So, we're going to talk to the database,
get a list of students, and then we're going to create
this very pretty table of our data,
and I'll show you how to do all of this from scratch.
So, we'll just drill down, we'll take it one step at a time,
and we'll work through it.
So speaking of steps, you know how I love to do lists.
So, I'm going to break this down into four main steps.
So the first step is creating a student class,
student dot java.
Then we're going to create our student database utility.
Next, we're going to create our controller servlet.
And then finally we'll wrap it up all together
with our final JSP page.
Alright so that's the big picture, let's go ahead
and dive in and let's start writing some code, yeah.
Alright so moving into Eclipse, we're going to use that
project that we've been using already, web student tracker.
And the first thing we want to do is create this
student dot java class, it's simply just a Java class
that's going to hold the student's first name,
last name and email address.
So, I'm moving to this Java resources directory,
move to my package, and I'll simply do a right click
and I'll say new Java class.
Alright so that brings up the dialog here,
for the name of the class it's simply student,
and once you're happy with that then go ahead
and click on the finish button.
Alright so we have this very basic student class here,
nothing's here, so let's go ahead and define four fields.
So, I'll need a field for the student id,
and then I'll also add fields here for the student's
first name, last name, and also email address.
So, this is the basic data that we want to
you know keep track of when we're building our application.
Okay great, so now we want to create some constructors,
and we'll actually create two constructors,
I'll actually make use of Eclipse to help me out
with creating the constructors.
So first I'll do a right click, I'll go to source and
I'll choose generate constructor using fields.
And Eclipse will pop up a dialog asking me which fields
to initialize, make sure they're all selected here
with the check boxes, and then we'll go ahead
and click on the finish button.
So this will give me a constructor for all of the fields,
right, so this is really cool, Eclipse created all this
code for us automatically.
Alright, and I'll just remove line 11, we don't need that,
and this is basically our constructor.
Now I want to add one more constructor here.
So I'll right click, I'll say source, generate constructor
using fields, and I want to create a version of the
constructor that doesn't use the id, so I'll simply
deselect or uncheck the box for id, but I'll keep
the others for first name, last name, and email address,
because there's certain scenarios where we don't have
the id or we don't need the id for our student.
Alright so make sure your screen looks like this,
and keep all the other defaults, and then go ahead
and click on the ok button.
Alright, so that's the new constructor that Eclipse
just created for us, which is really cool,
first name, last name, and email.
I'll take out that line for the for the super,
and then here's our other guy, so we're good to go.
So, we have two constructors now, we have two different
ways of creating this student class,
okay so this looks really good so far.
Now what I'd like to do is go through and create getter
and setter methods for this class.
So again, make use of Eclipse, I'll do a right click,
choose source, and go to generate getters and setters.
Eclipse will bring up this dialog, and again we go
through and select all the items here, for email,
first name, id, and last name.
Make sure they're all selected, keep all of the
other defaults, and then go ahead and click
on the okay button.
Okay cool, so Eclipse created a lot of getter and setter
methods for us, and again this is really fun that
Eclipse is generating code for us, I love that.
Now, one last thing I want to do is add a toString method.
So, I'll simply do a right click here, I'll choose source
and then I'll say generate toString.
The toString method is very useful for debugging
and logging information.
So, here I make sure that we have all the fields selected
id, first name, last name, and email, and I'll keep
all the other defaults, and then I hit ok.
So again, if I need to do some debugging or logging
on this application, by having the toString method
we can easily get a dump of the students information
without having to manually do it ourselves,
so this is good, so we're in good shape here.
So that's it, that's our student class that we had
four fields that we created, id, first name, last name,
and email, we created constructors, and then we also
created getters and setters, and finally toStrings.
This is kind of like some basic house keeping
that we needed to take care of, but we're in really
good shape now, so good job.