Alright, so we've completed the first item
on our to-do list, we created our Student.java class.
Now we're gonna focus on creating
our Database Utility Class.
So, again, moving back into Eclipse,
the first thing I wanna do is create the shell
or structure here for this Class,
so I'll simply do a right-click
and I'll say New, Class.
And the name for this Class, I'll call it StudentDbUtil,
and I'll keep all the other defaults here on this screen
and I'll click on the Finish button.
Okay, great, so a very basic shell of a Class right now,
StudentDbUtil,
and this is where we need to write some cool code here.
So, the first thing we wanna do is
set up a reference to a DataSource,
so I'll just simply say private DataSource dataSource
and I'll fix the imports here, javax.sql.
Alright, so that's good.
Now we need to set up a Constructor for this Class,
so here I'll say StudentDbUtil.
Remember, the Constructor had the same name as the Class.
I'll say StudentDbUtil, pass in theDataSource,
and I simply assign it.
So, here I'll say dataSource equals theDataSource.
So, theDataSource is the parameter being passed
into this Constructor and that's basically it.
So, we're gonna have somebody
that'll create this StudentDbUtil
and they'll pass in a reference to our dataSource object.
And actually, our Servlet will kinda do this work,
but we'll see that in a following video.
Alright, now the main thing in this StudentDbUtil is
that we're gonna have a method
that's actually gonna list the students,
so let me just kinda write the shell here
or the outline here for the method.
We're gonna have a method called getStudents
and throws Exception, possibly,
and here we have a return type of List&lt;Students&gt;,
so we're gonna get a list of students from a database
and then we'll return that.
So, that's the main method that we're gonna create here
in this Database Utility.
Let me go ahead and fix the imports here,
so java.utl.list,
and let me just kinda stub out some basic code here
to get things lined up.
So, I'll create this ArrayList students.
Right now it's empty
and then I'll say return students.
So, right now I'm just kinda stubbing things out.
In the middle, on line 18,
we're gonna write a lot of code
that'll actually populate that ArrayList,
but for now, I'm just kinda stubbing it out,
just so we can kinda see the big picture here
for this method.
Alright, so this method is gonna do
some database work using JDBC,
so I'll just set up some JDBC objects right now,
set them to null,
and then we'll make use of them a little later here
in this method.
So, I'll set up myConn, myStmt,
and also set up my ResultSet,
and we'll set all these values to null for right now.
And then also, I'll use my Eclipse trick again
to fix the imports here,
so remember, you can go to the Source menu
and you can say Source, Organize Imports,
and this'll basically help you
import the appropriate Classes
and Interfaces, and so on.
So, here I'll choose java.sql.Statement, click Next,
and I'll do a similar thing here
for java.sql.Connection,
and then it'll resolve the result set automatically
and so, that takes care of those errors,
so that looks really good so far.
Alright, so now let's kinda roll out sleeves up
and let's get down here.
So, again, I always like to drop in some comments here,
just to kinda give myself a clue
as far as what I need to do
before I should start writing some real code.
So here, I wanna get a connection first,
I wanna create a sql statement,
then I wanna execute the query,
and then process the result set,
so kinda a similar thing,
what we did in the Test Servlet,
but here we're kinda just doing it
in a more formal fashion here.
And then also, close any of the JDBC objects.
So, that's kinda the big picture,
the main outline
for this method that we're gonna write.
A lot of this code, I'll place inside of a try block
and I'll make use of a finally
to kinda help me clean up some of the JDBC objects,
but we'll flesh that out in a bit,
so let me kinda tab this in.
Let's see, that return students,
I actually wanna move that up a bit,
so let me just grab that line 42
and cut and paste it
and put it right here near the end
of that try block.
Alright, okay, that looks good.
Okay, so now we can start cutting some code here,
so let's get busy.
So, the first thing here is getting a connection,
so here I'll say myConn equals dataSource.getConnection.
Now it'll basically give me a connection
to the database
and actually, give me a connection from
that connection pool.
Remember, dataSource is our ConnectionPool.
Create a sql statement here
and select star from students,
and I'm gonna order by last_name,
so when I get the data from the database,
I want it to be ordered by
or sorted by the student's last name.
I simply create a sql statement object here,
so I'll say myStmt equals myConn.createStatement.
Alright, so that's the basic process here.
Now let's go ahead and execute our query,
so I'll have myRs equals myStmt.executeQuery
and then I pass in that sql String
that I just created a little earlier.
So this will give me a result set.
Now, kinda for the heavy lifting here,
processing a result set,
so we need to go through the loop
and perform some operations
and build up our list.
Alright, so here I'll say while myRs.next,
basically looping through this result set,
then I'll perform some operations.
And again, since we have a lot of work
to do inside of this while loop,
I'll kinda write some comments here,
just to kinda keep us on track.
The first thing we need to do is retrieve data
from the result set row.
Based on that information,
we're gonna create a new student object
and then we're gonna add it to our list of students.
Alright, so that's the basic idea
or outline here for this while loop.
Alrighty, so let's go ahead
and grab the student id from the result set,
so I'll say myRs.getInt id,
and so id in quotes is the actual column name.
I'll also grab the firstName,
so I'll say myRs.getString first_name,
and again, that's the actual column name from the database.
And then I'll just repeat the process here for lastName
and also for email address.
Okay, great, so now that I have the data off of the row,
now I can use that to create a new student object,
so I'll make use of my Student Constructor
that I created earlier
and I'll say tempStudent equals new Student
and I pass in the id,
firstName, lastName, and email address.
So, that'll create a new student object based on
that one row from the result set.
And then I simply wanna add it to my list of students,
so I'll say students.add and I'll give that tempStudent.
So, basically what we'll do in this loop is we'll just
keep processing a result set
and adding those to our list.
Now, you may wonder, well,
where is students, that list of students?
Where'd that come from?
Well, just scrolling up to the top of this method here,
when we first started out we created this
ArrayList of students,
and right now it's empty when we first start out
and then as we go through this for loop
or this while loop here, we're gonna populate it
and keep adding more students to that list.
So, here's the while loop.
Again, we basically retrieve data
from the result set row,
we create the student object,
and we add it to the list of students.
And we just keep doing that
for each element there in our result set.
Now, in a previous video,
when we did our little Test Servlet,
I told you it was kinda quick and dirty,
but here I actually wanna close some
of our JDBC objects,
so here make use of best practices,
kinda clean up after ourselves.
So, whenever we make use of JDBC objects,
we need to close them,
like closing the result set, the statement,
and also, the connection,
and we don't wanna just hold onto them forever
'cause we'll eventually have a memory leak
and we'll run out of statements, cursors,
or run out of connections.
So here, I'm gonna call a method here, close,
myConn, myStmt, and myRs.
Now, Eclipse says, hey, buddy,
you have a problem here.
There's no method in its Class called close.
So, then I'll say, alright Eclipse,
well, why don't you create it for me?
Get to work.
(laughs)
So, this is cool, so if there's a method that's not defined,
you can tell Eclipse to create that method
and they'll basically stub it out
for you automagically, which is kinda cool,
and then inside of this method,
I can go ahead and do my real work.
Alright, so Eclipse created the shell of this method
or the stub of this method
and I'll go ahead and write some code here.
So, I'll just set up a little try catch block
and what I wanna do inside of this try block is,
I basically wanna close each one
of those elements there, or objects,
so I'm gonna close the result set, statement,
and myConn.
So, the first this I do is I check
to make sure that those objects are not null,
so if the myRs is not null,
then I'll say myRs.close.
Alright, so that'll close the result set.
And then I'll do a similar thing here for statement,
so if myStmt is not equal to null,
then I'll say myStmt.close.
And then, I'll do a similar thing here for my connection,
so if myConn's not equal to null,
then I'll say myConn.close.
Now, one thing about myConn is
that it doesn't really close the database connection,
all it does is basically
puts it back into the connection pool.
Kinda makes it available for someone else to use,
so they're kinda marking it as available now
because our connection pool
kinda keeps all those connections open,
but they simply hand them out
to people who really wanna use them or whatever.
So, kinda like when you rent a car
or hire a car, you use it and then you return it,
and then the company will make it available
for someone else to use,
so that's the idea here,
so don't get too concerned about line 76.
They simply make the connection available
for someone else to use.
Alright, but it's really important
that you handle this clean-up work
because if you don't, in a production application,
you could run into problems if you don't
close your result set or statements.
Over time, maybe a couple of days
or a couple of weeks,
you'll eventually run out of some resources,
so make sure you make use of that close technique.
Alright, so that's pretty much it
in our Student Database UTL.
So, we have this method, getStudents,
that's gonna return a list of student objects,
and we kinda went through the basic process
of making this happen.
We created an empty list of students,
got a connection, SQL query,
and then we processed the result set.
And then finally, on line 55,
we actually returned the actual list of students
to whoever called it,
so that's the most important thing there.
So, that's it for our StudentDbUtil
as far as listing students,
so this looks really good so far
and our Servlet will actually make use
of this Database UTL to get data from the database.
So, good job so far with this work.