Alright, so we just finished
the coding for our student database util.
Now let's go ahead and move over to our controller servlet.
It's gonna handle the initial request
and then talk to that utility and send it to a JSP.
Alright, so this is our servlet here.
So, let's move into Eclipse and
let's move over to our source code package.
And we're gonna create a new class.
Or we're actually gonna create a new servlet.
So, New Servlet.
And the name of our servlet,
we'll call it StudentControllerServlet.
And then we'll go ahead and click on the next button.
And we'll keep the defaults here.
We'll simply click on Next.
And we'll uncheck the item
for Constructors and uncheck the doPost.
And we'll keep the others here.
So make sure your screen matches mine
and then go ahead and click on the finish button.
Okay, great.
So, Eclipse has a very basic servlet here for us.
Let's go ahead and you know,
add some good functionality here.
So, stretch out, get some white space.
And the first thing we'll do
is we'll set up a reference to a studentDbUtil.
We haven't assigned it yet, we'll assign it later.
And then, I also wanna make use of that
Java EE resource injection so they can
inject that data source for me.
So I have @Resource(name="jdbc/web_student_tracker").
And again, we covered this in the
test video a little bit earlier.
So, the Tomcat server will actually
inject that connection pool object
and assign it here to this variable data source.
So let me go ahead and fix up some of these imports here
for javax.annotation.Resource.
And again with data source make sure
you get the right one here.
So javax.sql.DataSource because there's others out there,
make sure you got the right one.
Alright so javax.sql.DataSource, boom.
Now what we actually wanna do is,
we wanna initialize this StudentdbUtil
and in the servlet life cycle they have a special
method that you can override called init.
So this init method will be called
by the app server when this servlet is initialized.
So here I'll go to source
and then I'll say, Override/Implement Methods.
So we're gonna override a method that we inherit
and we're gonna add our own custom functionality to it.
So we extend off of HttpServlet but we actually want
to override a method that we inherit
from our parent, parent GenericServlet.
And there's a method here called init.
So there's an init method with no arguments
and that's the one that we wanna select.
So make sure that you check the box here for this one.
And then go ahead and click the OK button.
So again this init method is actually
called by the Java EE server or by Tomcat
when this servlet is first loaded or initialized.
So this is a good place for you to put your own custom
initialization work, inside of this init method.
And this is part of the spec, part of the API.
So work that you would normally do on a constructor
when you're working with servlets, you would normally
put it inside of the init method.
So what we want to do here, is we want to create
an instance of our student database util
and pass in our datasource object.
Alright so it's really simple here,
we just hook this trycatch block.
So here I say, studentDbUtil = new StudentDbUtil
and then we pass in dataSource.
Okay and so let me scroll back up
so we can kinda connect the dots here.
So studentDbUtil is a data member that we've defined
and we're assigning it here on line 31
and then dataSource is that resource injection item,
our connection pool and we're passing it in right here.
So that'll actually create our studentDbUtil.
Then here I'll just say catch exception,
if there were any exceptions
with creating that database util.
Then I'll say, throw new ServletException.
So you know maybe for some reason our database
wasn't up and running or I don't know,
some weird permissions problem.
We'll just throw this servlet exception
and it'll show it in the browser.
Alright and that's it, so that's our init method.
So again work that you would normally do on a constructor,
when you work with servlets you place that code
inside of the init method and something that we inherit
from generic servlet and we can override it
and add our own custom functionality.
Alright, good job.
Alright so let's go ahead and move into this doGet method
and let's start doing some more coding here.
So we did all of our initialization work up top,
now let's just dive into doGet and you know
handle that request that's coming in.
So I'll go ahead and clear out some of the docs,
some of the auto-generated stuff.
And now this is where we're gonna kinda write
some of our code for this doGet method of this servlet.
So basically what we wanna do in this doGet method
is that we wanna list the students in MVC fashion.
So we wanna get the data, set the attribute
and then use that request dispatcher
and send it over to the JSP.
So that's kind of the game plan here
and what I'll do is I'll actually just define
a little helper method to do this for me.
So I'll have this method called listStudents
and I'll pass in that request object and a response.
And just to kind of, you know, do some clean coding here,
some best practices of kinda lining this up.
So listStudents but again Eclipse says, hey dude (laughs)
you don't have a method.
And I'll say, alright Eclipse create it for me.
So I'll just choose this option here,
create this method, listStudents.
Again really nice feature of Eclipse,
I like to have Eclipse help me out and write some code.
So they basically stub the code out for us
and then we need to go in and do our work.
Alright so I'll remove that auto-generated comment
and I'll put in my own personal comments,
just to kinda help me out and keep me
on track with what I need to do.
So I know the first thing I need to do
is get the students from our database util.
Then I need to add those students to that request object
as an attribute and then finally I need to send it
to the JSP page, our view page,
using that request dispatcher.
So again this is the basic approach
that we're gonna take here in this listStudents method.
Alright so I kinda stretched out,
gave us a lot of white space to play around with here.
And I'll say list students
= studentDbUtil.getStudents.
And that's the method that we created in
that previous video right?
So we did all the low level JDBC work
and now we're simply calling that method
and we're getting a list of objects.
So really good job there.
And then again, go ahead
and fix my import statement here for a list.
So make sure you choose java.util.List.
Make sure you get the right one,
because there's a number of different options out there.
So java.util.List.
And now I wanna add the students to the request,
so like we've learned before we say, request.setAttribute.
We give an attribute name and then
we give the actual object that we're setting.
So here I'll call it STUDENT_LIST.
That's the actual name I'll use for this attribute.
And then the actual object, well that's the list
of students from line 49, so I'll say students.
So again when you set an attribute, you set the actual
attribute name and then the actual value
or the object reference.
So that takes care of that part of it.
And then finally we set up our RequestDispatcher
because we want to send data over to that JSP page.
So again I say dispatcher = request.getRequestDispatcher,
ah that's a mouthful.
And I give the name of a JSP page, list-students.jsp.
So again this basically sets up a handle for that
and then I give dispatcher.forward and then I pass in
that request object and also that response object.
So we've seen this before in some of
our previous videos of doing MVC work.
So I have some exceptions here that I need
to kind of address and figure out
the best way of doing this.
And what I'll do here is I'll actually modify
this listStudents method to actually
throw a give an exception.
So instead of handling it here locally in this method,
I wanna throw it to the calling program
so they can kinda handle it in one central location.
So I'll modify the signature here for my listStudents.
So I'll move over and I'll grab right there,
yeah that angle bracket and I'll say throws Exception.
So at this level we don't have to worry
about handling the exceptions we're gonna
throw it to the calling program.
Now if we scroll up a little bit we'll notice
that Eclipse will show us a new error, okay?
So on line 43 it says, hey you know,
there's an error, an unhandled exception
because that listStudents throws an exception.
Alright fine, no problem I'll just wrap this
in a try catch block and we'll handle it in that fashion.
So try catch and I'll say catch Exception exc
and then I'll say throw new ServletException
and I just simply wrap the exception.
So it'll get thrown back
and the exception will appear in the browser.
We could always customize this a bit
and add more elegant error tracking
but let's kinda go with this for now
and we can do some other logging in future videos.
But that's the basic idea here.
So on our doGet method we call listStudents,
it'll do its work and get our data
and then forward it over to the JSP.
So that's the main idea, the main outline here for this
listStudents and here's the listStudents method again.
Getting the data from the database util,
adding it to the request and then
sending it over to the JSP object.
So this looks really, really good.
Very pretty, I like it.
Okay great, so I hope this is all kinda comin together
for you, you know, we're kinda doin this step by step.
You've seen a lot of these steps in previous videos
but now we're really hooking it together
with a real database.
So in the next video we'll jump forward
and then we'll talk about making use of the JSP page.
So I'll see yah in the next video, alright.