Alright, so we have our
controller servlet completed.
Let's go ahead and focus in on our JSP page now.
So in our project, in our WebContent folder,
let's go ahead and create a new file for our JSP.
So I'll right-click, I'll say: new, file.
and for the name of the file;
I'll call it "list-students.jsp".
And once I'm happy with that I'll hit okay,
and now we have this empty file here,
and we need to go ahead and add some information to it.
So the first thing we need to do is our JSP's gonna make
use of some Java packages so I need to do an import.
So I need to import java dot util dot star,
because I'm gonna use--
list an array list,
and also some of my own custom classes from my package;
com.Luv2code.web.jdbc.*
So this is basically just an import for two packages,
and then remember in JSP
we can import multiple packages
by giving a comma with unlimited list of package names.
Alright, so we have the packages here,
now I'll just do my very basic HTML
setup work, so I'll set up my HTML head,
and I'll set up my HTML body.
Alright, so we have our general HTML housekeeping
taken care of.
Let me just set up a title here for this page;
I'll call it: Student Tracker App.
Alright, so that parts taken care of.
Now, what I wanna do is actually make use of that
request object and use some of its data.
So I'll set up a JSP scriptlet
and I want to get the
list of students from that request attribute that was
passed over by the servlet.
So I know the servlet has a list of students
that it put into that request object
so I'll simply say: theStudents equals
and then I'll retrieve that information and I'll downcast
it, so I'll say: List Student
and I'll say request dot get attribute
and I'll give the attribute name that was used by
the servlet. So it's: student underscore list.
And that will give me a handle to the students.
Now, I always like to go into the servlet source code
and just verify that I have the correct attribute name
so I'll swing back over to the servlet source code
for my student controller servlet,
and I'll move down to the section
where we did our request dispatcher and here we go,
great. So this line's 58 and 59.
This is where we set the students and
the request attribute and note here what's highlighted:
Student underscore list. So that's the same attribute name.
So, just make sure you follow that pattern there.
Student underscore list.
Good.
So now we have the list of students.
So let me stretch out and get some white space here.
And now what I always like to do is just a very simple
proof of concept, that hey, we can get the data.
So, before I get into displaying the actual
HTML table, I just want to dump out those students,
just so it can print the information to the browser,
just to make sure that hey,
we can actually get some data.
And the output will be ugly,
but at least we can verify that we have data
right now from that servlet.
So let me go ahead and run this servlet,
so student controller servlet,
right-click.
I'll choose run as, and I'll choose run on server.
Alright, so here's the output, so our servlet just ran
so again, remember our servlet talks to the database util
gets that list of students,
forwards it over to the JSP
and right now our JSP is just very simple.
We're just dumping out the list of students,
and again, it's really really ugly right now.
(laughs)
But don't worry, we'll actually get into all the
HTML table stuff. Again, I just like to make sure that
we can get the data and we can get it to the JSP.
Now, this is just more of a-- making things
look pretty inside the house right now, that's all.
Alright, so let's go ahead and move back into our JSP.
And now we actually want to build the HTML table.
And so I'll kinda work on my HTML page.
We'll actually make use of some style sheets a little later
on, but for now, I'll go ahead and just kinda lay out
some of the content here for this HTML page
and we'll apply some styles in the following video.
Alright, so here I'll just set up some div's.
So div's are basically just little containers or
placeholders for putting information or
managing information on an HTML page.
So we're going to use style sheets later,
so I'm just going to make use of some div's
for the wrapper, for the header.
So our header will show up, h2 as: Foobar University
and again, stretch out, get some white space here.
Then I'll go ahead and start working on
my main content div.
So this is my container here.
And then the div for this one will be: content,
and again, we'll apply-- CSS styles for these
given items, but for now, we're just laying it out.
The main part here is just focusing on
building out our table. So we want to have an
HTML table that'll give the students:
First name, last name and email address.
So to handle that, I'll first-- in my table here,
I'll set up a table-row and I'll set up a table header
so just so we can see the actual headers here,
for the table.
So again, we'll have: first name,
and I just copy/paste this line.
And then paste that a couple of times here,
and then here, we'll have it for last name,
and then we'll also have it for email.
Okay, great. So this takes care of our headers right now
for our HTML table. So this looks good so far.
Now, what I wanna do is, move down a bit,
and then I actually loop through that list of students
and put this information in different table rows.
So here I'll just do a "for" loop, I'll say:
student, temp student. Colon, the students.
Now the students; you may wonder well where did
that come from? Well that's the variable that we
set up earlier in this JSP page.
So on line 11, we have "the students";
that's the list that we retrieved from that
request attribute. So that's the list of students
that we're looping over right now.
So I just have my open curly brace and my close
curly brace, and then basically inside of this loop
this is where we're gonna print out the students
first name, last name and email address.
So I'll set up a table row for this
and then I'll set up table data.
So table data,
I'll make use of a JSP expression, so angle bracket, percent
with an equal, and I'll say
temp student dot get first name.
So that'll get me the first name for the student
and then I'll copy this line and I'll paste it
a couple of times here,
and so here I'll have a
get last name, and then also get email.
Alright, good, so there's the email portion of it.
So that's basically the looping portion here
for our table.
So this looks really good,
so here's our table, we have our table headers up top
and then we looped that list of students
and we print out the first name, last name and
email address. So this looks really, really good.
I'm excited about this right now.
Alright so, let's save it and let's test it out.
So all I have to do is go back to my previous
screen here, my browser screen here for the servlet
and all I have to do is simply reload.
Remember with JSP's if you change it,
there's no need to re-run the code,
you simply just refresh and there you go,
so bam! I love this.
So here's our table for FooBar University,
we have our five students listed out,
so this is really, really cool
so we have this information in tabular data.
Now, it's a little ugly right now
(laughs)
the table is kinda plain, it's kinda blah,
it doesn't really match the screenshots we had earlier.
But don't worry,
in the following video, I'll show you how to apply
Cascading Style Sheets to this table,
to make it look pretty.
To make it look beautiful.
(laughs)
Alright, So I'm having a lot of fun here.
So, in the next video, we'll cover CSS
and I'll show you how to apply those styles
in our JSP page.
Alright, I'll see you soon.