Okay, great.
So we're making some really good progress right now.
We have this table, but it's kinda ugly,
and what we wanna do is make it pretty.
Like I said earlier, make it beautiful.
So we're gonna make use of cascading style sheets for this.
Now, we actually have a cascading style sheet
that's available in our starter files.
So I'm gonna move back over to my directory,
where I extracted all of my sample code,
and then there's a directory here
called web student tracker starter files.
So let's go ahead and expand that folder
and web content, then there's a folder here
called CSS, for cascading style sheets.
So, we already have a CSS file that's already created.
So, let's go ahead and select this file.
Right click and choose copy.
Alright, so we have this file copied.
Let's move back into Eclipse, and in Eclipse
what we wanna do is create a new folder
for our cascading style sheets.
So we do a right click, we say new folder,
and this is under web content,
a new folder called CSS.
So, web content, CSS.
So we'll hit finish, and now we have
this new CSS folder that's underneath web content.
Now, this is the folder that we'll paste our file,
so we simply go right click and choose paste.
Now, for the CSS file, you could really
put it anywhere that you want.
I'm just putting it here in the CSS folder
just for organization, but you could put it
in any directory at any location that you want
underneath web content.
Alright, so here's our styles CSS.
Now, full disclaimer, I'm not a CSS guru.
I normally have a friend help me out with CSS,
or I normally find examples on the web
and kinda copy paste, so I'm not a graphic designer.
But, anyway, this is a basic CSS
that can kinda help us out.
Now, let's use the CSS in our JSP page.
This is a common question, like how do we use a CSS
in a JSP page?
So, again, assuming we have the CSS file already created,
then in our JSP page it's just like an HTML page, right?
So, to use CSS in HTML, you simply put it
the head, same thing here for JSP.
So we set the link type, text slash CSS,
We give the rel of style sheet,
and then we give the href to where
the style sheet's located, so right?
So we created this directory called CSS
and we had a file here called style dot CSS,
and that's basically a reference there
to the style sheet.
So, CSS slash style dot CSS, and that's
the directory that we have here
as part of our project under web content,
CSS, style dot CSS.
Now, that style sheet has rules,
and I've applied those rules to this actual HTML content,
or this JSP page, and then that will give us
a pretty output here.
So, some of the rules relate to,
I'll kinda scroll down here in a second,
so we have styles here for wrapper,
we have styles for header.
We also have styles in that sheet
for container and content.
You can go back and dig into the style sheet
to look at all of those styles.
But, anyway, that's that.
It's in place.
We're ready to go.
So, then we can go back to our student tracker,
click the refresh button, and boom, wow.
This is great.
So, isn't this great?
So we had a very basic, ugly HTML table,
and by simply adding CSS styles, now it's pretty.
It's beautiful.
It's lovely.
Alrighty, so as you can see I'm having a lot of fun here,
'cause I'm really excited.
We accomplished some really, really good stuff here.
So, anyway, that's kind of full-circle.
So we have the list of students feature working.
In the following videos we'll go and add
some more functionality.
But for now, take a break, pat yourself on the back,
job well done.