Hi, in this video we're gonna add JSTL support
to our classroom project.
So far we've built our MVC framework
but you may have noticed when I was writing the code for
the JSP, that I made use of Scriptlet code.
ohh
And you may have wondered 'Why not add JSTL?'
So, you may remember from some previous sessions
I covered JSTL and how the best practice is to replace
Scriptlet code with JSTL tags,
um so I think that I should follow my own advice here.
Or, I should practice what I preach.
So in this video we will actually replace our
JSP Scriptlet code with JSTL.
And, you know how I love To Do lists here.
So what we're gonna do in step one is that
we're gonna add our JSTL JAR files to our project.
Then we'll go through and we'll update our JSP page
to make use of the JSTL tags,
and in particular we'll make use of the &lt;c:forEach&gt; tag
And that's really all we have to do
all the servlet and database code stays the same,
we're simply updating the JSP page.
Alright so lets go ahead and move into Eclipse.
So the first step is adding
the JSTL JAR files to our project
Now we're going to add these files
into our WEB-INF/lib directory, and
remember the WEB-INF/lib directory is a special directory
where you place any third party JAR files.
So, as you see we're making use of this JDBC driver
and its already there in our lib directory.
So now we want to add the JSTL JAR files.
So I'll swing over to my finder or explorer here,
and moving back to the code we downloaded
earlier in the course, we have a directory here
for web student tracker starter files.
So I'll expand the directory down to WebContent/WEB-INF/lib
and in this directory we have two JAR files that we need.
We have two JSTL JAR files,
so what you should do is go ahead
and select both of those files,
do a right click and choose copy,
coz those are the files that we want.
Okay, great. So those files are copied
now lets move back over to the Eclipse and
in Eclipse we want to place this information into
the WebContent/WEB-INF/lib directory
and then simply do a right click and choose paste.
Okay, this looks really good now.
So we should have those two new JAR files for JSTL
in our WEB-INF/lb directory.
So this is really good,
so we're kind set up now with step one
so we've added those JAR files and we're ready to go.
Alright, so moving forward here on the next step
we want to update our JSP page
to make use of those JSTL tags.
So let me go ahead and open my file list-students.jsp
Currently we have Scriptlet code here
we're gonna make some modifications to this file.
So the first thing want to do is, on line one,
I want to move or delete this line of doing the page import
When we're using JSTL we don't have to any
imports here of java class libraries.
So I'll delete that file.
And now what I'm gonna do, is add in the reference here
for the JSTL tag libs for core.
So I just did a copy paste here,
you can go ahead and type it in,
just pause the video and type it in,
but I always like to make sure I get this right
because the uri has to match exactly or else
everything else will fall apart.
So make sure you get the first line correct here.
Okay so then we can move down
So we have this section of code here for a Scriptlet
where we would retrieve the object
from other request attributes.
We're actually gonna delete this because we don't have to
use it when we make use of JSTL
so JSTL will do a lot of this work for us
behind the scenes.
So lines 12 through 16 I can simply highlight them
and just hit the delete key.
And, boof! Goes away.
(chuckles)
Alright, now lets scroll on down here
and the next thing we want to do here is we actually
want to replace our Scriptlet code with JSTL &lt;c:forEach&gt;.
So on line 32, instead of having a normal
for loop using Scriptlet code, I'm going to have a JSTL tag.
And, I'm going to put in here for the JSTL &lt;c:forEach&gt; tag.
Then I'll grab the end tag and I'll move it down to line 42
Actually, line 41,
and I'll place it right there
just so we have a start for each tag
and an end for each tag.
Now I need to go ahead and flesh out some items here
so var="tempStudent", that's our temporary variable we use
when we go through the loop.
And then items='' will actually be the attribute name
of the data.
So this is the same attribute name
that was set by the Servlet STUDENT_LIST
so this JSTL tag they'll actually go into that
request attribute, or sorry,
they'll actually go into that request object
get the attribute called STUDENT_LIST
and then make it available.
So they'll do a lot of the work for us behind the scenes
which is a nice feature here of JSTL.
Alright great, so now what I'm gonna do here
is replace my
JSP Scriptlet expressions here
and I'll replace it with a JSP expression language
So, that's the dollar sign curly brace
and you simply give the object name dot the property name.
So here I have tempStudent.firstName
so then I'll just copy this line
and I'll simply paste it for all the others real quick
so I'll just copy this
and then I'll just paste it here for lastName
and I'll paste it here for email.
And I'll go through and do a quick update here,
so tempStudent.lastName
and I'll do tempStudent.email.
So as a reminder,
when we use this JSP expression langauge,
remember that it will actually call tempStudent.getemail
so it will actually call your getter method here for email.
So tempStudent.getemail,
it will do a similar thing for firstName, lastName and so on
So that's basically our for-loop now
so instead of using JSP Scriptlet here
we're making use of the JSTL tags
and making use of the &lt;c:forEach&gt; tags.
So, just kinda cleaned it up a bit.
Not much of a big deal there.
Alright so lets go ahead and try this out and run it.
So I need to go back and run my actual
Servlet here, our controller servlet.
So, move back up my java resources.
Right click on that StudentControllerServlet.java
And then select Run As, and then Run on Server.
And break.
So that's the output, so again no surprises here
everything is going to work exactly the same,
the only difference is that we simply modified
our JSP page to make use of JSTL.
But to the end user, no real difference,
everything still looks fine,
everything still looks beautiful our beautiful table again.
Alright so that covers it here, we went through and we
took our JSP Scriptlet code, removed it
and we replaced it with JSTL tags
So good job so far and good job for following best practices
Including myself
(chuckles)
Alright, see you in the next video.