Hi, I this video we're gonna learn
about adding welcome files with servlets.
So currently, in order to access our MVC application
we have to explicitly call the servlet URL.
So we give localhost, web student tracker,
slash student controller servlet
and that's fine for development and testing
but not really good for real world development
or real world deployment.
So, what I'd like to do is make things
just a little bit simpler
by simply just giving the URL to the web app
without having to explicitly call the servlet.
So, I'd like to take this URL
and be able to share it with somebody
without getting into all the gory details
of student control or servlet.
So, what you can do is make use of a feature
with the Java servlets or web apps
where there's a deployment descriptor file
called web.xml and it has various configs
for application deployment.
So, one of the options available is welcome files.
So this will basically tell the server,
hey, if no one accesses a servlet or file directly,
then go look for these welcome files
and serve those up instead.
So, basically it's gonna look for a welcome file
and it'll look for that welcome file in your web.xml file.
So you have this welcome file list
and you'll have a list of files.
Now, it's actually gonna search these files top down,
So it'll come through.
It'll say hey is there an index.html.
If so, it'll serve it up.
You can add as many welcome files here as you'd like.
You can also add references to servlets here
and this is what it'll look for
as far as a welcome file if the URL doesn't have
an explicit file reference.
So this is kind of cool.
So that's kind of the theory,
let's swing into Eclipse and let's try this out.
So first off before we get into coding
I just wanna show you what'll happen here
if we don't have a file reference.
So, note the URL, I have the big, long URL
with student controller servlet.
I'm gonna simply take that off
and just try and access my app directly
and I'll just hit the enter button.
And ugh yucky, we have this 404 error.
So basically it wasn't able to find a resource
because right now, this web app
doesn't have any welcome files to find or configure.
So, we need to fix that.
So in order to fix it,
we first need to add a web.xml file to our project
and configure it properly.
So I'll move back into our starter files.
I'll move into this directory here, WEB-INF
and I'll select this file web.xml.
I'll do a right click and I'll copy this file.
Then I'll move back over to Eclipse
and then I'll actually paste this file
into my WEB-INF directory.
So I'll paste it into WebContent/WEB-INF.
So that's the web.xml file.
And once I paste this new file here
I need to restart Tomcat,
just so it'll pick up these new configurations
for this project.
So you can just simply choose your Tomcat server,
right click, choose restart.
Alright, so WebContent, WEB-INF, web.xml,
double click it.
So here's the file that we had from the slides.
So basically it's just a web deployment descriptor
and it has those welcome files.
What I wanna do here is create a new welcome file
called index.html.
So I wanna solve the problem
that we were having a little earlier.
So, creating a new file, index.html.
Enter it here and once I'm happy with that file name,
I can go ahead and click on the finish button.
Okay great so blank file.
So let's just create a very simple html file
and with the body I'll set up just some very basic text,
Hello Brave New World.
Brave new world,
and I'll set up some h1 tags around it.
Alright, so just a very basic Hello World page.
Right, I'll save this file.
Now if I go back to my browser
I should be able to test this out.
So in my browser, instead of the 404 error,
if I click on reload for this URL,
then boom, good job.
So now I'm getting that html file that I just added
and that's because this index.html
that's listed as a welcome file
in my web.xml file.
So the system it went through looking for some file.
It looked for index.jsp, it didn't find it
and it looked for index.html, found one
and that's the file that it served up.
So this was working out really good.
So we have the basics going here for our welcome files.
So, good job so far.
But I really want more.
I don't want just the hello world,
I want my servlet, okay,
I want my student controller servlet.
So what I'll do is I'll actually add the servlet
as a welcome file.
So I'll simply grab the URL mapping for this servlet,
I'll copy it
and then I'll use that in that web.xml
for setting up a references to a welcome file.
So I'll move here into this web.xml
and I'll add a new entry here for our welcome file
and so instead of giving and actual file name
like a jsp or a html file,
I'll give the URL mapping of my servlet.
Student controller servlet
and it's listed first.
So it should pick that one up
before it makes it to the html page.
So just be careful on the order.
Remember it'll search for files top-down.
Again, go through and just refresh
or restart this Tomcat server
because we made some config changes to our web.xml file.
Alright, so now that Tomcat is restarted,
then I can go back into my browser
and test some things out.
So here I click on refresh
and booya,
now, note the URL is just web-student-tracker,
but behind the scenes it's automatically forwarding
or calling our student controller servlet.
So this looks great.
So there's no servlet reference in the URL.
But it's basically being served up,
processing all of our big MVC stuff
is working in the background
thanks to our database work.
So, this is great
so I just wanted to show you this little trick here
for making use of welcome files here
with the web.xml.
Alright, good job.