Hello, in this video
I'm gonna show you how to use session tracking with JSP.
Now, we'll cover the following topics.
First off, I'll give you a session tracking demo
and then we'll look at the session coding steps
and then finally, we'll pull it altogether
with a full JSP page example.
Now, for this video I'll actually break it up
into two separate videos,
I'll cover just the slides in part one
and then I'll get into the coding portion in part two.
All right, so what exactly is the JSP session object?
Well, the session object is created once
for a browser session and it's unique for a given user.
So, you commonly use this to keep track of a user's actions.
So, if you can think of like an online banking application
or a shopping cart application,
or maybe like an online exam application,
for every user that's accessing the web application,
you need to keep track of those unique actions
and those actions specific to that given user.
That's the idea of a session,
so I always say a session,
think of it as a shopping cart for a unique user.
Now, I'm gonna actually show you
a demo of using JSP sessions,
a very simple demo where we'll manage a to-do list.
A user will have a list of items
stored in the session and then each user
will have their own list for tracking
and I'll show it to you in a nice little demo
coming up here in a second.
All right, so here's our demo,
so I'm in my web browser.
Up top you can add new items to your list,
so think of it as like your to-do list for today
and you can just enter some items,
so here I'll say I need to go buy groceries
and I'll hit Submit.
That will add it to my list,
so right now that's in my session.
Next one here, go to the gym
and then I can just add some additional items here,
mail letters and so on.
You get the idea.
So, basically here this browser here
actually has a unique session
associated with it in the server's memory.
Now, let me bring in another browser here
just to simulate a different user,
so let me just kind of resize the window here,
so I have Firefox on the left
and I'll bring in a Chrome browser on the right.
All right, so here's my Chrome browser,
so Firefox on the left, Chrome on the right.
I go to that same URL,
I'll increase the font here for a second
and now in the Chrome browser on the right
I'll add some items also,
so again, remember, each browser user
has a unique session,
so here the first item I'll enter go running,
hit Submit and then another one here, repair bike
and so on and I can keep adding items.
So, the key here is that each browser
has its own unique session object in the background,
so it's almost like a shopping cart,
each user has their own shopping cart
and the system can keep track of it,
so I can go back over here on the left-hand side in Firefox,
since I'm recording all these Java videos,
I need to go off and record more videos,
so anyway, the basic idea here
is that each browser has a unique session object
on the Tomcat server in memory
and you can keep track of each user's individual actions,
so on the next slide here I'll show you
kind of how it works as far the big picture
and then we'll get into some of the coding portion of it.
All right, so here's the big picture.
So, you can have multiple users of your application.
They're all accessing maybe one JSP or whatever,
that JSP can make use of a session object,
so each user of the system
will have their own session object.
Now, a couple things here,
the session object is kept in memory,
so it's not stored on a database
or it's not stored on the file system,
it's only in your server's memory
like in the Tomcat server memory
and each user has their own session ID,
so the Tomcat server will actually assign
a session ID to the user
and Tomcat has its own algorithm for assigning
but the key thing is that you the developer
you don't have to worry about the session ID generation,
you also don't have to worry about passing
a session ID back and forth,
the Tomcat server and the browser will handle that
for you automatically,
so in this slide here, we have three users,
Charles, Donald and Dawn
and they each have their own session object
in the Tomcat server memory.
All right, so let's look at some
of the coding mechanics here
like how do we add data to the session object?
Well, the method signature is session.setAttribute,
so you make use of the built-in session object
and you call setAttribute
and you give the name and the value,
so the name is basically just a label
and then the value is any object
that you want to place in the session.
So, here's a coding example,
in this example I want to place an ArrayList
into the session, so here I create the list upfront
and then I say session.setAttribute,
I give the name of myToDoList,
so that's the name, and you can use any name you want,
comma items and that's that ArrayList object
that I have.
Now you can place any type of data here.
You can place ArrayList, your own custom employee objects,
strings, any type of object you can place
inside of the JSP session object.
All right, now the next thing here
is how do you retrieve data from the session object?
So, the method signature is session.getAttribute
and you give the name of the item
that you're retrieving
and it's going to return you a plain object,
so here's a coding example of how to do this.
So, here I'll start on the right-hand side,
I'll say session.getAttribute,
I give myToDoList, that's the same name I used
in the previous slide.
It's gonna return me an object.
Now what I wanna do is down cast it
to the appropriate type of list&lt;String&gt;
and then I can assign it on the left-hand side,
so a variable my stuff,
so you basically say session.getAttribute
and you use the name of the object
that you want to reference
and it will return it back to you.
And again, remember, you'll have to down cast it
to the appropriate type
if you want to use that later on in your page.
Okay, great, now there's also some other useful methods
that you can use on a JSP session object.
This is not the full list.
You can go to the full Java doc to get all the details
but for right now you check this first method here is isNew.
You can find out if it's a new true or false.
You can also get the session ID
just by calling getId
and this is useful if you wanted to maybe log
some information in your server logs,
or maybe log something in the database.
You can also call invalidate,
so if you want to get rid of a user session object
like say for example, a user logs out,
then you can call session.invalidate
and that will basically clear up that user's session
and then finally, you may wonder well,
how long does a session stay around in memory?
Well, basically it stays around
for a certain idle time period
or an inactive interval.
So, by default, a Tomcat server,
the inactive interval is set for 30 minutes
but it varies by server,
so you need to check your server documentation for that
but you can explicitly set the inactive interval,
so like if you're doing like an online banking,
most banks are very aggressive and they say
only five minutes, so you can simply setMaxInactiveInterval
and you pass in the value.
The one thing to be aware of here
is that this method takes the value in milliseconds,
so you have to give the appropriate number
of milliseconds there for your inactive interval.
And that's it.
All right, so I kind of covered a high level here
as far as the mechanics we're using JSP session objects,
so in the next video we'll get our hands dirty
with all the full coding on the JSP session exam.
I'll see you then.