Hey, in this video
I'm gonna show you how to do session tracking with JSP
and in particular we'll cover the coding portion of it.
Now, just as a quick refresher
let's look at the app that we're gonna code,
so again, remember, the demo,
you can add a new item
and we'll display the list here at the bottom.
So, I can type in a new item like buy groceries,
click on the Submit button
and it'll show up there at the bottom in my to-do list
and I can add one more item here,
go to gym and again.
Now, remember, the to-do list is actually saved
in our session object,
so it's a unique object
for each browser or user of our application
and I'll actually show you how to write
all of the coding for this from scratch in this video.
You know how I love to-do lists,
so here, the first thing we need to do
is create the HTML form,
then the second thing we need to do
is add the new item to the to-do list
and then finally, we need to display all to-do items
from the session object.
All right, so a lot of good stuff here
and we'll actually write all the code
for this from scratch.
All right, so just moving into Eclipse,
the first thing we need to do is create a new file,
so in our WebContent folder
we'll just do a right click,
we'll say New, File.
And I'll give the name of this file here,
I'll call it to do list demo.jsp
and once I'm happy with the name
I'll click on the Finish button.
All right, so we have our empty page here.
We'll start off with our normal HTML body tags
and now what I wanna do is just write out some comments
as far as our major steps in our to-do list,
so step one we need to create the HTML form
and then in step two we need to add
the new item to the to-do list
and then for step three we need to display
all to-do items from the session,
so this is our basic game plan here
for building out the code
and again, we'll write all the code for this from scratch
in this video.
All right, so let's start with step one,
creating the HTML form,
so the first thing we need to do is set up the form.
We'll set the action equals todo-demo.jsp,
so basically this page will submit data
right back to itself
because our file is called todo-demo.jsp,
so we're going to submit data right back to ourself
and I'll show you how to handle reading a form data
but what I'll do here is I'll set up this input text
for the items.
That's where the user will enter their to-do item
and I'll also set up another input type here for submit.
So, this is for the actual submit button.
And that's it, that's our basic HTML form
for reading in a to-do list item
along with a submit button.
And then just as a basic test harness here
I simply want to display that form data
just to verify that I can actually read the data
that they passed in,
so here I'll just say item entered
and then I'll say request.getParameter theItem,
so that will actually read the form data
and that's the same name as the field up here
on line seven as far as the name,
so we're basically reading that form field
and printing the information out.
Now, the first time we show this page
that value will be null
but we'll fill it in with some real information
as we submit data.
All right, so let's run it,
let's just right click on that file,
say Run As and Run on Server.
All right, so again, here's our form here.
Notice the item entered is null
but once I submit data,
then we see that new form field show up,
so I'll go to the store,
do the laundry and so on,
so we know that our form's working properly
and we know that our JSP can display that form data,
so this looks really good so far.
All right, so let's move down to step number two
and here we need to actually add the new item
to the to-do list.
So, one thing we're gonna make use of
is we're gonna make use of collections,
I want to make use of an array list.
We'll say get the to-do items from the session.
If the item doesn't exist,
then we're actually gonna create a new one
and we'll also see if there's any form data
that needs to be added.
So, that's our basic game plan here
for step number two.
All right, so one thing we're gonna need to use
is a lot of classes from the java.util package,
so let me just move to the top of this file
and just do an import on the package java.util,
so again, we do the angle bracket percent
with an at symbol
and we say page import equals java.util.*
so this will give me everything in the java.util package
like list, array list, so on and so forth
and we use that a lot in this JSP page,
so the import here will help us out
and save us on some of the typing.
The first thing I need to do here
is get the items from the sessions,
so I'll say List&lt;String&gt; items
equals LIst&lt;String&gt; for down casting it,
so we're gonna have a list of type string
and we say session.getAttribute
and we give the name
and here again, we can give any name
as long as we're consistent,
so for the name I'll call it myToDoList.
So, this will use that built-in session object
say getAttribute for a given name myToDoList
and down cast it accordingly.
Now, first I need to make sure
that it exists or not,
so if it doesn't exist, then I need to create a new one,
so if items equals null,
then that means I need to create a new list,
so here I say items equals new ArrayList&lt;String&gt;
so this will basically give me an array list
that can hold string items
and now I'm gonna actually add this list
to the session, so I'll say session.setAttribute
and then I give the name
and again, I'm going to use the same name
that I used for retrieving it, myToDoList
and I simply say setAttribute myToDoList, items.
And so, this handles making sure
that we have an item in the session,
if not, we create a new one
and then we set that list on the session.
Now, the next thing we need to do
is see if there's form data to add,
so I just use that method request.getParameter
and I use the parameter name of theItem,
so that's the actual form field that we had earlier
in this exercise.
Then I simply say if theItem is not equal to null
and that means that we have some data
and we can actually add that data,
so I'm gonna add this data to the list
of items, so here we say items.add
and we pass in theItem
and again, remember, items is the arrayList
and theItem is the actual form data
that we read in, so we're basically just adding
something to that existing list
and it'll simply build over time.
And remember, the arrayList is more like a global array.
You can simply add multiple items to it.
All right, so we're almost there.
The final step here, step three,
display all to-do items from the session.
So first off, let me just give you some basic HTML markup,
just like a little header here, To Do List Items,
all that good stuff, put a break there
and now what I need to do is build a bullet list of items,
so here I make use of ol,
it's HTML tag for orderedList
and this will basically give us a numbered list basically
and now I'll add a scriptlet
and I'm gonna loop through that arrayList
and then for each item simply print it out.
So, here I say string temp : items,
that's our list
and then I do an out.printLine
which is another built-in object
that we can use for printing directly to that JSP page.
So, here I'll say out.printLine, li temp
plus slash li,
so li is for listItem,
so this will basically help us build
a numbered list or an ordered list
of items for the HTML page.
We'll do this dynamically on the fly
based on whatever's in the to-do list.
All right, so this looks really good so far,
so I think we're pretty much done.
Oh yeah, just some clean up here on lines 14 and 15,
remove that code, we don't need this anymore,
that was more of just a test,
so I just rip that out, I'll delete that code
and save my file
and now we can move back to the browser.
The only thing I need to do is just remove those parameters
from the end of this URL,
so everything after the question mark
I can simply highlight and hit the delete key on
and I'll just hit enter,
it'll refresh the page.
All right, so at this point,
add new item, my to-do list items is null
or empty actually,
I'll add a new item here,
mow the yard, hit Submit,
so it's adding it to our to-do list,
wash the dishes, Submit,
and record more Java videos, come on, buddy,
get on the stick.
So, I need to record more videos.
I also need to write a lot of code,
so let me just add this in here,
so I crank out some more code.
That's what this is all about.
And so, that's it, so notice here
how we're building a list,
it's keeping track of everything
and it works out pretty good
and hopefully at the end of tonight
I can actually get some sleep.
We'll see.
But again, we're making use of session tracking,
we're keeping track of all of our to-do items
in the session, so these items are unique
for this given browser user.
If I opened up a different browser,
I'd see a totally different list,
that will be empty
and we can basically keep track
of all the unique actions for a given user,
so that's kind of session tracking in a nutshell.
Good job.