Hello, in this video,
we're gonna learn how to use cookies with ASP.
So we'll cover the following topics.
First off we'll find out what are cookies
and how we can use them and then we'll actually
explore the cookies API and learn how to write code
for reading and writing cookies.
Alright, so we have a lot of good things
in store in this video.
Let's go ahead and get started
so what's the purpose of cookies
and you may have heard of cookies before
but basically cookies allow you to personalize
a website for a user and so in effect
you can actually keep track of any user preferences.
Say for example you have a new site
and a user chose their favorite programming language
as Java, then you can keep track of that
and show them Java news in the future
or if you have a travel site and they frequently fly
from a given airport, then you can show them
all flights from that given airport.
So it allows you to keep track of long term preferences
for a user even after they close
their browser and restart it.
Alright so let's look at an example here
so I'll use that expedia.com travel site.
Again I use this website a lot
because I travel frequently between Philadelphia and India
so here in this form I'll just go ahead
and setup my departure city of where I'm flying from,
Philadelphia, PA in the US and I travel to Bangalore
at the deal in India so I'll just set up
the departure dates, I'm just making this up right now.
My departure date and my return date
but the key here is that once I do a search,
Expedia will go off and find flights for me
from Philadelphia to Bangalore.
Now the nice thing about it is that Expedia
will actually create a cookie and store it on my browser
such that when they come back at a later time
or actually when I come back at a later time,
Expedia will remember, it's like hey,
your last flight that you searched for
was Philadelphia to Bangalore and here's some new prices.
So I'll go ahead and quit my browser right now
and then I'll start up the browser again from scratch
and so now I have my browser back up
and then I actually go into Expedia again
and it'll actually remember information
about my previous operation and again,
they're making use of cookies,
they're keeping track of my preferences
so they automatically know that I'm gonna go
from Philadelphia to Bangalore,
just as a suggestion and they make use of cookies
for this type of functionality which is really cool
and I'll actually show you how to write Java code
or JSP code for reading cookies and also writing cookies.
Alright, so again what is a cookie?
Well it's basically text data that's exchanged
between the web browser and server
so this is functionality that's built into the browser
so you have your web browser when you visit a given server,
that browser will send over cookies to that server
and so that's how that expedia.com website
was able to remember my information,
it says oh great, you've been to Expedia before.
They read my cookies, they found out my departure
and destination city and displayed a custom form for me.
The site can also create new cookies
and send them to my browser to keep track
of information for any of my return visits.
So that's the idea of a cookie and so I'll actually show you
the server side code for reading cookies
and also writing cookies and sending them back
to the browser.
Now what exactly is in a cookie?
Well you can kind of think of a cookie
as just like a name, value pair so a cookie has a given name
like in this example, myApp.favoriteLanguage
and then the value could be Ruby,
alright so that's one cookie
and the application can actually make use
of multiple cookies so we can have another cookie here
called myApp.favoriteCity and then the value
could be Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
and your application can actually create many cookies,
the max is about 20 cookies per site per path
but that's more than enough for most examples
for building applications.
Now how are cookies passed back and forth?
Well the browser when it connects to the server,
the browser will only send cookies
that match that server's domain alright
so here's our browser, we're connecting to a given website,
the browser will only send over cookies that match
so for example, when I connect to expedia.com,
it will only send over cookies from expedia.com.
Likewise, if I was using like maybe CNN.com
and connected to CNN, the browser would only send cookies
that were set by CNN.com so they won't switch up
and send everything across like if I'm at Expedia,
it wouldn't send over CNN.com cookies to Expedia,
only matches on the actual domain name
and the given path of the application
so that's the key there so you know,
there's no security issues going on or whatever.
Alright so where are the cookies?
So I'm kinda moving back into my browser.
Depending on the browser you're using,
there's a different format for doing this
but here with Firefox, I can go under preferences
and once I'm on the preferences,
then over on the far left there's
a little menu option here for privacy
and I can select that link for privacy.
Now it's not really straightforward
but there's a little link here
called remove individual cookies.
This will allow you to view your cookies
so you can go ahead and select that link
and it'll show you a list of all cookies
that are set in this browser for the given domain names
so note here, you see all the sites,
the different sites that set cookies
and then the actual cookie name.
What I'm doing here is I'm actually searching for cookies
that were set by Expedia so we'll see all
these different Expedia sites
and the appropriate cookie names.
If you select one of these cookies,
then it'll actually show you the name of the cookie,
the actual content, whatever text that's stored there,
the host and the path.
Also at the bottom you'll see there's a expiration tab.
I'm sorry, an expiration field so this will tell you
how long this cookie will last
so basically one year from today,
one year from today is when that cookie will expire
so it'll always be on my system
until that given timeframe comes up
and I'll show you how to actually write the Java code
for setting the expiration time for cookies and so on
but anyway, just a nice little behind the scenes tour.
Alright so the cookie API.
Well there's a special class called cookie,
it's defined in the package javax.servlet.http.
This package is given to you for free in all JSP pages
so there's no hard requirement for you
to import this package.
You automatically get this package
so you can simply make use of the cookie class directly
in your JSP page.
Now when you use a cookie, the first thing you need to do
is construct it alright so here's the actual constructor
from the Java documentation so you create a cookie,
you pass in the name of the cookie and the value
for the cookie.
Now the name you can give any name that you want
as long as you're consistent within your application
and the value you can store any value or any data
that you want in the cookie as a string value.
Alright, so here's some real Java code
and you're probably wondering hey, where's the code.
Alright so here's the code that we'll use
for actually sending a cookie to a browser okay,
so let me set this up so let's say for example,
there's a form, the user can select
their favorite programming language
and they can send it over to this JSP page.
What this JSP page is gonna do is it's gonna read
that form data for their favorite programming language,
it's gonna create a cookie and it's gonna send it back
to the browser such that later on
when they come back to visit our site
a day later, a week later or a month later,
we'll remember their favorite language
and then we can customize the output page
for their favorite programming language.
Alright, so let's kind of walk through the code here
so the first one here,
request.getParameter("favoriteLanguage"),
again we're just reading something from the form data.
The next thing we need to do is create the cookie
so I say new cookie, I give the name value pair
so the name is myApp.favoriteLanguage
and again the name can be anything, comma favLang,
that's the variable from the previous line
so that's our cookie object.
Now we need to set the actual lifespan for the cookie,
how long do we want this cookie to last
so by default, a cookie has a lifespan of zero
which means that once the browser closes,
that cookie will expire.
So if you want the cookie to last for a longer time,
you have to set the lifespan
so here you have to say theCookie.setMaxAge
and you give the age.
Now this is the one part of the API
that I just don't like.
I wish they could make something easy
like setting a duration, you could say one month,
two years or you know five years or something
but you can't do that, it's not that simple.
You have to set the maximum age
as the total number of seconds.
Gosh I hate that.
Alright so anyway, so the bottom line
is that you have to do the math right
so if you want it for one week,
you have to compute the total number of seconds in a week.
If you want it for a year, the total number of seconds
in a year so this example here is for a year
so that's the total number of seconds for a year
and that's the API and that's just how it is.
But anyway, let's get that past that.
Once we have the cookie created,
we set the max age then we send the cookie to the browser
so we load it up into that response object
that's gonna go back to the browser
so here I say response.addCookie and I simply
give a reference to the cookie variable
and that's it basically so that's
for sending back one cookie.
If you wanted to send back multiple cookies,
well you simply create a new cookie object
and you say response.addCookie,
you know my cookie number two or whatever
and you repeat that process X number of times
but again there's a max on 20 cookies per domain per path
but anyway that's the basic code there
for sending a cookie to a browser.
Alright, so now the browser has a cookie
that's been set by our application
by our JSP from that previous slide.
Now when the user returns back at a later time,
we want to show them a custom page
based on their cookie information
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna read
their favorite programming language cookie
and then do something with it.
So to get a handle to the cookies,
I make use of that request object
and I'll say request.getCookies.
This will return me an array of cookies
so note here on the left hand side,
cookie with the square bracket,
the square brackets means an array so that's the cookies.
Then I check to make sure theCookies
is not equal to null because maybe
they didn't have any to send over.
Once I know we have cookies,
then I simply do a for loop
so I set up a for loop, Cookie tempCookie : theCookies
and the cookies is the variable from that previous line
so then I simply go through each one of those cookies
and I compare that cookie name to the name
that I'm looking for so I'm actually looking
for the cookie name, myApp.favoriteLanguage
so I simply say if myApp.favoriteLanguage
equals tempCookie.getName,
then that's the favorite language
equals tempCookie.Value so I get the value of that cookie
and then I break out of that loop
and then later on in my JSP page,
I could maybe use that fave language
to display custom news for the user
like maybe I would hit the database
and get some information or hit a Twitter feed or something
but at that point, I have the key,
I have the actual value of the favorite cookie
that the user selected and I can do
whatever I'd like to do it so in a nutshell,
that's how you read cookies from the browser.
Now again this is kind of very high level,
we just saw some code snippets.
In the next video, we'll write some real code
and I'll pull together a nice little example
where we'll have some JSP pages,
we're reading cookies, we're setting cookies
and we're building custom pages
so don't worry, I'll put this altogether for you
and you'll see a nice working example, alright.
So I'll see you in the next video.