Hey, in this video we're actually
gonna look at the code demo
for using cookies with JSP.
So, lets kind of pull it all together
with a real example.
So, we're gonna have three pages
that we're gonna build in this video.
The first thing we're gonna start off with
is the cookies homepage,
so this is for our little training portal,
so if the user has a favorite language selected,
then we'll show them a list of new books on that topic,
news reports, and hot jobs, and so on.
So, by default, if they don't have any cookies set,
we'll simply just make use of Java
as their default language.
Now, at the bottom they have a link
where they can actually personalize this page
and choose a different language.
So, this will take us over to our cookies form
where they can select their own programming language,
or their favorite programming language,
and here Java, C Sharp, PHP, Ruby,
they can select that favorite language,
Like, say for example they chose Ruby,
they hit submit,
then at the bottom,
we'll give them their response page
or confirmation page saying,
hey, thanks, we've set your favorite language to Ruby.
Now, when they return back to the homepage,
then new versions of the homepage
will make use of the cookie that was set
and then show that information accordingly.
So, let's look at a real quick demo here.
Starting at the homepage,
by default the language is Java,
so we're assuming that no cookies were set
and we just simply default to Java.
Now the user can go through and personalize this page.
So, here there's a form,
they can choose a drop down list,
choose their favorite programming language.
So, in this example here I'll choose Ruby,
and then I'll hit the submit button.
And so again, the confirmation page,
hey, we set your favorite language to Ruby.
Now, when I return back to the homepage,
it should personalize it for the Ruby language for me.
So, here selecting return to homepage
and then here it is,
new books for Ruby.
Latest news reports for Ruby.
Hot jobs for Ruby.
So, basically what this page is doing now
is it's simply reading the cookie value
and reading that favorite language
and then it's customizing this page
based on that cookie.
Now, remember, cookies last for a long time,
so I can actually close my browser
and then come back in
and it'll actually remember
that cookie information for me.
So, cookies are persistent
based on the actual age you set for the cookie
and it'll last for that given time period.
So, we see this works out for us in this example.
So, good job so far.
All right, so let's talk about writing code,
but I always like to start with a to do list.
The first thing we're gonna have to do
is create an HTML form to personalize the site.
Then, we'll need to build a JSP to read form data
and set cookies.
And then finally, we have to create our home page
to read the cookies and display the personalized content.
A lot of good things in store here.
Let's dive in and start writin' some code.