Hey, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse
and let's start coding.
So, the first thing I wanna do is actually
create a new file.
So I'll move down to this WebContent directory,
and I'll create a new file.
So I'll say New, File,
and for the actual file name,
I'll choose cookies-personalize-form.html.
This will be our HTML form for personalizing the website.
Once we're happy with that name,
we'll go and click Finish.
All right, so in this file,
I'll just go ahead and write out my basic HTML
header information in my HTML body.
For the header, I'll just go ahead
and set up a title real quick,
Personalize The Site
and that's my basic housekeeping.
Now I'll actually go through and build out the form.
So, I'll set up my form,
I'll set action equals to cookies-personalize-response.jsp.
And so, now I'll just kind of build out my form.
First off I'll prompt the user hey,
select your favorite programming language
and I'll set up a dropdown list
or a select item,
so we've seen this before,
so I set the name equals favoriteLanguage
and then I just drop in those languages,
Java, C#, PHP and Ruby
and again, we've seen all this before.
Now one more thing I need to do
with this form is set up my Submit button.
So, I'll move down here,
I'll say input type equals submit
and then value equals Submit.
And that's basically it here for our form,
just prompting the user
for their favorite programming language
and then having our Submit button.
All right, so we can go ahead and save that file
and let's just do a quick test on it
just to make sure it works out,
so I'll just choose this cookies-personalize-form.html
and I'll just say run on Server
and this looks pretty good, so great,
there's our prompt, there's our dropdown list
and our Submit button,
so this part looks okay so far.
So, moving ahead to step two,
I need to create another new file.
This file is gonna be our response page,
so I'll call it cookies-personalize-repsonse.jsp.
And once I'm happy with that name,
I'll go ahead and click on the Finish button.
All right, so this JSP basically is gonna read the form data
and then also create cookies or set cookies
and pass them back to the browser,
so again, let me go ahead and do my basic housekeeping here
for the HTML
and then I'm going to set up a scriplet
for my angle bracket percent.
The first thing I need to do is read the form data,
so I'm going to read that form field favoriteLanguage
that we had in the previous file.
Now that I have that actual favoriteLanguage,
now what I'm going to do is create a cookie,
so I'll say theCookie equals new Cookie
and I give that name value pair,
so name of myApp.favoriteLanguage
and then the value is favLang.
So, now now that I have a cookie created,
next I need to actually set the lifespan
on the cookie, so I'll say theCookie.setMaxAge
and this is the ugly part again remember,
you have to give the total number of seconds
and so, I did the math and that's the total number
of seconds for one year.
Once we have that taken care of,
then we simply need to send the cookie to the browser
and we do that by doing a response.addCookie
and then giving a reference to that cookie object
and that's basically it for this step two
of reading the form data
and then setting the cookie.
So, now what we wanna do is go through
and just put our body in here,
so this body is mainly just a confirmation
just to echo whatever the user entered,
so here I'll say hey thanks, we set your favorite language
to and then we just drop in that parameter information,
so I'll use the dollar sign param.favoriteLanguage.
And then at the bottom I'm gonna set up a link
back to the home page,
so I'll say set up an href
and I'll say return to homepage
so that way they can make it back to the home page
and then see their new customized content.
So, this part's all laid out
for this response page.
And so, I think this pretty much covers everything
for step two.
All right, so let's go ahead and take care of step three.
So, let's go ahead and create a new file again,
and the name of this file is cookies-homepage.jsp,
so this is our main JSP page
that's gonna display the personalized content.
All right, once we have that file name entered,
go ahead and click the Finish button.
And I'll kind of expand my window here for a second.
So again, normal housekeeping for the HTML.
So, basically here I'll set up a header,
Training Portal,
and now I wanna first off read
the favorite programming language cookie,
so I'll drop in a little scriplet code here.
First off, I'll set up a default,
so if there are no cookies,
the favorite language is just gonna default to Java.
Then next I'm actually gonna get the cookies
from that request object,
so remember, it's going to return an array,
so I'll say cookie with a square brackets for an array
equals request.getCookies.
So, next I simply just need to loop through
and find our favorite language cookie,
so here I check to make sure
that cookies is not equal to null
and then I set up a for loop.
So, I have for Cookie tempCookie : cookies
and now I basically just want to check
the name of each cookie
to see if they're equal to our favorite language,
so equals tempCookie.getName.
If that's true then we can get the actual value
of that cookie, that's our favoriteLanguage,
so favLang equals tempCookie,getvalue
and then break
and I actually have a typo here.
Cookies is incorrect.
This should actually be theCookies
because that's the array of cookies
that we received from the previous line,
so good, I fixed that typo.
Good job.
All right, so this looks good so far,
so we can save this file
and this part of it basically handles reading
that favoriteLanguage cookie.
All right, so now that I have the cookie,
I know the actual value of the favoriteLanguage,
now what I can do down in this body here
is I can actually show a personalized page
based on this information,
so that favLang, that's the variable
that we received a little higher up there on line 20.
So, I'm just going to set up
some little sections here for this.
So for example, showing new books for this language,
so I'll say hey, new books for language X
and so, I'll just drop in an expression here,
angle bracket percent with an equal symbol, favLang
and then I'll just set up a UL
for unorderedList
and I'll just put in some placeholders here,
blah, blah, blah, just placeholders,
no real stuff there.
Ideally we could maybe talk to a database,
query a database, get a list of books
for this given topic
and then print those out
but for now we'll just put in the little placeholders here.
We simply want to focus on cookies for right now.
So, now what I'll do is I'll take this information,
I'll just kind of do a copy, paste on it
and I'll just drop it in here,
so this is for latest news reports
for the favoriteLanguage
and then a similar thing here,
another copy, paste and I'll just drop in
hot jobs for favoriteLanguage and blah, blah, blah
and that's pretty much it.
So, we have a customized page
based on that cookie value
and we're showing it to the user,
so this looks pretty good so far.
And then one last thing I wanna do
I simply want to give them a link
where they can personalize this page again,
so say for example they wanted to change the language
to like PHP or Ruby or C#,
they can easily do that with this href link.
All right, so I'm going to save this file,
and I can move over and now we should have three files
right now, so we should have our cookies-homepage,
our personalize-form
and also our personalize-response.
So, let's go ahead and run the homepage right now,
so I'll simply do a right click
and I'll choose Run As, and then Run on Server.
And so, this will bring it up in the internal browser.
I want to just copy this URL.
I'm gonna drop it into the Firefox browser,
so I'll say Copy
and I'll move over to Firefox,
I'll drop that in
and so, here's the actual page,
so training protal
and then by default we're just showing Java
because no cookies were set at this time.
I can go ahead and click the link
to personalize the page
and I can go through and choose
one of the languages here
and in this example I'm gonna choose PHP
as the language.
And then I'll go ahead and hit the Submit button.
Okay, great, so it says hey, thanks,
we set your favorite language to PHP,
so behind the scenes they created a cookie
and they passed it back to the browser.
Now you can go ahead
and click on this Return to Homepage link
and now note our customized page right now.
So, New Books for PHP,
Reports, Hot Jobs and so on,
so our cookies portion of it is working out just fine for us
and this is kind of cool.
But you may want to actually verify
that the cookies are actually being set,
so in the Firefox browser
you can just click on this option here to the far right,
move down and choose Preferences,
and over on the far left there's a little menu item here
called Privacy, we can select that option
and again, remember,
here in the center, remove individual cookies.
That's the link that will actually show us
all of the cookies.
And here are the cookies
that were set for our site, localhost
and we can kind of expand this a bit
and we'll see that there are two cookies sent,
JSESSIONID and there's myApp.favoriteLanguage,
so I'll select that guy,
so that's the cookie name,
that's what we created in our code
and that's the content,
that's what the user just selected here
in that last demo.
So, this all looks really good.
This is kind of how we designed it
and how we actually implemented our code.
So, I would say congrats on doing cookies in JSP.