Hi, in this video we're gonna learn how to
add a student to our database.
So we'll cover the following topics.
Fist we'll get a quick demo of the add student feature,
then we'll look at the big picture,
and then we'll also take a look at the sequence diagram
just to see how everything fits together.
Alright, so let's first start with the demo
of the add student feature.
So in our home page we're gonna have
this new button here called add student.
Basically the user will click on this add student button
and will show them a new form.
Okay great, so here's the form.
We'll collect the students first name,
last name and email address.
So I'll go ahead and enter some sample data here.
So I have this student Andrew Whittaker
and his email address is andy@luv2code.com.
So then once we're happy with the data
we can go ahead and click on the save button.
Okay great, so we just added the student.
So note here on our list we have the new student
Andrew Whittaker and his email address, andy@luv2code.com.
So we're actually reading this information from the database
so that previous screen at form, we would actually insert
or add the students to the database,
and now here we're seeing the results of that query.
So this looks really good, and we'll learn how to build up
all of the code in the following videos.
So this is kind of the big picture here.
So we start with our home page list students.jsp,
a list of all of our students.
Then we click the add student button.
It takes us to the add student form.
As you saw in the demo,
once you fill out the information in the form
and hit save, that actually sends it over
behind the scenes to our servlet
which is our student controller.
This student controller reads the form data
and then passes it over to our student database Util
who actually does the insert into the database.
Now some of the details behind the scenes here.
So that form we actually sent the data over
using the get method. So they'll call
the doGet method on the servlet.
And then we'll create this hidden form field called command.
So command equals add.
So this is something that we make up
specific for our project, I kinda just made that up
that command.
It's a hidden form fill, we'll send it over
then our servlet will read that command
and figure out that it needs to add a student.
Because, in the future we'll have other features for editing
a student and also deleting a student.
So I just wanted to give additional commands there.
So again, I love my to do list, right.
So the first thing we need to do it update our list students
jsp, to add that button.
Then we're gonna create the html form,
and then update our student controller servlet.
And then finally we'll work on our student database Util
to do all the low level JDBC work
of adding the student to the database.
So that's the big game plan.
So, we'll break this up over multiple videos
just like we've done before.
We'll wright all the code from scratch,
and at the end we'll have a full working example.
I'm excited,
a lot of work ahead,
and we'll knock it out together.
So I'll see ya in the next video.