All right, so the first task in our to do list
is to update the list-students.jsp
and we're actually gonna add that new button onto the page.
We're gonna have the Add Student button on our page.
So let's dive in and get started.
All right, so basically what I wanna do
is add that button to this list-students.jsp page.
So I'll go ahead and open up that page.
I'll expand my window here.
And then I'll basically move down
to an area right below the header.
And right here in this content section
I want to put in a new button.
So I'll just write out a little HTML comment
just to again keep myself on track.
All right, so I'll set up this input type="button".
And the value is Add Student, so that's the actual label
that they'll see on the button.
And I also wanna add some other items here
so when they actually click the button
I wanna tell the system what to do.
So onclick then I basically wanna show
my HTML form for adding a student.
So again, onclick, I simply give
the name of the form that I want them to display.
So this is our add-student-form.jsp.
And then finally here I wanna add a little fancy CSS style.
So here I'll say add-student-button.
That's the style from the style sheet that we're using
that it'll apply to that button just to give it a color,
rounded edges and all that good stuff.
So that's basically really all we need to do
for adding a new button here on our list-student.jsp.
Now let's go over and try it out here.
So I'll just run my web app again.
So great, this looks really good.
Take a look, we have our new button here, Add Student.
Looks really fancy.
I'm impressed.
(laughs)
Now, actually, I'm not impressed.
Cause when I click that button it gives me a 404 error.
Like, what's up with that?
Well, of course right, we haven't created this file yet.
We haven't created the add-student-form
and that's our next order of business here.
So, what I'll do is actually just create
a placeholder for the form right now.
Just a very simple page but at least
I just wanna create that file.
So I'll just do a new file and then I'll give
the name of the file of add-student-form.jsp.
And for this again just a real simple placeholder here.
So, I just wanna put just something
real simple here just so the file exists
because were trying to make a good impression.
All right, so let's save this.
And now if we go back to our browser
we should see something slightly different.
So I'll just click on back, do a little refresh here,
and then click on Add Student.
And boom, cool, all right, great.
So we have this little placeholder file.
So we created that new file
and just put just some very basic text there.
But we're in good shape for right now.
What we'll do in the following video
is that we'll actually fill out the form
and put proper form fields and submit buttons
and all that good stuff but at least we have
kind of the basics in place for right now.
So, I'll see you in the next video
when we'll hook up our new form.
See you then.