Alrighty, so we can go ahead
and check the box there for the first step.
That's done.
Now we'll focus on step two, creating
the HTML form for our new student.
So we'll have a form, we'll have text fields
for first name, last name, and e-mail,
we'll have a save button, and then we'll have
a little link at the bottom to take them
back to the original list.
So that's the big picture, that's the game plan.
Let's go ahead and dive into Eclipse
and let's start coding.
Alright, so we have some unfinished business
here with the form.
Our previous form simply had a placeholder.
Now we need to get in here and do some real work.
So I'll just expand the window here, open it up.
And for this page, first I'll just
take care of some general HTMl housekeeping,
so I'll set up like the doc type,
and then I'll get in here and I'll set up
the header for this page.
So we'll set the page title for add student.
And this page is also gonna make use of some style sheets.
So I'll set up a reference for two style sheets.
So the first style sheet is basically
what we used before, style dot CSS,
and then we'll have another reference here
for a special style sheet specifically
for this add student form.
So the file is called add student style dot CSS.
But we don't have that right now.
It's actually in our starter files,
so what we'll do is we'll actually copy that CSS
from the starter files and put it into this project.
So let me just swing over to my finder window,
just bring it on screen here for a second.
Alright, there it is.
Again, on our source download,
then I'll go down to the starter files directory,
and I'll move into web content, CSS,
and there's a file in there called
add student style dot CSS, so that's
the new CSS file that we want.
So we'll simply copy that file,
and we're gonna copy it to our Eclipse project.
So I just do a copy here, then
I'll move back over to Eclipse.
And under CSS, then I'll paste that file.
Alright, so this looks pretty good.
So, on line eight, this is where we referenced that new file
and we referenced the CSS add student style dot CSS.
So that's the new file that we just copied over.
So that all works out.
So we're good to go with that.
And if you want to, you can go look at this CSS.
Again, I'm not a CSS guru.
You can peruse this on your own.
I normally have friends help me out
or I just kinda copy some stuff off the web.
That's the piece there.
But anyways, we have our header set up,
we're in good shape.
But now it's time for us to focus in
on the body of our page.
So, I'll actually put in some more housekeeping stuff here
for our body.
Primarily just like the header information
for the actual page.
I'll just put this in here real quick.
So, we simply just do some divs here again,
wrap our header, FooBar University.
Same thing that we saw before in
some of the previous videos.
Here I set up the H three for the add student header.
And now this is where I get down to business here.
So I set up this form.
Action equals student controller servlet.
So we're gonna send data to the student controller servlet
using the method equals get.
So this I'll actually call the do get method
on our student controller servlet.
And we learned about form submissions earlier in the class,
but this is just more of a refresher
and a real-world application for it.
Now, also remember, earlier I said
we're gonna have a hidden form field.
So I have this input type equals hidden,
and the name equals command, value equals add.
Again, this is specific to us.
We're kinda making this up, so name equals command,
we can give any name we want there.
Value equals add you can give any value.
But we're just gonna follow the convention of
name equals command, value equals add.
But add could be anything.
It could be add student, add data, add stuff, whatever.
But I'm just gonna keep it simple for right now.
Now I'm gonna set up a little table,
and this table's gonna hold the different form elements,
like the actual label and the actual text field
that the user will enter their data.
Just to kinda keep things lined up.
So, for this first table row, I'll just set up
the entry, the label, for first name.
And then I'll also set up a input type, or text field,
for first name.
So, again, this'll basically give me a label
and then a input text field.
Alright, so let's go ahead and try this out.
So let me move back over to my app,
and I will take a look at my add student form
and I'll just show it in the browser.
So I'll just simply right click, do a run as,
run on server, and then, boom, looks pretty good.
So this is our form.
It's very crude right now, but it's our form.
So we have our header, add student,
and then we have this first label here, first name,
and a text field.
So basically all we need to do now
is kinda more of the same.
Just kinda copy paste for all the other names there.
There's a little typo I had in this thing,
I just fixed that.
Lowercase T for student.
And again, just kinda copy paste this
x number of times.
So, drop in a copy paste here, another copy paste,
and then I'll just go through and update the labels.
So this is for last name.
I'll set the field name for last name.
And then the third one here is for e-mail.
And I'll set the name of this field as e-mail.
So, again, remember with the form,
when you have these name entries,
these are the actual parameter names that you'll use
when you read the form data in your actual servlet code.
And then the one last thing I need to do here
is another copy paste.
I need to just put in an entry here for the submit button.
And then the actual value for this button is save.
So value equals save.
And then I even have a CSS style that I wanna apply to it,
so here I have class equals save.
So that's something from the cascading style sheet.
And that's our submit button basically.
Alright, so let's go ahead and just do
a quick refresh on this form.
And, woo hoo.
Looks pretty good.
It's starting to shape up here.
So, we have our fields here for first name,
last name, and e-mail, and we have our submit button
here at the bottom.
So this looks really, really good so far.
Good job.
And now, one last thing I wanna do
is I wanna add a link at the bottom of that form,
just so the user can go back to the list students page.
So I'll just enter a quick little div here,
just to give us a nice little line break.
And then I'll just set up a link
back to the original page.
So, here I have, I'll set up an anchor href equals,
and I'll just basically point back to the
student controller servlet.
And then, here I'll just say back to list
or something like that.
Yeah, there we go.
That'll work.
And so that would give me a little link
that'll point back to the original page
that'll list all the students out.
Then I can go back over here and just do a little refresh.
And then, cool, so in the bottom right
I have that href link back to list.
So, cool, so we're in good shape for right now.
So anyways, mission accomplished.
We've created our form.
We have everything set up, and in the following video
we'll work in our servlet to read this form data.