Alrighty, we can check the box there
for step number two.
So moving onto step three, we're actually gonna update our
StudentControllerServlet.
And basically we're gonna handle the requests coming in
and also read the form data.
So, moving into Eclipse,
what we wanna do is open up our code
for StudentControllerServlet.
And so when the form data is submitted,
they're actually gonna pass the data,
or they're actually gonna call the method on doGet,
because that form's gonna send data over
using a get request.
So it's gonna come into this doGet method.
Currently right now, all we do is simply list the students,
but what we need to do is actually read the command
and route the code accordingly,
depending on if they're gonna add a student
or list a student.
So I'll just put a little comment here for
read the command parameter.
And then once we read that command,
then we need to route it to the appropriate piece of code.
So as you see, I like to put comments here
to keep myself on track.
So I can simply read the parameter by saying
String theCommand = request.getParameter,
and the parameter is command.
And then basically what I wanna do
if the command is missing,
like if it's null or just wasn't passed over,
then I'll simply default to listing the students.
So then I'll say theCommand = "List",
just kinda assign it by default.
So this way my code is somewhat flexible,
in that if they don't give us a command
then we'll at least be able to list
without hitting a null point or exception.
Then what I wanna do is basically do a switch on the command
and based on that value,
I wanna route it to that appropriate method.
So the command,
so case of list, meaning that if the command equals list,
then I'll call that method listStudents
passing in the request response.
And it's the same method that we had earlier
in our Servlet so far.
So that's the first case that I'll test for.
Then I'll also check for the case of add.
So again, if the command comes over
where the command equals add,
then here I wanna call a method called addStudent
and I'll pass in that request response object.
And then also I'll just have a,
I'll set up a catchall, a default case,
or like an else, meaning that if none of those things match,
or match up then we'll just default
and then our default operation will be listStudents.
So if they send over a bad command that we don't understand,
we'll simply just send them back the list of students.
And we're keeping it simple for right now.
We could get real nasty with them
and give them a bad error message
but for now we'll just list the students.
So that's basically it for our routing logic here,
when the command comes in.
So this looks good, but there's one problem,
and there's a problem on line 59
and Eclipse is not gonna let us get away with it. (chuckles)
And it says hey this method addStudent,
we don't know about it,
and just like we did in the previous videos,
we'll say okay, Eclipse,
well then why don't you go ahead
and create that method for me?
And so I'll select the link and viola!
Eclipse will create this nice little method for me,
called addStudent
and I can go ahead and write some of my code in there.
So, cool.
I just love it when Eclipse writes code for me.
I just wish it could write all the code. (chuckles)
But no worries, that's why we're here, right?
That's why we get paid all the big bucks,
cause we are the experts.
We are the gurus.
So again, I'm gonna stretch out here
and get some white space
and actually what I'll do before I start writing code,
is I'm gonna write some more comments
just to kinda tell myself what to do
when it's time to add a student.
So I'm gonna read the student info from the form data,
and based on that data I'm gonna create
a new student object,
and then I'll add that student to the database,
and then finally once it's added to the database,
we wanna send them back to the main page,
meaning we wanna get a list of all the students again
so we can see our new person that we just added.
So that's the game plan for this add student method.
Alright so let's go ahead and dig in
with this read student info.
Again, this is reading form data, right?
So we're simply doing request.getParameter
and we're given the form field.
So here starting out with first name,
it's called firstName.
And then I simply copy this line
and just paste it for the other fields,
cause it's just a copy paste exercise now.
Last name, and then a similar thing here for email.
And so basically that's it.
That's the code here for reading student info
from the form data.
Alright, now moving on down here,
we can use this information to create a new student object.
So I'll say Student theStudent = new Student,
and I can pass in those values,
firstName, lastName, and email.
So at this point, I have a student object
that's been created.
Then I wanna actually add the student to the database.
So I'll make use of my studentDbUtil
and I'll say addStudent and I'll pass in theStudent object.
Now again, we have a problem here.
Eclipse doesn't know about the method.
I'm gonna tell Eclipse,
hey buddy, go ahead and create this method for me.
Okay, great.
So Eclipse actually created this method for us.
So we're actually in this class StudentDbUtil,
and if we scroll back down to our method,
they actually created this method here addStudent.
So this is kinda really cool.
Now, we're not really doing the JDBC stuff right now,
so I'm just gonna put a little heads up that,
do nothing for now.
We'll actually add this code in a following video
but I'll just kinda put the placeholder
in there for right now.
So anyway, so that,
at least that clears the air here for line 84.
So we do have a method here called addStudent
even if it does nothing,
that method does exist now.
And then finally I wanna send them back to the main page.
Just so they can list all the students and so hey,
I just reuse that method that I already have,
listStudents and pass in a request response.
So this actually kinda worked out pretty good,
I can just reuse some code that I already have.
Except for there's one small little problem here.
So let's see what the problem is.
I can just hover over and it will say
there is an unhandled exception.
So okay, good.
So in this case I wanna add a throws declaration.
I wanna choose the first option here,
add throws declaration.
So what it's gonna here on that method
that we're working in right now, addStudent in the Servlet,
at the far right they're gonna add throws Exception,
because it's possible that method we call there
could throw an exception and we need to either handle it
or list ourselves as throwing it.
And I'll just take the shortcut for now.
So there we go, so throws.
So we're good to go.
It takes care of all the issues here
and this is basically the code here for adding a student.
And this is the code that's in our Servlet for right now.
Alrighty, so we can go ahead and save that.
And I think we can even try and run this thing.
Let's try that.
So back up here to my application,
just run it.
And so now we have our nice little button here,
Add Student shows our form.
So we already built the form
so we can go ahead and fill it out with some information,
our Andrew Whittaker.
And it's andy@luv2code.com.
And once we're happy with that info we hit save
but oh no!
Andy's not in the list, why?
Well because our database code
doesn't really do anything yet.
Aagh!
No problem, we kinda knew that already.
So this is good for right now,
at least we have the Servlet code in place.
In the next video,
we're actually gonna put the database code in place
to actually do the database insert.
So, I'll see you in the next video.