Alright, so we're making some good progress.
We've covered the first three steps,
the last step here is updating our StudentDBUtil.
So, this is where we're actually gonna make use
of that addStudent method
and we're actually gonna put the real JDBC code in there
for doing an insert into the database.
So, just a quick recap here in our StudentControllerServlet.
In our addStudent method here,
we have a call
to studentDbUtil.addStudent,
so that's in place right now,
but what we need to do is actually put some real code inside
of that method.
So, I can just go to this method here
and navigate to it,
let me show you this little Eclipse trick here.
I can choose the method, right-click,
and I can say Open Declaration, or I can hit F3,
and it'll actually take me directly to that code,
so that's an Eclipse trick for you.
So, now I'm in my StudentDBUtil right now
and I'm at this method here, addStudent,
so DBUtil,
addStudent.
In this method, this is where we're gonna do our JDBC work,
so we're gonna get low-level, get a connection,
all of that good stuff.
So, let me clear out this method here
and again, I always like to start with comments,
just to kinda let me know
what I need to write.
So, I already know upfront I'm gonna need a throws Exception
so I'll just go ahead and put that in there now.
So, I'll need to create a SQL statement
for doing the insert,
I'll also need to set up the parameter values
for the query.
I'm sorry, the parameter values for the SQL
based on the student's information.
I'll need to execute the SQL insert
and then finally, I'll need to clean up my JDBC objects,
so that's basically the game plan
of things that I need to do in this method
for adding a student.
So, I'll just set up some basic JDBC objects here for
Connection and a PreparedStatement,
and I'll also set up my little try catch block here,
and also take care of the imports,
so import java.sql.PreparedStatement.
Alright, so let's start off here
with creating the SQL for the insert.
So, this is the SQL that we're gonna do for
actually doing the insert into the database
for the student,
but actually, whoa,
I actually need to get my connection first.
I forgot about that,
so that's the first thing we're gonna do here,
is get our connection.
Now we can go through and write our SQL String.
So, I'm gonna make use of SQL,
I'll say insert into student.
That's our table name.
Then I need to give the actual columns
and then the actual values,
so the columns are first name comma last name, comma email,
and make sure you keep an extra space at the end
of those lines there, inside the quotes.
And then for values, I'll make use
of the question mark placeholders
because I'm using PreparedStatements.
So, PreparedStatements are based off of placeholders
and you fill in those placeholders
or param values with actual data,
so I'll go ahead and set those param values now
in this next piece of code.
So, first off, I'll just kinda prepare
the statement upfront,
say myStmt equals myConn.preparedStatement
based on that SQL
and now I can go through and set the actual param values.
So, here I can say setString,
I get the parameterIndex of one
and I get the value of the student.FirstName.
So, the parameter values for PreparedStatements
are one-based, meaning that the first one is at one,
not zero, so don't wanna confuse you there.
Alright, because everything else in Java is zero-based,
like arrays, but our param values here,
for PreparedStatements, are one-based.
So, anyway, one for first name,
two for last name, three for email.
Alright, so that looks good.
So, we have all the param values set,
now it's just a matter of executing that SQL statement,
so I'll simply say myStmt.execute
and it'll do the work.
So, it should take a student,
perform an insert into that student table,
and there we go.
So, that's kinda the big game plan there
for this method in our StudentDBUtil,
so get a connection, create SQL, set the param values,
and execute the SQL insert.
And then finally, I need to clean up the JDBC objects
because I have a connection object
and a statement,
so I simply use a close on myConn comma myStmt,
comma null.
This last null here is for a result set.
In this case we don't have a result set,
so we simply pass in the value of null
and that's it.
So, we have out addStudent method in place,
so we are ready to go.
Alrighty, so let's do that.
So, I'm gonna go ahead and run the application again.
It's gonna give me my list,
I'll hit the Add Student button.
I'll enter the data again for Andrew Whittaker,
and andy@luv2code.com,
then I'll hit Save
and then, boom!
Check it out at the bottom, Andrew Whittaker,
so he's actually in the database
and this is really, really cool.
I'm excited about it, but you may wonder,
I don't believe you,
so let's go and actually look at the database.
So, I'm logging into my database here
and I will go to this web_student_tracker,
my Tables student and I will query that table,
and then, there it is.
So, he's there at the bottom,
so he's ID number six, Andrew Whittaker.
So, the data really is making it into the database
and so we have our database interaction,
so this is cool.
So, we did the full circle here
of writing the code all the way from the beginning
and then following it all the way to the back end
with the Database UTL,
so I would say mission accomplished
for the addStudent feature.
So, I'd say good job, we made it through it.