Hey! In this video,
we're gonna cover MCV with Servlets and JSP.
Now, when we had our initial discussions
on Servlets and JSPs you may have wondered,
well which one to use and my answer was,
hey use them both, integrate them together.
So here we have the Servlet
that'll do the business logic work
and the JSP will actually handle the view.
And, as I mentioned earlier, this is a very popular pattern.
It's called the Model-View-Controller Design Pattern
and it's actually used by a lot
of the popular Java frameworks.
So here's the big picture of the Model-View-Controller.
The web browser will send them the request,
the request initially comes into the controller servlet.
The purpose of the controller servlet
is to hold the business logic.
Now, it may delegate a call out
to the model to get additional data,
or additional information.
Then, once it has the data,
then it can send information over to the view page
and the view page is actually the JSP.
Once the JSP has the information,
then the JSP can render an HTML view
and the JSP will send that view back to the web browser.
So that's kinda the big picture here
with the Model-View-Controller.
So what are the benefits of MVC.
Well, first off it's a very good line item
to put on a resume because everyone wants this.
(laughing)
Sorry, just joking.
The main benefits here is,
one to minimize HTML code in the servlet.
So in our servlet, no more out dot print lines
in the servlet code cause that just didn't feel right,
that looked ugly.
Also, we want to minimize the Java business logic
in the JSPs.
So, no more large scriplet codes in the JSP.
The JSP will only handle the view.
So really it's a good, clean separation
of roles here in our web application.
Alright, so the big question is,
well how can the servlet call the JSP,
or how the servlet send data to the JSP.
Well, the servlet's gonna make use
of something called a request dispatcher.
So here's the actual code for using a request dispatcher.
So the first step, in step one we get
the request dispatcher.
So we make use of request.getrequestdispatcher
and we give the reference of the actual page
we want to reference.
So here, view students.jsp
that's the JSP page we want to call.
Once we have this dispatcher set up,
then we need to forward information to the dispatcher.
So here I say dispatcher.forward
and then I make use of the request and the response object.
So it'll send it over to the JSP
and the JSP can read information from that request
and also use that response.
Now, the other question is like,
well how can I send data to the JSP.
Like, I need to get additional data from the database
or from a back end system.
Well we can add data to the request object using attributes.
So here on the slide in step zero I add data.
So first off I could set up just an array
of strings here for students
and then I say request said attribute.
I give the attribute name
of student_list comma the actual value students,
so that's an object.
So you can actually add any object here that you wanted.
Here I'm simply adding an array of strings,
but you could add an array list,
you can add a custom object,
you can add any Java object that want here
to this request attribute.
And then the following steps are the same.
So step one, get the request dispatcher,
step two forwarding to the JSP.
All that's the same that we saw in the previous slide.
And you can add as many attributes here as you'd like,
as long as they have a unique name.
Alright, so the servlet has added data to the request object
and they did the request dispatcher to forward to the JSP,
now the JSP can actually view this data
and here we're gonna make use of the JSTL,
or the JSP standard tag library.
So at the top we give our taglib
and then in the center here
we make use of one of those JSTL core tags for each.
And we're basically gonna loop over the request attribute.
So here I have for each var equals temp Student,
items equals $.
This student_list, that's the actual attribute name
that was set by the servlet.
Alright, so the exact same name with the exact same case.
That's the data that was set by the servlet
and we can reference that
and we can simply print out temp student
and that will give us the output here for this system.
Great, so this is a very basic example here
of setting up and MVC application.
So we wrote all the code from scratch
so we looked at the servlet controller
and then we also looked at the JSP,
and what we'll do in the next video
is that we'll move into Eclipse
and we'll actually get some hands on,
we'll write all the code from scratch
so you can see how an MVC system works
with servlets and JSP.
Alright, I'll see you in the next video. Woohoo!