Alright, so let's go ahead
and move into Eclipse.
And again we're gonna continue
to use that same project servletdemo.
The first thing we need to do here is we need to
add support for for our JSTL libraries to this project.
And effectively what we need to here is copy the JAR files
into this servletdemo project.
So what I'll do is I'll actually open up one of our previous
projects called tagdemo and I'll move into that web content
WEB-INF/lib directory. There's two JAR files here.
These are the two JAR files that I'll need for JSTL.
So let me go ahead and select those two JAR files,
right click and choose copy.
So I'm copying these JAR files from tag demo
and I'm gonna move them up to my servletdemo project.
So again we're adding JSTL support.
So in servletdemo on the WEB-INF/lib,
I'll just do a right click and I'll do a paste.
And this will basically paste it in those JAR files
to this servletdemo. So this looks really good.
I should have two JAR files here listed.
So this is great. So now this project has JSTL support,
and we're good to go with this.
Alright, that took care of our housekeeping admin work
for servletdemo by adding JSTL support.
Now let's go ahead and work on our
Mvc example.
So the first step we need to do is we need to actually
build a controller Servlet.
So I'm moving to my Java resources directory.
Under source, I move down to my package servletdemo,
I'm gonna add a new Servlet here.
So I'm gonna right click and I'll say new Servlet.
Alright, so this brings up our new Servlet screen.
What I wanna do is call this
Servlet class name MvcDemoServlet.
So that's the name that we're gonna use for this example.
Once I'm happy with the name,
I'll go ahead and click finish.
So again, Eclipse goes off, does a lot of work,
creating a nice Servlet for us to start with.
So this is very good. I love the way Eclipse helps us
jump start our development process.
Alright, so here's our Mvc Servlet with the annotation.
I'm gonna focus on the doGet method,
so let me just clear out some space here at the bottom.
And, I'm gonna do all of my work inside of the doGet.
Now they have some auto generated code here,
I'm gonna actually remove that code,
and put in my own code.
We're gonna code this from scratch.
So again, I always like to set up my comments here.
So the set 0 is we're gonna add data.
Step one, we're gonna get the request dispatcher.
And then, step two, we're gonna
forward the request to the JSP.
So those are the three main steps
that we're gonna accomplish here
in this doGet method for our Mvc demo.
So first off, adding some data.
So I'm just gonna make up some data here.
Students, and I give a four student names.
We could retrieve this from a database
or we could possibly retrieve this
from a backend helper object.
But just for keeping it simple right now,
I'll just define the data right here in this Servlet.
We'll get into more advance examples later on in the course.
And then I have the students object,
so now I set attributes. So I give the attribute name.
I'll call it student_,list,
and then I give a reference to that object
that I just created in the previous line here students.
So that's basically it.
So we've created some data, and we've added this data
to the request object
by making use of request set attribute.
And again, we can set as many attributes as we'd like here
as long as they have unique names.
Alright, so the next thing I need to do is set up
a request dispatcher. So remember the request dispatcher
is what we can use to actually make a call to the JSP page.
So I say get request dispatcher
and I give the actual name
of the JSP, view_students.jsp.
And, I'll go here to line 35 and I'll fix some of the
imports here for this request dispatcher class.
And I'll select that option,
that should clear up the imports there.
Okay great, so I have the request dispatcher
for that view_students.jsp.
Now step two is very important,
I have to complete this step.
I have to explicitly forward the request
over to
that JSP.
So here I say dispatcher.forward,
and I'll forward over the request and the response option.
So those are the two parameters
that came into this method here,
that we've added some data to the request,
and then we're forwarding that data
all across to that actual JSP.
And that JSP can read the data at a later time.
But that's the main code here for
forwarding the request to the JSP.
Alright, so just kinda stepping back here just looking
at the method that we've created all from scratch.
Step zero we added the student data,
step one we got the request dispatcher,
and then step two we forwarded the request to the JSP.
So this is the main work for our Servlet controller,
in our Mvc example.
Good job.
Alright, so the next thing we need to do in our Mvc example
is that we need to add the JSP page,
that view_students.jsp.
We need to actually create that file.
So my web content directory, I'll right click.
I'll say new file.
And I'll have to use the exact same file name
that my JSP is gonna forward to.
So, there gonna foreword it to view_students.jsp.
So you have to make sure those names
are the same and correct.
And once you're happy with this name,
go ahead and click finish.
So let me expand this window here.
One thing this JSP page is gonna make use of JSTL.
So we always have to give our JSTL
taglib reference at the top.
Then I have a little cheat sheet that I like to copy
paste cause I, you know, I don't wanna get it wrong.
So I like to do it the correct way every time.
So anyway, that's the taglib reference.
Let me go ahead and do some html housekeeping here
with our html tags and our body tags.
Now, what I'd like to do is actually do a loop.
And I wanna loop over that
student list data that was passed in.
So I set up this c:forEach,
and I set the variable, I call it temp student.
And then items, this is the actual name of that attribute
that was set by the Servlets.
So here I say
${
student_list,
so again this is the exact same attribute name
that was set by the Servlet.
And we have to use the exact same name
in order for the JSP to find it.
So that's like the label or the alias for that data.
So we have that set up. Now I can actually display
that tempStudent here. So I use ${tempstudent
and I just add a little br for a line break,
and that's basically it.
So this four loop here will basically loop through that
student list and it'll display
the actual student information,
or the temp student as it goes through the list.
So this is really good, I'm excited about this.
I'm ready to try it out [Laughs].
Alright so, in order to test this one here
we need to go and run our Mvc Servlet.
So I select my Mvc demoservlet,
I'll do a right click,
and I'll choose run as,
and then run on server.
And, woohoo, this looks really good.
So, this is the result of our Mvc example.
Our Mvc Servlet went off and
added some data to that request.
It sent it to our JSP and our JSP went through and displayed
each one of those student names.
So their all working together.
This is awesome, I like it.
So this is a good way to kinda wrap this up.
So we built an Mvc system from scratch,
very simple one, but we built it from scratch.
We created a controller Servlet,
and we also created a view JSP,
and we integrated Servlets and JSP together
for an Mvc system.
Great job.