Hey, in this video we're going
to cover MVC with servlets and JSP
and I'll actually go into more detail
than we did in the previous videos.
So in the previous video we had an overview of MVC, right,
so the first thing is that,
the request comes into the controllers servlet,
we make use of the model and then we have the view,
and then I'd sent it back to the web browser.
However, in the previous videos we didn't really get
into the details of step two as far as using the model.
So that's what we'll do in this video.
We'll actually create a helper class,
called StudentDataUtil.java and it's going to be our model.
It's basically going to give us a list of students,
so basically, for step two,
our controller servlet will make a call
to the student data util, get a list of students
and then it will put them into that request attribute,
send it over to the view
and then the view will generate a view page
that it'll send back to the browser.
So, this view page that the JSP sends back,
we're going to enhance it a little bit.
In the previous videos we simply made use of a list,
here we're actually going to make use of a table.
That's the most common thing
that you'll do in a real application,
is display your information in tabular format.
So, we'll modify our JSP page to make use of a table.
Now as you know, I love to do lists,
I like to do everything step by step.
So the first thing we're going to do is,
we're going to create a student class,
the second thing we'll do is create that helper class
for the model Student Data Util.
Then we'll create out MVC servlet
and then finally we'll create the view JSP.
And what I'll do is I'll show you
all of these steps in the following videos.
And I'll break it up to separate videos for each step.
But don't worry we'll see everything from scratch,
you'll see everything step by step
and then finally at the end we'll pull it all together
as one big application so you can see it works.
So we have a lot of coding in store for us.
Let's go ahead and dive in.