Alright, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
And what we're going to do is continue
to use that same project Servlet demo.
So, the first thing that we need to do on our step one,
is that we need to create this Student Class.
(Silence)
So what I'll do is move down to my Java Resources Directory
and move into this package and, actually, what I want to do
is create a new package just for this demo.
So, I'll just right-click and I'll say New, Package.
And the name that I want to use is very similar
to the previous one, but I'll simply want to add on mvctwo.
So that's the name of the package.
And once we're happy with that,
we can go ahead and click Finish.
Okay, cool. So now we have this new package.
So let's go ahead and add our Student Class
in its new package. So this new package, mvctwo.
I'll right-click on it and I'll say New, Class.
(Silence)
And my class name here is, this is for our student class,
so I'll just type in the name of Student.
And I keep all the other defaults
and I go ahead and hit Finish.
Okay, great. So we have this very basic class.
So we're starting from scratch here.
So let's go ahead and define the fields here
for our student. We're going to define fields for
firstName, lastName, and email address.
(Silence)
So we should have these three fields here,
listed for our student class for right now.
Now, what I'd like to do is also create a constructor
to help us initialize those fields when we create a student.
So let me expand the window.
So, here, let's generate a constructor.
So I'm going to use an Eclipse
trick to generate a constructor.
So I simply do a right-click, I choose Source,
and I choose Generate Constructor using Fields.
Ew, pretty fancy, here. Let's try this out.
So, Eclipse will actually generate a constructor for you.
It'll generate code for you based
on the fields that you select.
So I'll make sure they're all selected
and then I'll hit OK and then, Boom! Whalah!
This is cool. So Eclipse actually created
a constructor class for me that I can use later on
in my application without having to write any codes.
So that's a nice little Eclipse trick.
Okay, wait. There's more. I have one more trick for you.
We're going to make use of generating getters and setters.
So, again, Eclipse can generate getters and
setters for you automatically.
So what I'll do here, again, I'll right-click,
I'll choose Source, and now, this time,
I'll choose Generate Getters and Setters.
(Silence)
And Eclipse will pop up a dialogue
with the list of fields here.
I'll go ahead and choose Select All
to make sure all of these fields are selected for
email, firstName, and lastName.
And I'll keep all the other defaults here.
And once you're happy with that,
you can go and click the OK button.
And now Eclipse just generated a lot of code here.
(laughing) It created Getters and Setters for firstName,
email, and lastName. So, again,
a lot of coding here that we didn't have to write ourselves.
We made use of those Eclipse tricks
to generate the code for us.
So this pretty much takes care of everything here
for our student class and we can go ahead
and move on to some other work.
So good job so far.