Okay, so in our next step what we're
going to do is actually create the StudentDataUtil.
Remember, this is our helper class
that will allow us to access the model.
So, what I'll do here is I'll just move over
to this package nvc2 and I'll right click
and I'm going to create a new class.
So right click, say new, class.
And for the class name we'll call it StudentDataUtil.
And I'll keep all the other defaults here
and I'll go ahead and select the finish button.
Alright great, so this is my StudentDataUtil
and again, this is basically our model so
this will basically return a list of student objects
when the servlet calls it, so this will actually
be called by the servlet.
I'll set up this method here, public static list student
get students, so the method is get students.
It's going to return a list of students.
And I'll simply fix the imports here
for that list of objects from Java.Util.
Okay, so here's my method, now let me go ahead and
just kind of write some comments here as for
what I need to do for the real coding here.
So the first thing is creating an empty list.
The next thing is adding sample data.
And then I need to return that list to the calling program.
So that's the basic game plan here
for the implementation of this get students method.
Alright, so let's write some code.
So the first thing you need to do is create and empty list.
So I'll create a list of students and
I'll just say new array list and then
just open paren and closed paren.
And again, I need to go through and fix the
imports here so I can import that Java.Util.arraylist class.
Alright cool, so I have those two imports there at the top.
Great, the next step here is adding sample data.
So I just make use of that array list students.
And I say students.add and now what I need to do is
actually create a new student object here.
So I need to use that constructor
that we created in the previous video.
So I'll say new student and I'll just pass in
the values there for the student.
So the first student here is Mary Public and
her email address is mary@luv2code.com.
So that's our first student that we've added to the list.
Let me get some white space here.
And I'm just going to copy and paste
line 14 a couple of times for the other students.
So I'll just copy this line
and then I'll just paste it x number of times.
So I think I'll do it two more times, yeah that's good.
And I'll just change the first name and last name here
for some of the other students.
So I have John Doe.
And then we also have Ajay Rao.
Alright, so that looks good right now.
So we basically added three students here to our array list.
Good, so we have some data here right now.
So this is really good.
Now what I want to do is simply return this list
to the calling program, so I simply use a return
and I give a reference to that array list and that's it.
And I can save it and I think I'm in good shape here.
So again, this is simply our helper class, our model
that will actually be called by our servlet.
So we simply create some student objects and
then we return that list of student objects
to the calling program, okay, good job so far.