Okay, great, so we have our
StudenDataUtil created.
The next step is that we need to create our MVC Servlet.
So what I'll do is I'll simply right click,
I'll say New, Servlet.
This will bring up the dialogue window here.
For the class name for our Servlet
we're gonna call it MvcDemoServletTwo,
so that's the name that we'll have here for it.
And actually I have a typo here.
Let me fix that typo to a lowercase W.
Good, and now you can go ahead and hit the Finish button
once you're happy with that.
Okay, great.
So again, Eclipse does a lot of work.
It creates a very basic Servlet for us.
The first two lines here, 13 and 14,
it sets up our @WebServlet for MvcDemoServletTwo.
So, that's the basic, off-the-shelf stuff
that Eclipse will generate for us.
What I wanna focus on is this doGet method,
'cause that's where the requests
are gonna come into, this doGet,
so I'll just kinda clean up,
make some white space here,
give me some room to work with.
And what I'm going to do is actually,
inside of this doGet method is
remove that auto-generated code.
I wanna put my own code there,
so I'll simply highlight this and delete it.
And again, you know, I like to kinda go step-by-step
and I also like to start my comments here.
So, I'll just write some comments for us
for what I have to do.
So, the first thing I need to do
is get data from the helper class.
That's the StudentDataUtil that we created a little earlier.
And then the next thing I need to do is
add this list of students to the request attribute,
or the request object.
Then the next thing I need to do is actually
get the request dispatcher,
and once I have the request dispatcher,
then I can forward it to the appropriate JSP page.
So, those are the basic steps of what I need to do
in my Servlet code inside of this doGet method.
All right, so let me start writing some code.
So, I'll get the list of students from that
StudentDataUtil, our model, or our helper class.
So, I'll simply say StudentDataUtil.getStudents,
and that's the method that we created
in that previous video.
And I need to go through and just
fix some of the imports here
for the JavaUtil.list.
All right, so now I need to add the students
to the request object, so I'll simply set an attribute,
so I say request.setAttribute,
and I give the name, so I'll call it student_list,
that's the name, and then I give a reference to the object
from the previous line, students.
So, give the name, the object.
Next, what I do is I get the request dispatcher.
So, I say RequestDispatcher,
dispatcher=request.getRequestDispatcher,
and I simply give a path to the JSP page.
So, the page I'm gonna send that over to is
view_students_two.jsp.
And again, go ahead and fix up some of the imports here
for the request dispatcher class.
All right, so that's my request dispatcher.
Now I need to actually forward the request
and response over, using this request dispatcher.
So here I say dispatcher.forward,
then I pass in the request response objects.
And these objects were actually passed in as method params
up on line 31.
All right, so this looks good.
This is basically the code that we need to add
in our MVC Servlet to talk to our helper class model,
add the students to the request object,
get the request dispatcher, and then forward.
So, this is all really good,
and we built all of this code from scratch.
So, in the next video, we'll build out the JSP page.