Alrighty!
So we have our Servlet completed.
The next thing we need to do is complete our JSP view.
And in our Servlet we actually reference the file name,
the file name is "view_students_two.jsp."
So we need to create a page with that exact name.
And what I'd like to do it just kinda
move back to my project structure.
I'm actually gonna copy one of our
previous JSP files and simply rename it.
So in my WebContent directory,
we already have view_students.jsp.
I'm gonna simply copy that file
and paste it and just rename it
and give it a new name.
So here I'll choose view_students.jsp,
and I'll select this file,
and I'll do a right-click and choose Copy.
And then what I'll do is
I'll simply do a right-click and choose Paste.
And for the new name
I'm gonna use that new name that we
specified in our Servlet.
So this is view_students_two.jsp.
So that's the new that we're using for this demo.
So once you're happy with all of that,
go ahead and click the Okay button.
Okay, great, so we should have this new file here
called view_students_two.jsp.
So go ahead and double-click that file and open it.
And what I'll do is I'll kinda expand my window here.
So this is gonna be the view page for our MVC system,
and what we need to do here is actually
build an HTML table.
So most of this is gonna be a HTML exercise.
So I'll just go ahead and set up my HTML heading2 up-top.
Do a little horizontal line here.
And now, inside of this For Loop,
instead of simply just printing out a list of students,
I actually want to make use of tables
and table rows, so on and so forth.
So, let me just clear up some white space here.
And on the bottom right,
you see a little picture or diagram
as far as what we want to have
as our end result.
A table with headings and rows.
So first off for my table,
I'll set up my table headings here up-top.
So, I'll make use for this...
Actually, before I get into that,
let me just set my border equal to one.
Okay, now I can get into my table headings here.
So I'll set up a table row.
And then I'll make use of "th."
"th" is for "table heading."
And then I'll just give the headings here for First Name,
and I'll just copy-paste this line
for the other headings here.
So this'll be for the heading for Last Name,
and then this final column here is
the heading for Email.
So those are the actual table headings that we'll have here
for our table.
All right, so, now,
inside of our For Loop,
we're looping over those students.
That's our list,
student list that came our MVC Servlet.
Now, what I want to do here is
build up a table row and then for each cell,
I'mma specify information for the student.
Here, so I say tempStudent.firstName.
This'll actually call the getter method on that student,
so this'll actually call tempStudent.getFirstName().
And that's part of the JSP expression language.
And we've kind of learned all this before.
But I just wanted to reiterate that for you.
And that'll give use the first name.
And now I can just copy-paste this line
for the other fields here.
So I'll copy-paste,
and I'll just update this line here for Last Name
and then also Email.
Okay great, so that's our For Loop.
So we're gonna loop over that student list
that was placed into the request by our MVC Servlet,
and then we simply loop over each one of those items,
put it into a table row,
and for each cell, we display
First Name, Last Name, Email.
And we just simply loop through the list.
So this looks really good here
as far as giving us a HTML table output,
and we kind of built this list up on the fly.
Or I'm sorry.
We actually built up this table on the fly.
All right, good job.
All right so let's go ahead and run it.
And I'll go up to this MvcDemoServletTwo,
and I'll launch it or run it.
I'll simply do a right-click,
and then I'll choose Run As,
Run on Server.
And so this will give me the output.
So we have First Name,
Last Name,
and Email.
So this matches what the information
that was populated by that
studentHelper class StudentDataUtil.
So this looks really good.
So this is kind of like our desired result here
for our MVC demo.
Now, one thing I want to modify here is that
right now we had to run the Servlet directly.
I like to set up a link to the Servlet
from an HTML page.
So in my WebContent directory,
I'm going to create a very simple HTML page.
So I'll simply do a right-click;
I'll say New,
File.
And the name of this page,
I'll call it index.html,
so just a very basic HTML page.
So let's go ahead and click on Finish, here.
And basically it's a very simple page.
All I want to do is just have a webpage link
that'll point to my Servlet.
So I'll just set up the basic HTML body stuff.
And here I'm gonna set up a HTML link,
so I use "a href,"
and I give the URL reference to my Servlet.
So that's MvcDemoServletTwo.
So this will give me a hyperlink here on my page.
So I'll say,
View Students with MVC Two.
So this'll build up a very basic HTML page with a link
pointing to our Servlet.
All right, so we can save this file,
and then we can run this file directly.
So I can simply right-click on index.html,
do a right-click and choose Run as,
and then Run on Server.
Okay, great, so again,
very basic html page.
But hey, now this is our link.
This is really good.
So now the user can simply click this link.
And it'll actually launch our MvcServlet.
So, select the link, and boom!
There we go.
We have the output.
So this went full-circle.
We pulled this all together.
So we have the request coming in from the browser,
went to our Servlet.
It made it over to our model,
which in turn would send data over to our JSP.
And then finally send back the results to the browser.
So, I think we did MVC full-circle.
And we did it all from scratch.
Good job.