Hey!
In this video, I'm gonna show you how
to create a Hello World program with JSP.
So the common question is well,
what is a JSP file?
Well, a JSP file is simply an HTML page
with some Java code sprinkled in.
And it basically gives you dynamic content
that you can include in your page.
So in this diagram here, this is a basic JSP file.
It has some HTML code, some Java code,
you can make some more HTML code, and so on.
The end result is that you'll have an HTML page
with content that's generated by some Java code.
Alright, so the next question is well,
where is the JSP processed?
Well, a JSP file is actually processed on the server.
So it's processed on your tomcat server,
your glassfish and Java server.
The result of the Java code is actually
included in the HTML returned to the browser.
So here's an example.
We have a web browser, we make a request for a JSP page,
it goes across, the JSP pages processed by a server
and then the results of that Java code will generate HTML
and that those result will actually
return back to the web browser.
And if returned back to the browser,
just plain HTML.
So in a fact, the Java code can generate HTML
that goes back to the web browser.
Alrighty.
So next where should we place the JSP file?
Well, the JSP file goes into your WebContent folder.
So you create a new eclipse project
that have a WebContent folder,
you place the file there.
Then one requirement is that the JSP file
must have a .jsp extension.
So, here's an example here we have on a slide.
WebContent helloworld.jsp.
Now, it's just like any other normal HTML file
that you place out there,
like building a normal website,
you can have multiple JSP files,
you can place your JSP files in sub direct and so on.
So, it's almost like building a website
with multiple HTML pages except
for here we'll have .jsp files
with that JSP extension.
Alright.
So you're probably wondering,
"Hey, show me the code!"
So here's an example of a code,
very basic Hello World program.
Again remember, a JSP file is simply an HTML page
with a small bit of Java code sprinkled in.
So, here we have our body,
h3 Hello World of Java and then the time
on the server is and right here,
this is what we have Java code.
So, with JSP you make use the angle bracket percent
and then some of it you can put a JSP element.
So in this case, we're going
to put what we call a JSP expression.
So we use the equal symbol.
So, angle bracket percent equal
and then we put in some Java code.
So this example, we create a new date object.
This will give us the current time stamp
and then we include the output
of the state object in the page.
So in effect, it will call about two-string method
on the state object and include the result
of that in this page that goes back to the browser.
So, I know I gave you a lot of information there,
let's go ahead and switch over and look at eclipse
and write this code and then we'll run it within eclipse.
Alright.
So, we're in eclipse.
So, the first thing we need to do is we need
to create a new web project.
So I'll go up to my file menu,
I'll say new and then I'll choose dynamic web project.
And this will bring up the dialogue,
we can enter our project name.
Here I'll call it jspdemo.
You can give any name for the project
but here I'm just keeping it simple.
Make sure that target runtime is setup for apache tomcat v8
and you can keep all the other defaults with no problem
and then simply hit the finish button.
So, this will create new project for us.
So we have jspdemo and if we expand this directory,
we'll see that we have a WebContent folder
and right now our WebContent folder is empty.
There is no pages that are created.
So here I'm going to create a new file.
So in the WebContent, I'll right click,
I'll say new file.
And I'll call this helloworld.jsp.
And once done with the file name,
I'll hit the finish button.
Alright.
So, here's our file.
It's empty right now,
so I'll just go and create a very basic HTML page
and eclipse will help me out with some of the tags here.
And I'll set up a body and then I'll set up my h3,
Hello World of Java
and then I'll say the time on the server is.
And this where we'll drop in some Java code.
So, use that angle bracket percent with an equal symbol
and I say new Java util date.
So again, it's going to create a new date object
with the current time stamp and then the result
of that time stamp will be included right here
in this page that will go back to the browser.
So, that's basically my Hello World JSP right now.
Alright.
So, let's go ahead and run this example.
So what I'll do is I'll move over here
to that file helloworld.jsp.
I'll simply right click the file and I'll say run as
and I'll choose run on server.
So, eclipse will be first.
It will say choose your server.
We're going to use the existing tomcat v8 server
and in the bottom left we'll check the box
that always use the server when running this project
and from there I can go and hit the finish button.
So this will actually start on my tomcat server
if it's not running and then
it should execute this JSP page.
So, great!
Here the results.
Hello World of Java.
The time on the server is and they drop in the time stamp.
So this is the actual current time stamp
that I have on my server at the time of this recording.
So note here, it created that new date object
and then the results of that date object
were included in that page.
Now, what I'd like to do is copy this URL
and just drop in to a regular web browser.
So I'll just right click,
I'll say copy
and then I'll switch over to a web browser
like Firefox and I'll just drop in that URL.
So just do a right click and I'll choose paste.
Then I'll hit enter
and there's the JSP page inside of the browsers.
So, Hello World of Java
and the time on the server is.
And so then I can right click and take a look at the source.
And so here's the source, so this is what,
this is kind of behind the scenes tour here.
So this is the source that came back to the browser.
So the time on the server is and it has this information.
So, the web browser really doesn't know
how this code was generated.
It simply renders the response.
So, that's JSP in a nutshell.
Alright.
So, we covered a very basic JSP Hello World example.
We're going to dig deeper or dive deeper into JSP
as we go through in the following videos.
But that's enough, just to kind of get us started.
We can see the basics and we can check the box
for Hello World.
Alright. So, stay tuned.
A lot of good things in store in the following videos.