Hello.
In this video, we're gonna learn how to use JSP expressions.
So, in JSP, there's actually
different types of scripting elements.
There's three actually, JSP expressions,
JSP scriptlets, and declarations.
Now, what we'll do is we'll actually have a deep dive
on each one of these topics in separate videos
but I wanted to give you just an overview real quick.
So a JSP expression is basically a small Java expression
that you can include in the page
of the syntax's angle bracket percent with an equal symbol.
And we'll see a lot of that in this video.
There's also what we call a JSP scriptlet.
So a JSP scriptlet is simply an angle bracket percent
and then you add some Java code.
You can add one to many lines of Java code
and we'll see that in a following video.
And then finally, there's a JSP declaration.
So this is angle bracket percent with an exclamation point.
And so here, you can define a Java variable or method.
And again, we'll do a deep dive on that.
So this next slide here is on JSP expressions.
So, basically you can compute some type of expression
and the result of that is included in the HTML page
that's returned to the browser.
And so, here's an example
and we saw this from one of our previous videos.
Actually the previous Hello World video.
In your JSP file, you can say the time on the server is
and then you can add an expression.
So again, remember, angle bracket percent
with an equal symbol and we can place a Java object there.
Once this is processed by the server,
then the generated HTML is simply the two string version
of that given date object.
But let's take a look at some more examples
of using JSP expressions.
So in this next example,
I'm gonna show you how we can convert a string.
So here I have this new string Hello World.
And then I can say .toUpperCase.
So I'm gonna basically convert this string to all caps
or to all upper case.
And the result of that will be included
right here in the page.
So that's for like strings and objects.
You can also make use of mathematical expressions.
So here I can multiply a value 25 times four equals
and you could put any math expression in there
that you'd like.
You can also have Boolean expressions.
So here, I could say, is 75 less than 69?
And it'll give me a value of true or false.
And that's an example here of using JSP expressions.
So we saw objects, mathematical expressions,
and also, Boolean expressions.
OK great, so let's move into Eclipse
and let's try this stuff out.
I like to continue to use the same project
from the previous video, jspdemo.
I'd like to move down to my WebContent folder
and what I wanna do here is actually create a new file.
So I'll just right click, I'll say new, file.
And for the name of this file,
I'll simply call it expression-test.jsp.
And once you're happy with that file name,
you can go ahead and click the finish button.
OK great, so we have a very basic file here
and actually an empty file.
And we need to add something in it.
So let's go ahead and start off with our basic HTML.
I'll set up my body tag.
And now I'll go ahead and type out that first bit
of converting a string to upper case.
And now what I'd like to do is add a JSP expression.
So again, angle bracket percent.
And so here I say new string Hello World
and I do a dot and I get the code completion here
and I'll say .toUpperCase.
I'll select that item there.
It's kinda cool Eclipse can kinda help you out
with some of the code completion there in a JSP file.
Alright, so that's it, so, that's the file.
I can go ahead and save it.
And what I'd like to do is go ahead and run this file.
So I'll just do a right click, I'll say run as,
and then I'll choose run on server.
Alright so this will start up my Tomcat server
if it's not running already.
And then right here in the browser it'll give us the result.
Converting a string to uppercase.
And remember we had Hello World as normal case
and now this basically converted Hello World
to all upper case.
So that's the result of our JSP expression running
which is really cool.
Alright, so let's take this a little bit further.
I'm just gonna add some line breaks in here.
And now I wanna do an example
using a mathematical expression here.
So here I'll say 25 multiplied by four equals
and now again I'll make use of my JSP expression.
Angle bracket percent with an equal symbol, 25 times four.
So the result of this is of course is 100, right?
And the value of 100 will be included right there.
So I simply save the file.
So now here I can simply go back to my browser.
I don't have to run it again.
All I have to do is simply reload this page
and the results will show up.
So I'll simply hit the reload or the refresh button here.
And there it is.
25 multiplied by four equals 100.
Mission accomplished, very good.
So again, a nice thing here with JSP.
If you make any changes to the file,
you don't have to rerun it or redeploy.
You simply just reload that page and you're ready to go.
OK, let's do one more thing.
Let's play around with Boolean expressions.
So let me just move down here, add a line break.
Let me just add some extra white space here
just so we can see everything.
And I'll just have a very basic Boolean expression example.
Is 75 less than 69?
And now I'll let Java compute this for me.
Again, very trivial, right?
But we're just showing you an example here
of a Boolean expression.
So, 75 less than 69.
This will evaluate as true or false.
Of course, we know this will return false, right?
But we'll see how the JSP program
will help us out with this.
Alright, so I'll save the file here.
I'll move back over to the browser.
And again, all I have to do is just reload or refresh.
And then there it is.
Is 75 less than 69?
False.
So very good.
So we saw a really good example there
of using JSP expressions for Booleans.
Also for math and also for string objects.
Alright, so let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
We did a deep dive on JSP expressions.
I showed you different types of expressions
using objects, math expressions,
and also Boolean expressions.
In the following videos, we'll dive into JSP scriptlets
and we'll also dive into JSP declarations.
So stay tuned, I'll see you there.