Hello, in this video
we are going to learn about JSP Scriptlets.
So, what exactly is a scriptlet?
Well a scriptlet is a JSP construct.
It allows you to add one to many lines of Java code.
And, once you have this set up, then you can also include
content in the page by making use of out.print line.
So the basic syntax is angle bracket percent,
you write your x number of lines of code,
and then percent angle bracket.
And that code will be executed top down
when the page is processed.
Alright, so that's the background.
Let's look at a code example.
So, very basic example here,
Hello World of Java,
and then I'll add a scriptlet.
Again, angle bracket percent.
Once your inside the angle bracket percent,
then you can start writing real Java code.
So what I'd like to do here is set up a for loop.
for int i equals one, i is less than equal to five,
i plus plus.
And, I'd like to print out I really love to code.
Now, instead of doing a system out print line,
I'll make use of out.print lines.
So this constant will be included
in the html page that's return.
So here I say out.print line I really love to code,
and I can add in the value of i.
Now, here's the output at the bottom of what we'll see
once we run this JSP.
I will have our header, Hello World of Java.
So here we'll have our statement printed five times
along with the actual loop index.
And that's the basic there on setting up a JSP Scriptlet.
So angle bracket percent, and then you go ahead
and you write your Java code.
Alright now before we move into the actual coding demo,
I want to just let you know about the best practice.
You want to minimize the amount of scriplet code in a JSP.
So don't go overboard.
Avoid dumping thousands of lines of Java code in a JSP
because it makes it hard to maintain, it's poor design,
and it's poor architecture.
What you want to do, if you have a lot of code
that you need to use in a JSP,
I recommend that you refact this into a separate Java class
or make use of MVC.
And I'll show you how to do both of those
later in the course.
I'll show you how to make use of a separate Java class.
I'll also show you how to make use of a MCV framework
when we servlets and JSPs working together.
But anyway, I just had to say this upfront
as a best practice so you don't go off and do
things the wrong way.
Alright so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
And, let's write some code.
So what I like to do is I like to continue to use
the previous project, JSP demo.
And what we're going to do here, we're going to actually
move into our web content directory,
and we are going to create a new file.
So I will just right click on web content,
and I'll say new, and I will choose file.
So the actual name of the file that I'm going to set up here
is called scriptlet-test.jsp.
Alright, so that's the file name.
And once your happy with this file name,
you can go ahead and click the finish button.
Alright great, so we have this blank file
and we need to start writing some code.
So first off, let me expand the window here.
And I will set up the basic html.
And I will go through and set up the basic body.
Alright so, I'll set up that header three,
Hello World of Java.
Okay great.
Now when I make use of a scriptlet, so again,
angle bracket percentage, and then we can
write our Java code here.
So I am going to something very similar
to what we had on the slide.
I'll simply set up a for loop for
i equal one, i is less than equal to five, i plus plus.
And then I want to print out some information
included in the page.
I'll make use of out.print line.
And then again, we are having fun here,
I really love to code, woo hoo.
And I'll add the little loop parameter here.
So there we go, so that's our scriptlet code.
So we have a for loop.
We need to print out some information.
We make use of that out.print line.
And, I know, there it is.
Pretty simple.
Alright so let's go ahead and save this file.
And, let's move over here and let's run it.
So let's right click on this file, scriptlet-test.jsp,
right click, choose run as, run on server.
And great, here's our output.
We have our Hello World of Java,
and then we have this code that was generated
by our for loop, I really love to code, woo hoo.
And we have the loop parameters going one through five,
as you can see I am having a lot of fun here
with this really love to code.
But that's it.
OK, so this wraps up the video.
I showed you how to make use of JSP Scriptlets.
You can add some Java code to generate content
dynamically, on the fly.
The following videos will talk about JSP Declarations,
so stay tuned.
A lot of good stuff coming up.