Hey, in this video I'm going to show you
how to use JSP declarations.
JSP declarations basically allow you to
declare a method in the JSP page,
and then you can call them from the same JSP page.
So it's very useful like any normal code that you create.
If you need to execute some code
over and over again, you simply encapsulate it
in a method declaration.
And you can do a similar thing here with JSP.
The syntax is basically an angle bracket, percent,
with an exclamation point, and then you declare
your method like any normal Java method.
Alright, so let's take a look at an example here
of a JSP declaration.
Up top, I'm gonna declare a method.
So, again, declarations, angle bracket, percent,
with an exclamation point.
So once you're inside of here, this is just like
a normal Java method declaration.
You have a return type of string,
the name of the method, makeItLower,
any input parameters, in this case I have string data,
and then internally inside the body
you write your actual implementation code.
So in this example, my implementation code
is going to be real simple.
For makeItLower, I'll simply take the data
and call .toLowerCase.
And again, very trivial method here.
I just wanted to show you how to declare
a method in a JSP page.
And then at the bottom I can make use of that method.
So here I have a, make use of a JSP expression.
I'll do a angle bracket, percent, with an equals symbol,
and I say makeItLower and I pass in the string that
I want to convert, and that's it.
So at the bottom here,
this is what the output will look like.
So lower case "Hello World" then colon
and then I have the actual hello world.
So the result of making that expression
or that method call,
the results will be displayed right here in that JSP page.
And that's basically it.
Let's talk about some best practices.
This follows what I discussed earlier
with scriptlets, similar thing here.
You want to minimize the number of declarations
in a JSP page and also avoid dumping thousands
of lines of code in the JSP.
Also, you want to refactor this into
separate Java classes or make use of MVC,
and I'll cover all of that later in the course.
So in general, don't overdo it with JSP declarations.
Let's move into Eclipse and I want to continue
to use the existing project, jspdemo.
And what I'd like to do is move down
to this WebContent folder and I'm gonna add a new file.
So I'll simply do a right-click,
I'll say New, File.
So I'm gonna create this new file.
The name of the file I'll call it declaration-test.jsp.
And once you're happy with the file name,
you can go ahead and click Finish.
All right, so here's our file.
It's empty; we need to add some code here.
So I'll start off with my normal html and body.
And now what I'd like to do is actually declare
a method so I use the JSP syntax,
angle bracket, percent, with the exclamation point.
So at this point, I can actually start writing
normal Java code, so I'm going to write a Java method.
So we have return type string,
method name of makeItLower,
input data of string, and inside I'll actually
write the real implementation code.
And again, this very trivial example,
I'll just say data.toLowerCase.
And that's really it for this method declaration.
So again, with JSP, you make a declaration
by using the angle bracket, percent,
with the exclamation point.
Okay, great, so we have the method declared.
Now let's use this method.
So here, I'll have some text, lower case,
actually I'll say lower case hello world,
and then I'll make use of that JSP expression.
So I can call that method declaration.
So I say makeItLower, and I pass in some data,
call it hello world, and then there we go.
So that's an example here of making a call to that method.
And I call it by making use of a JSP expression.
So the result of this method call here
will be included here right in this page.
All right, so let's go ahead and run the application.
So I move over here to this file declaration.jsp,
I'll do a right-click, and I'll say Run As,
Run on Server.
And then the browser will come up with our result
so we have lower case hello world,
then we have, of course, the lower case version
of the hello world string.
And that's it, and that's the result of our
JSP expression making a call to our method
that we declared using a JSP declaration.
Good, so we kinda pulled it all together
with a nice little example.
Good job.
All right, so let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
So in this video I showed you how to use JSP declarations.
We created a declaration and then we called that
declaration from a JSP page.