Hey, in this video I'm gonna show you how to
call a Java class from JSP.
Now, in the previous videos, I mentioned that you
wanted to minimize the scriptlets and declarations in a JSP.
You wanna avoid dumping thousands of lines of code
in your JSP.
Now, it's okay to add small bits of scriplet,
small bits of declarations, but don't overdo it.
So, in order to kinda help with this problem,
you can refactor your code into a separate Java class
or make use of MVC.
So, in this video, I'm actually gonna show you
how to refactor that into a separate Java class.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna have a JSP file
and this JSP file is gonna actually call a
separate Java class.
So the Java class'll have all of our code,
all of our business logic, and so on,
and the JSP can simply make a call, let the Java code
or the Java class do the heavy lifting,
and then the JSP can get the results and
continue on with its processing.
Now, whenever I build videos like this,
I always like to put together a to do list.
So, the first thing we need to do is create the Java class.
Once we have the class created, we're gonna call our
Java class from the JSP page.
Alright, so a lotta good things in store here.
Let's go ahead and dig in and start coding.
Alright, so what I like to do is move into Eclipse.
And what we're gonna do is we're gonna continue to use
an existing project, jspdemo.
And the first step here is creating a Java class.
So, I'll move into Java resources, source, and actually
I'll create a package first.
So I'll create a package,
alright, just a location to place
our Java class.
So the name of our package will be com.luv2code.jsp.
And you can go ahead and hit the finish button.
So this creates the package.
Now I'm gonna actually create my Java class in this package.
So I'll simply do a right click, and I'll say new, class.
And, for the name of the class,
I'm gonna call it FunUtils.
And I'll keep all of the other defaults,
and once I'm happy with this,
I'll go ahead and click the finish button.
Okay, great, so we have our basic class
here that's lined up.
So what I wanna do is create a method in this class.
And it's the actual method makeItLower.
So I'll make this method static, so
public static String makeItLower,
we pass in a string parameter.
And then again, very trivial method here,
return data.twoLowerCase.
So again, this is the same method we use in our
declarations example.
Here I'm simply gonna refactor it and put it into this
Java class.
So I'll save my file up top.
And so I have this method here, makeItLower, that's part
of this class FunUtils.
Okay, great.
So now what I'd like to do is create a JSP file
that's gonna actually call this class.
So I'll move down to my web content directory
and I'll do a right click, and I'll say new, file.
Now, the name of this file, I'll actually call it
fun-test.jsp.
Because we're testing out the FunUtils.
And once I'm happy with this name here I'll go ahead
and click the finish button.
So I'll go ahead and take care of my basic tags here
for html and body.
And let's have some fun here.
(laughs)
I'm gonna make a call using the JSP expression
and I'll call that method that's defined in that class
but I have to give the fully qualified class name.
So I need to give the package name dot the class name dot
the method name.
And so I'll call makeItLower and I'll pass in "FUN FUN FUN".
Because we're having a lot of fun here.
(laughs)
Alright, so this looks okay.
Well, not really.
There's a lot of stuff going on here.
I'll break it down for you.
So we have this JSP expression.
And we're gonna call this class that's in a package
called com.luv2code.jsp.
That's the package name.
And then the actual class name is FunUntils.
And then the method name is makeItLower.
Ugh. Lotta stuff.
We can actually clean this up a bit by making use of
an import statement.
So what I'll do up top is in a JSP page you can actually
import a class.
So use the angle bracket percent with an "at" symbol
and you say page import and then you give the name of the
package or the class that you wanna import.
So here I'm gonna do an import on com.luv2code.jsp.FunUtils.
And now I can clean up the reference here in the
JSP expression.
So here's my page import: com luv2code jsp dot FunUtils.
So the class is FunUtils.
I could also make use of the wild card if I like,
just using a star if I had more items in there.
And then also the other common question is, well,
what about importing additional packages?
Well, you simply give a comma delimited list of packages
or classes that you wanna import.
And that's it.
So, if we wanted to use ArrayList, that's how we'd
go about it.
But we're not using ArrayList here, so I'll just
go ahead and take it out.
But again, just a comma delimited list.
Alright, so that's my FunTest.jsp, save the file.
Now I can go ahead and run this fun test,
so I can do a right click.
I'll say "run on server".
And it'll prompt me to restart the server.
That's because I added a new class and it needs to do
some class loading.
So just go ahead and hit "okay".
It'll go through it's little process.
But at the end here, we'll have our output.
So, there it is.
"Let's have some fun".
And then we have "fun fun fun".
All lowercase.
Remember, the code example, it was in all caps.
Now it's in all lowercase.
So we know that we are actually calling that method
that's defined in that Java class.
So great.
So this is really good.
So we were successful in having a JSP make a call
to a Java class.
Alright, so let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
So we went through the development process of
calling a Java class from a JSP.
Good job.