Hey.
In this video, I'm gonna show you how to make
use of JSP Built-In Server Objects.
So, with built-in server objects,
these are given to you for free.
So, there's no need to create them,
you can simply use them directly in your JSP page.
And you've actually played around with some of this
earlier and I'll show you this in the next slide.
So, here's a list of the commonly used
JSP Server Objects.
So, starting here, at the top with request.
It contains information about the HTTP request headers
and also form data.
We're gonna use this a lot in some of the following
videos for reading form data.
There's also the response object for sending back
HTTP specific information
and we'll use this also in the following video
on making use of cookies.
Now, this one server object you used already,
the out object, and we used that for our out.print line
in one of the previous videos.
So, again a built-in server object, given to you for free.
Now, there's two others here.
Session. It's a unique session for each user.
You can kind of think of the session option as
kind of like a shopping cart.
You know, each user has their own unique shopping cart.
I will use this in the following video.
And finally there's the application object.
So, this is shared for all users of a given web app.
And I'll discuss various use cases
on how to use the application object.
Now, just a full disclaimer,
this is not an exhaustive list.
There are other server objects out there,
but these are the ones that are
most commonly used for JSP web apps.
Alright, so here's the idea.
You have the browser communicating with JSP.
Behind the scenes, the HTTP protocol,
they actually send over a request object.
This request object contains header information
and body information.
The JSP can perform some work on that information
and then send back a response.
So, we have the whole request/response protocol going.
In the demo, I'll actually show you
how to make use of the request object.
Alright, so lets go ahead and move into Eclipse.
What I'd like to do is
continue to use the existing project, jspdemo.
Now, I'd like to move down to the folder here: WebContent,
because we're actually gonna create a new file.
So, I just say right click, I say New, File.
Now, the name I'll give here, I'll call it builtin-test.jsp
because we're, of course, testing some of the
built=in objects.
And once you're happy with the name,
we'll go ahead and click: Finish.
Okay, great.
So, let's expand the window, here, for a second
and that way we have a blank file,
we can just start writing some code.
So, again, I start off with my html
and my body information.
I'll just set up a header 3,
just to give us a little name here for the page.
And then what I wanna do is I actually wanna
read some information about the request.
So, I wanna find out what type of browser
the user is using to access my JSP page.
So, you can access this information
using the request object.
So, I can say request.getheader,
and then you give the header name of User-Agent.
So, this will tell you the actual browser
that the client is using.
Also, it'll tell you the operating system
that they're running on.
So, I'm gonna go ahead and add some line breaks, here.
And now I also wanna find out what language the
client is making use of in their browser.
So, if they're using English,
Spanish, German, French.
So, here I say request.getlocal
and this'll give me the actual local that the user
has set up on their system.
So, we could use this to customize the type
of pages we send the user based on their actual local.
Like English or German or Spanish.
And that's basically it for this very basic demo, here.
So, go ahead and save your file,
and now let's go ahead and run this program.
So, I'll move to the file builtin-test.jsp,
I'll do a right click,
and I'll say run as, and then run on server.
Okay, great. So, the application runs.
Note here request user agent.
So, they'll tell us the type of browser
that's coming through.
So, here we're using this internal browser
that's built-in as part of this Eclipse tool.
But note it also says that we're using a Mac OSX.
So, we know the operating system and the browser
that user's running on.
Let me copy this information
and put into a different browser.
I'll drop it into Chrome and I'll just paste it.
And I'll just hit: Enter.
And so now, we get the same information
but note here it says Chrome.
So, they give us the actual Chrome browser that we're using
and the version, Mac OS,
and also the request language in English.
So, again you could possibly use this to customize
the different pages you want to send back to the user
based on their browser type, OS type,
or their language type.
So, good job.
An example of using that built-in request object.
Okay, great. Let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
In this video, I showed you how to use some of the built-in
server objects.
We may use the request object to find out the user's
operating system and browser.
In the following videos, we'll do a drill down into
some of the other objects,
and you can kind of see them
working out real world, for the various use cases.