Hello, in this video I'm gonna show you how to use JSP
for including other files.
So the common use case for including files is
including standard headers and footers.
So, say for example, you're building a website and you want
to have the same header and footer information displayed
on every page.
So you can simply create the header and footer
in separate files and include them in your JSP files.
Alright, so when you include a file, you can include
either HTML files or JSP files, it's totally up to you.
So at the top here, I do a jsp:include,
and page equals my-header.html.
A similar thing here at the bottom.
I can do a jsp:include, page equals my-footer.jsp.
And that's it.
Very simple, very straightforward.
Alright, so let's go ahead and try this out.
So let's move into Eclipse.
What I'd like to do is to continue to use
that existing project, jspdemo.
And let's move down to the WebContent folder,
and what I want to do first is create those files
I'm gonna include.
So first I'm gonna create the header file,
so I'll say New File,
and I'll give the file name of my-header.html.
So that's the header that we're gonna include.
And when you're happy with the file name here, click Finish.
So for the header, I simply want
to give the name JSP Tutorial.
So I'm going to set up h1,
and I'll make the alignment for it to be center.
And then inside the tag here, I'll just say JSP Tutorial.
So this'll be included on all pages
for my given website that I'm just making up right now.
So I'll go ahead and save this file.
So this is our header file that we have set up right now.
Now let's move over and let's create our footer.
So again, in WebContent, I'll do a right click,
I'll say New File,
and I'll call it my-footer.jsp.
So in the footer we actually want to add some JSP coding.
So once we're happy with the file name,
go ahead and click Finish.
So, for here, for the footer for every page,
I want to give the time the page was last modified,
or we're just gonna kind of make this up actually.
So here I'll just say last modified, or last updated,
and then I'll just drop in the actual date and time stamp.
So that way, all of our pages look fresh every time a user
will visit our website.
Now I'll just hit the Save button.
Okay, great, so now at this point
we have our header complete
and we also have our footer complete.
So now we can go ahead and create our main page,
that's actually gonna include these files.
So I'll move over to the WebContent folder,
I'll do a right click,
I'll say New File,
and I'll call this homepage.jsp.
And once we're happy with the name here, we'll click Finish.
So on this homepage, what we're gonna do is
we're actually gonna include information
from the headers and the footers, and also we'll put some
of our regular content here.
So I'll do the standard work here for our HTML and our body.
And now I want to do is import, or include, the header.
So I'll say jsp:include,
I give page equals my-header.html.
And now I can enter some regular content
that I'll have on my homepage.
Here I'm just gonna put in some filler stuff,
just some blah blah blah,
just to, you know,
placeholders here.
And then I'll copy this line x number of times,
just to kind of fill it up a little bit.
So that's our content.
Let's go ahead and include our footer.
So I'll say jsp:include, page equals my-footer.jsp,
because our footer is a JSP file.
And again, it can go either way, HTML or JSP,
depending on how you want to build out your pages.
And that's it, so I can go ahead and save this file,
and then I can go ahead and run it.
Alright, so I can move over to this file homepage.jsp,
I can do a right click, then I can say Run As,
and then Run on Server.
Okay, great, this looks really good.
So up top, we have our header file
that we included, JSP Tutorial.
Then we have all of our body, our blah blah blah stuff.
And then we have the actual footer.
And then notice how the footer is a JSP,
and it included the current timestamp
when this page was accessed.
So our site will always look fresh as far as fresh content,
which is a good thing, right?
(chuckles)
So, good job.
In this video, I showed you how to build JSP pages
by including other files.