Hi. This is Chad Darby with luv2code.com
and welcome to my course on Java Server pages.
The main objective of this course is,
I want to show you how to build a JSP
web application all from scratch.
So here's the course road map.
The first thing we're going to do is learn how to get
started with JSP by setting up our Development Environment.
Then we'll explore some JSP scripting elements.
Next, we'll learn how to read HTML form data with JSP.
And then, I'll show you how to
manage application state with Cookies and Sessions,
and then we have a lot of more things that we'll
add to the course, so a lot of good things
coming up in this course for you.
Now, one thing about the course is that,
all of the source code is available for download.
So, you can download the source code at the beginning
and then you can follow along with
the videos and review the source code,
or you can write it in all by yourself, if you'd like.
It's totally up to you.
You have the option.
I'll present a lot of good information in the course,
however, you still may have a question or need help.
No problem, simply post the question in the Udemy
classroom discussion and I'll come through and answer it.
I'm a very responsive instructor,
so I normally respond within the next 24 hours.
Feel free to post your questions to the Udemy discussion.
Okay, great a lot of good information
coming up here for this course.
I'm excited and I hope you are too.
We'll have a lot of fun in this course,
so stay tuned for the following videos.