Hey!
In this video, I'm gonna show you how to install the
JSP Standard Tag Library.
All right, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
What we're gonna do here is we're actually
gonna create a new project.
So, I'll go to the file menu and I'll say
new, and I'll choose Dynamic Web Project.
And once the window's open here, for the project name,
we'll give the name of tagdemo.
And then I'll keep all the other defaults on this screen
and I'll hit the finish button.
All right, great.
So now I have this new project, tagdemo,
and it's empty right now.
Not much here, but I'm actually gonna add
some JST libraries.
So in the WebContent WEB-INF lib directory, it's empty,
I need to add some JAR files here.
Alrighty, so let's go ahead and open up
a web browser, and let's go visit this URL here:
luv2code.com/download-jstl.
This will allow you to download the JSTL JAR files
to your computer.
Your browser may prompt you, but eventually
it will download a zip file to your computer.
So I can find this file in my downloads directory.
On my computer, it will automatically
unzip that file.
So I'll have a directory here called jstl-libs.
Inside of this directory are two JAR files that I need
for JSTL.
One's the implementation, and the other is the API.
And you need both of these jar files.
So go ahead and select both of those files
and copy them.
And then, move over to your Eclipse project,
and we're gonna move into that WEB-INF lib directory
and we're actually gonna paste both of those files
into WEB-INF lib.
It's very important that you paste the files
into the WEB-INF lib directory.
This is a special directory that's a class path
for your web application.
Alrighty, great.
So once you've pasted those files here,
you should have two of them for JSTL.
Again, the first one is the implementation,
the second one is the actual API.
And you need both of those files in your project.
So, the first thing I need to do is
create a new file to test it out.
So under web content I'll do a right click,
I'll so new, file.
And then for the name of the file,
I'll just call it test.jsp.
It's a real simple test here.
Once you're happy with the name,
go ahead and click the finish button.
Okay, great.
So here's my simple file here at test.jsp.
Now let's go ahead and do our normal html housekeeping.
And, what I need to do here since I'm using a JSP tag;
I need to set up a reference to that tag library.
And I make use of it by using angle bracket percent
with an @ symbol, and this is new, I say, taglib uri,
I give the actual uri that's defined for this tag library...
So it's simply just a unique name or a unique identifier
for this tag library.
And you have to enter it exactly as I have here.
And then the prefix equals c.
So the prefix c is simply short for core.
So we're gonna make use of the core tag library here.
Okay, so this looks good so far.
So we have our tag lib reference set up.
All right.
So now, with that in place I can go ahead and try it out.
So I'll make use of one of the tags; c;set a variable
and I'm just gonna set this variable called stuff
and I'll give it a value of...
And I'll make use of the current time stamp.
So I'll just say new java util.date.
So basically I'm just creating a date object
and I'm assigning it to a variable.
And I'm gonna use that later on in my page.
All right, so there's a variable I have
it's called stuff, that was set using one of the core tags.
And now here I'll just say time on the server is...
And then I'll just display the value of stuff.
So I can make use of my JSP expression language,
that's the dollar sign curly brace,
and just give a reference to stuff.
And that's the same stuff that's defined on line seven.
So again, just a real quick example here
of making use of one of the core tags.
I'll go into more details in the following videos.
Just, wanted to just do a quick example here.
All right, so let's save the file.
Let's go ahead and run it.
And it'll prompt me on which server to use,
I always use it, hit okay for that, click finish,
and now it's up and running.
So in our internal browser here,
time on the server is...
And we crop in the time.
So this is really good.
So we actually make use of the JSTL core tag library
to set a variable, and then we simply displayed it.
Now, again, nothing really fancy here.
We'll get on to all the fun stuff later.
Just wanted to get everything set up.
Okay, great, so we have JSTL installed on our
local system and we'll make use of it in our
following videos.
Good job.