Hey!
In this video, we're gonna discuss the JSTL Core Tags.
So as you know there's a collection of
five tag libraries in JSTL.
So we'll take a look at some of the commonly used tags
in the Core library.
Now, in JSTL Core Tags,
there's a collection of about fifteen tags.
Now, we're not gonna cover all of them
but I will give you just a quick,
high level discussion of them.
So starting at the top, there's a catch tag
for handling exceptions.
The next two tags, for choose and if,
primarily for conditionals like using switch statements
or traditional if statements.
The next tag here is import for retrieving
relative URLs or absolute URLs.
The most commonly used on TRL forEach and forTokens.
Basically allows you to loop over a collection of data.
And we'll use that in this video.
There's the out tag for displaying output.
Otherwise is for handling the choose tag.
Params, redirects, removes, sets, URLs, and when.
So, again, a lot of tags here.
I'll cover the most commonly used tags in the video.
Hey, but don't worry.
You may wanna exhaustive, deep dive on each one of the tags.
At the end of this video I'll give you links
to documentation that covers each tag in detail.
So don't worry, I got you covered.
Alright, so, every page that makes use of the Core tags,
must include this reference.
So you have to yield the angle bracket percent
with an @ symbol.
You say taglib, and then give the uri.
So the uri must match exactly what you see here
on the screen.
And then you specify a prefix of C.
Now one thing about the uri is that
it's a bit misleading.
There's no real connection to the internet
to make use of this tag library.
It's simply a unique identifier.
They'll actually make use of this unique identifier
when they scan your local jar file
that's part of your project.
So again, no connection to the internet.
Simply a unique identifier that associates your tag
in the jar filed locally on your file system.
Alright so lets look at an example
of making use of that forEach tag.
So what I wanna do here is have a list of data,
and loop over it and display that data.
So, starting at the top, I'm gonna setup some sample data.
Now this is part of a scriptlet
and I know I say hey, use JSTL to minimize scriptlets,
but I'm basically using scriptlets here
just to load some sample data.
So, don't yell at me about this.
In general in the real world this'll normally
be provided by your MVC system.
And don't worry, later in the course we'll cover MVC
and I'll show you how to integrate MVC, which ASPs.
So don't worry.
But right now we're simply gonna set up an array
of cities Mumbai, Singapore, and my beloved Philadelphia.
And then I'll set this up as an attribute.
So whenever you make use of the JSTL tags,
they have to be part of an attribute
of one of the scopes either page request,
session or application.
So here I'm gonna set the pageContext.setAttribute.
I give the name of my cities comma
the reference of the object, cities.
So we give the name comma value pair.
Then I can move down into my body
and I can make use of this forEach tag.
So here I basically setup c:forEach,
so I give the prefix which is C, colon forEach,
and then I setup a variable tempCity.
So that's a temporary variable that we'll have
as we loop through this array.
So then for items I specify the reference
to the collection or array that I wanna loop over.
And I make use of a JSP expression language here.
So I use dollar sign, colon curly brace, myCities.
So this is the actual name of the attribute.
So it's not a direct reference of the object,
it's a name of the attribute, myCities.
Now, once I'm inside the for loop,
then I can simply make use of that temporary variable.
I can say dollar sign curly brace, tempCity.
And the break on it, and that's it.
So the desired output is what we'll see here
on the screen, we'll see our list of cities
displayed using this JCL.
That's basically it for the coding for that.
And in the next video I'll actually show you
some hands on coding while we'll write the code
for all of this from scratch.
Now as I mentioned, I'm providing some resources for you
to get all the details.
So if you wanted to get all the details
about every tag in the Core library,
you can make use of these references here.
So these websites that I have listed on the slide,
these are basically just redirects to the official
documentation from Oracle.
So I have links here for the custom tags tutorial,
JSTL tutorial.
The JSTL JavaDoc gives you the actual documentation
for every tag along with all of their attributes.
And then the JSTL Specification PDF again,
gives you more details on each one of the tags,
and their use cases.
So if you wanted details on every tag,
you can follow those resources.
Okay great, so the next video we'll actually
write some code, and we'll make use of this JSTL tag.
So I'll see you there.