All right, so let's go ahead
and move into Eclipse, and let's write some code.
So, in this tagdemo project,
I wanna move into my WebContent directory,
and I wanna add a new file.
So I'll just do right click, say new file.
So, the name of this new file, here, I'll call it
foreach-simple-test.jsp.
And once you're happy with that name,
you can go ahead and click on the finish button.
All right, so I'll expand the window here for a second.
I'm gonna go ahead and add in the taglib reference here.
So, I'm just gonna copy paste
from a little cheat sheet that I have because
I wanna make sure that I get this correct every time.
So, the angle bracket percent with the @,
taglib, and the uri, and basically follow
everything that I have here on this screen.
All right, so let's go ahead and set up a Scriplet.
I'm gonna set up a Scriptlet where I can
basically set up some sample data.
And again, like I said in a previous lecture,
this is normally set provided by your MVC system.
I'm just using this as a simple bootstrap here
for our demo.
So I'll define an array of cities,
Mumbai, Singapore, and Philadelphia.
And, as I mentioned earlier,
we need to set this as a page context attribute,
so here I'll say pageContext.setAttribute.
I'll simply give a name value here.
The name will be myCities, and the value will be
the reference to that city's array.
And that's basically it for setting up our sample data.
So here I'll just move down
and do some basic HTML body tags,
and now I'll make use of that core tag.
So, I'll say c:forEach.
And they'll kinda set up the basic tag here for me,
but I still need to fill in some of the blanks here.
So, on the forEach, I'll go through
and I'll set up the temporary variable.
I'll say var="tempCity," and then items=,
and I reference that attribute name,
so I'll use $.
And again, remember, it matches with the name
for the actual attribute that we set up
on line number seven.
All right, great, so now I can simply move in here
and make use of the temporary variable.
So, I simply make use of the dollar sign, curly brace,
and I say tempCity.
And then I simply just give a br for a line break.
And that's basically it for the body of this forEach tag.
All right, so we can go ahead and save this file,
then we can actually run it,
so I'll simply just do a right click on this
foreach-simple-test.jsp,
I'll say Run As, and then Run on Server.
And our JSP will execute, and great, here's our results.
So, we have our three cities listed,
Mumbai, Singapore, and Philadelphia.
And so, the nice thing about this
is that the output here was actually generated
by making use of that forEach tag
that's part of the JSP core.
So, good job so far.