Hey, in this video, we're gonna take a look
at some other examples using the forEach tag.
What we're gonna do is actually make use of HTML tables
with the forEach tag and we're gonna display information
for your list of students.
Here's the big picture here.
We're gonna have a Student object.
It's gonna have three fields.
It's gonna have a firstName, lastName,
and a boolean field if it's a gold customer.
And then what we're gonna do in our JSP
is we're gonna load up an array list of students
and then we'll actually loop through those students
using the forEach tag
and we'll use that to build up an HTML table.
All right, so that's the big idea, that's the big plan.
Let's go ahead and start coding.
All right, so I'm in Eclipse.
For this tagdemo project,
what I'm gonna do is actually start off
by creating a new Java package first.
I'll move down to the Java Resources directory,
to the src folder,
I'll do a right-click and I'll say New,
Package.
For the package name, I'll give com.luv2code.jsp.tagdemo.
Once I'm happy with that name,
I can go ahead and click the Finish button.
Okay, great, so we should have this new package
created for us right now.
What I'm gonna do here is actually create
a new class in this package
and I'll create this new Student class.
I'll do a right-click, I'll say New, Class.
The name I'll give for the class is Student
and on this screen, I'll keep all the other defaults
and I'll just hit the Finish button.
All right, so let me go ahead
and expand the window here for a second.
This is a very basic class.
It's gonna hold the firstName, lastName,
and goldCustomer for the student.
I'll say private String firstName.
Do the similar thing here for lastName.
I'll set this boolean field for goldCustomer,
and gold customer is like a VIP customer
or a special customer
that we may give special privileges to later on.
All right, so those are our fields.
Now, what I wanna do is create a constructor,
so I'll use an Eclipse tree.
I'll right-click, I'll choose Source,
I'll say Generate Constructor using Fields.
And so, Eclipse will come up with a list
of all of the fields that we have.
They're already preselected.
If not, you can hit the Select All, so they're all there.
And then go ahead and hit OK
and Eclipse will actually generate a constructor for you,
which is really cool. (chuckles)
Here's our brand new constructor
that Eclipse built for us on the fly
and this looks really good.
This saves a lot of typing and coding
that we have to manually do
just by taking advantage of Eclipse.
I'll also do a similar thing here
for our getter and setter methods,
so I'll let Eclipse generate this for me also.
So again, I'll just do a right-click.
I move to the Source
and I'll choose Generate Getters and Setters.
Eclipse will bring up the window.
We need to move over to the far right,
click Select All, make sure everything is checked,
as far as firstName, goldCustomer, and lastName.
And again, once we're happy with this,
we can go ahead and click the OK button.
Okay, this looks really good.
Eclipse created a lot of code for us here.
It created getters and setters for the firstName,
getters and setters for lastName, and also, isGoldCustomer.
Really, really good information here.
Great work by Eclipse. (chuckles)
We are very productive.
All right, so let's go ahead and save this file
and we can move over to our JSP page.
In my WebContent folder, I wanna create a new JSP page,
so I simply do a right-click,
I choose New, File.
The name I'll give for this file here,
I'll call it foreach-student-test.jsp.
And again, from there,
we can go ahead and click the Finish button.
All right, so let me go ahead
and maximize this window again.
And again, I'll also make use of my cheat sheet
to drop in a taglib for that core Tag Library.
All right, so remember,
we need to have exactly the same here as listed.
Also, I'm gonna need to make use of some packages,
so I'll need to do an import on java.util.*
and also do an import on our package we just created,
com.luv2code.jsp.tagdemo,
and that Student class.
Okay, great, so that takes care of our imports.
We imported two items here,
the java.util package and also the Student class
that we just created, so this looks pretty good so far.
All right, so I'll set up a scriptlet here.
And again, what I'm gonna do here
is set up our sample data.
I'll just create an array list of students.
And again, this is normally created by an MVC system
but for right now, we're just doing a quick test
just to bootstrap our system.
The first thing I'll do here
is create an array list of students
that's just empty right now.
In this array list, I'll go ahead and add a new student,
so I'll say new Student.
I'll use a constructor for John Doe
and then goldCustomer is false.
And then what I'll do here is I'll just copy-paste this line
x number of times
and I'll just add some more sample students here.
I'm gonna just copy this
and then just paste it one, two, three.
All right, great, so I'll go through
just change the names here real quickly for Maxwell Johnson.
And then I'll do a similar thing here
for another student, Mary Public.
And then I'll actually change her boolean value.
Instead of false, I'll set it to true.
And remember, that's for our gold customer,
our special, VIP customer.
This looks good so far.
We basically set up some sample data
that we can use in our application.
Oh, and there's one more thing I forgot.
We have to set this value as a attribute on the pageContext.
So, pageContext.setAttribute("myStudents",
and then I give the actual reference
to that array list data.
All right, so there we go.
We're really set up now, ready to go.
Good job.
All right, so I'll just go in here
and I'll just set up some HTML stuff, body.
All right, so for here, I like to go ahead
and make use of this forEach tag.
Here, I'll say c:forEach.
The variable equals tempStudent
and the items equals $.
And again, remember, it's the same name
that we use in the setAttribute up on line 13.
And now, I can make use of my JSP Expression Language here
to display information for the student's first name,
the student's last name,
and also, their gold customer status.
And remember, with the JSP Expression Language,
what actually happens in the background
is that they'll call the appropriate getter methods.
When we have tempStudent.firstName,
behind the scenes,
it will actually call tempStudent.getFirstName().
A similar thing here for last name,
will call tempStudent. the last name.
Now, for goldCustomer, it's a little bit different
because that's a boolean value.
Here, it will actually call tempStudent.isGoldCustomer.
But all of that work happens for you
automatically behind the scenes,
and that's part of the built-in JSP Expression Language.
All right, well, this looks good so far.
Let's save our file, and let's go ahead and try it out.
I'll go to this file here, foreach-student-test.jsp.
I'll do a right-click and I'll choose Run on Server.
Great, here's our output.
We have the student's first name,
the student's last name,
and then we have a value here, true or false,
if they're a gold customer or not.
This looks really good.
At least at this point,
we have the raw data being displayed.
What we can do is we can actually dress it up
to make use of HTML tables,
and I'll do that here in a second.
I'll move back into my JSP file here.
And now, we're gonna make use of HTML tables,
so let me go ahead and set up a basic HTML table tag
to get everything started.
I'll set up table.
I'll set border="1".
And I basically wanna include
all of this stuff inside of the table.
And now, I need to set up the table headers,
so we can have headers for the first name,
last name, and gold customer.
So first off, I set up a table row
and then I set up table header entries.
So, th is for table header.
I'll take care of the table header for first name
and then I just repeat the process
for last name and also, for gold customer,
and that will give me
the appropriate table headings at this point.
All right, so those are the table headers.
Now, let's go ahead and move into the forEach loop
and let's take care of the table rows for the data.
So, forEach, basically, for each student here,
I wanna set up a table row, and it's for tr.
And I'll get rid of that break.
We don't need that anymore.
And so, for each element here,
what I'll do is I'll just set up a cell.
A cell is td for table data,
so, angle bracket, table data.
And another thing here for td.
I'll do the same thing for firstName,
lastName, and also, goldCustomer.
I'll just repeat this process x number of times here.
Just giving some white space to make it look pretty.
And that's pretty much it.
This is our for loop
and our table rows,
and now, we'll make use of table data
for each one of those elements there,
for firstName, lastName, and goldCustomer.
That's the bulk of the work here
for doing our HTML table using the forEach tag.
Let's go ahead and save this file.
And then just go back to my browser
and I can simply refresh it because it's a JSP page,
so I select the little link here to refresh
and voila, there it is. (chuckles)
So, we have our HTML table that's generated.
We took care of our headers along the top
and then for each student in that array list,
we simply displayed a table row.
This looks really, really good.
Great job.