Hey!
In this video we're gonna learn about the JSTL Core Tag if.
So the if tag is used for a conditional test.
So basically the tag will evaluate an expression and
it'll display the body content only if the expression
evaluates to true.
And I have a nice little example of how we can use this
in our existing project.
So what we like to do is display Special Discount if
the student is a gold customer.
So here's a little code snippet of using this if tag.
So basically we say if and then we give test equals
and then we specify what we're testing.
So here I have a JSP expression.
Temp student dot gold customer.
Now again remember JSP will call the method for you
automatically in the background.
JSP will call temp student dot is gold customer.
This method, as you recall from the previous videos,
will return a value of true or false.
A boolean.
So if this value is true then it will display
special discount.
If it evaluates to false it won't display anything.
Alright, so a lot of good stuff here.
Let's move into Eclipse and let's try this code out.
Alright, so I'm in Eclipse.
I'm using this project tag demo.
And what I wanna do is move down to my WebContent folder
and I'm basically gonna make some enhancements to
our previous project.
So what I'll do is I'll actually copy our previous file
for each student test JSP.
I'll simply right click and copy that file.
And then likewise I'll right click and do a paste.
And I'll give it a new name here.
I'll call it if student test.
And once I'm happy with that name I'll go ahead and
click the OK button.
Alright.
So now I have this new file here if student test dot JSP.
It's basically a copy of our previous file.
We're simply gonna make some enhancements to it.
So everything that you see here is what we did
in our previous video.
I wanna move down to this section here for gold customer.
So remember, we wanna display a Special Discount if
the user is a gold customer.
Alright, so let me give me some space.
Some room to work here.
So I make use of the if tag.
C colon if test equals and then I put this expression
in quotes.
So again, JSP will call temp student dot is gold customer.
If that returns true then we'll display Special Discount.
If it returns false we won't display anything.
So just a very simply if then statement.
Alright so let's go ahead and try it out.
So I'll save my file.
I move over to the file.
I'll do a right click and I'll say run as run on server.
Okay good.
So this is some good results here.
So we have our students listed.
And then we have Mary Public and she's a gold customer
so it displayed Special Discount.
Notice for the other two students
it didn't display anything.
And let's just kinda review our data again.
And this is our test data.
So John, Doe, Maxwelll and Mary Public.
So Mary Public is the only one that's a gold customer.
She has a value of true.
And so that's why we have this given display
here on the screen.
So this looks really really good so far.
So we're making some good progress.
But what I'd like to do is somehow change this to
display something if they're not a gold customer.
So how can I do that?
Well, you would normally think you could make use of an
else statement but unfortunately this tag library
doesn't have an else for ifs.
So, kinda weird I know.
What we can do is we can just check the inverse.
So here I can say test equals not temp gold student.
So basically I'm checking to see
if it's not a gold customer.
If it's not a gold customer then I'll display something
different.
So here I'll just put a little dash meaning just
ya know, nothing.
We can say whatever we wanted to here for the body
but I'll just keep it simple and put a dash here.
And so this is how we can make use of an else kinda sort
kinda doing a hack work around.
But don't worry, in a following video I'll show you
some other options for handling this
type of scenario.
But let's go with what we have for right now.
So I'll save the file.
Move back to my browser.
And I will simply refresh the page.
Wow, this looks awesome.
Okay, good.
So now if they're not a gold customer we will display
a dash.
If they are a gold customer
then we display Special Discount.
Right.
So this is pretty cool.
And you can think of all different types of ways of
how you could use this in your application.
But this is good so far so great job.