Hey.
In this video, we're going to learn
how to use the choose tag.
So, JSTL has a choose statement.
This tag is very similar to a switch statement,
so we can basically test some conditions,
and then we'll have an otherwise, or default, handler.
I'll show you some code examples on how to do this.
Here's our basic example that we've been working on so far.
I'll make use of the choose statement,
and then we can put in different cases we want to test for.
The first one here,
when test="$"
so if they're a gold customer, will display special student.
Else, we have an otherwise here,
and that'll handle all the other cases.
You can add as many when conditionals as you'd like.
All right, so let's move into Eclipse,
and let's try this out with a code example.
What I like to do is move down to my WebContent directory,
and I'm going to basically copy our previous files,
our if-student-test.
We're going to copy this one,
and make some enhancements to it.
So I'll simply do a right-click,
and I'll choose Copy.
And then likewise, I'll simply just
do a right-click and choose Paste.
Then on here I'll give it a new name.
The new name, I'll call it choose-student-test.jsp
All right, and then once your happy with the filename,
just go ahead and hit the OK button.
All right, so here's our file.
Let me just go ahead and open it up here,
choose-student-test.jsp
Expand my window here,
and again, everything's like we had in a previous video.
I simply want to make use of the choose statement here,
and kind of work around that little hack we had
for not having an else statement previously.
So here I'll say
c:choose
I'll add the end tag for it,
and I'll move it down to the bottom.
Now this first if test, I'll change this to a when,
'cause this is my new test case I'm setting up.
And I'll also set up the matching when here.
Okay, great, so
when test="$"
then we'll display Special Discount.
And again, we can copy this when clause,
X number of times for different cases.
But here, this is kind of our else statement,
that we kind of did a little hack workaround with.
This is how we can clean it up here.
I can say c:otherwise
So basically, if none of the when clauses match,
then otherwise it'll execute this portion.
So otherwise, we'll just simply give a dash.
Let me just tab this in a bit
so we can see all the flow formatting together.
All right, now one thing I want to do is the otherwise.
Instead of the dash, I want to give something different,
something funny. (laughs)
Let's have fun with this.
So I'll say, "no soup for you!"
That's a classic quote from
an American TV show, Seinfeld.
So anyway, no soup for you
if you're not a Special Gold customer. (laughs)
All right, so that's basically our layout here.
We're testing for Gold Customer,
and if you don't match, then no soup for you.
So let's run this one.
I'm having too much fun here.
Right-click on choose-student-test.jsp,
Run As, Run on Server.
Okay, great, woo-hoo!
Here's our output.
So if they're not a Gold Customer,
we say, "no soup for you!"
And if they are a Gold Customer,
then we show Special Discount.
We did all of this stuff using that new choose tag in JSTL.
Hey, this looks really, really good.
Great job.