Hi, in this video we're going to learn
how to update a student in our application.
So we'll cover the following topics:
first I'll give you a demo of the Update Student feature,
then we'll also take a look at the big picture,
and finally we'll take a look at the sequence diagram
just to see how all the parts work together....
All right, so here's a demo of the application,
so I'm going to show you how the new Update feature works.
So notice here we have a new column called Action,
and we have these Update links, so basically
what this Update link will do it'll actually show you
a new form and it'll pre-populate that form with data.
So here I'm updating the student Lisa Astor,
so again, notice how the form is already pre-populated
with her information.
Now let's say for example Lisa was married, recently married
and she wants to change her last name to
her new married last name, so we can type in
her new last name here, and then also she wants to change
her email address, so now this is funnylisa
and she's actually has a separate address for Gmail,
so funnylisa@gmail.com, so that's all of her new information
here that we want to update for her, uh, system.
All right, so let's go ahead and hit the Save button...
And good, so here's our new updated lists,
so again we sort the students by last name,
so Lisa Mangano, her new married name,
and then also her email address, funnylisa@gmail.com,
so this worked out just right, I mean,
we updated an existing student.
Now in the video series here, we're going to break it up
over multiple videos, and I'll actually show you
how to build all this functionality out from scratch.
All right, so here's the big picture.
So, up in the top left, we start off with
the list of students along with that new column there.
They select that new column action for update.
It'll take them to the form, pre-populated as we saw
in the demo, and from there we'll send the data
over to the Student Controller servlet
that'll read the form data and then it'll pass it off to
the Helper Class, our database util, and remember
the database util handles all the low-level JDBC work.
Now one little thing here about the action link.
When they click on update, each link has the student id
embedded in the link, so when they click the link,
what we'll actually do behind the scenes that,
we'll actually load the student data from the database
and then we'll use that to pre-populate the form, all right,
so you'll learn all the mechanics there
on how to pre-populate a form with data from the database,
so a nice little bonus there for you.
And finally, once you have the form pre-populated
with information, then this is the sequence diagram
for actually saving the student or updating the student,
so they hit the Save button, we call Update Student
on our controller, and we pass over special command
for update, and then from there we send it over
to our database util to actually update the student.
So that's the basic process, that's the basic
sequence diagram for how all the different components
work together, and again we'll walk through all of this
in the video setup....
All right, back to my favorite to-do list.
So, the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to update the list of students,
so we're going to add that new column there
for an update link, then we'll create
our update student form, and we'll use that form
to pre-populate it with data for a given student.
Then, we're going to update our controller servlet,
so we're going to handle requests that are coming in
to our updated student, and then finally we'll update
our Student DbUtil, so that's where we'll add
the low-level JDBC code for doing an update.
And again, we'll break this up over a series of videos,
we'll deep-dive into each step, we'll do everything
step by step, and we'll code everything from scratch,
just like we've done before.
All right, so, a lot of stuff in store,
I'm excited again and again, so let's go ahead and dive in,
and let's write some more code, yeah.