All right, so let's get started.
So, the first item on our To Do List here
is to update the list-students.jsp
and add the new "Update" link.
So, the main thing here is that
we're gonna have this new column
that we're gonna add, and this column's
gonna have an Update link for each student.
Now, this link will actually contain the embedded student ID
and we'll be able to use this later on
when we need to pre-populate the form.
We'll cover that later, but for right now
the main focus of this video is simply
to create that new column and also
create the Update link for each student.
All right, so let's go ahead and move into the clips.
The main focus here is to update
the list-students.jsp and to add that new column.
All right, so I have the file open.
Let me go ahead and expand the file
and then let's move down to the section
where we set up our table headers.
And what I'm gonna do here is add a new column,
so I'll have a new column here called "Action."
All right, so we have our column in place now.
Now, the next thing we need to do is actually
set up a reference here for the actual Update link,
so I'll set up a new piece of information here
and instead of doing the real link for right now
I'll just put some little placeholder text
just to kinda get us going for right now.
So, a little to do comment to myself to add a link here.
I just want to make sure that I have our normal
html stuff laying out properly
before I get into all of the link stuff.
All right, so let's go ahead and test this file here
for a second, so I'll just do a quick run.
And okay, this looks good, so we have our new column
called Action and we have our little
to do statement for add a link here.
So, this is good so far.
So, we have the basics in place, but now
let's get into all the fancy coding aspect of it.
So, I'll move back into my list-students.jsp
and the main thing here is that I want
to actually set up a link for each student.
And in order to help me create these links
I'm actually gonna make use of a JSTL feature called URL.
So, this'll actually define a link to a URL
and we can also pass some parameters to it,
so it's a very nice feature.
So this is one of the JSTL tags we'll make use of here,
and you'll see it kinda real world, see how it works.
So, I'm gonna set up a variable name for that URL
called tempLink, and then for the value itself
I'll point to our student controller servlet.
Now, I have two parameters that I want to send over
to the student controller servlet,
but first parameter is I'll give the actual command.
So, we'll have a new command called LOAD,
then the next parameter which is
really important is the actual studentId.
I want to be able to give the actual studentId
of this student that I'm using right now,
so I'll say tempStudent.id, and note here
I'm using the JSP expression language
to get the current ID of that student.
So, in effect it's gonna create multiple links here
for each student with their embedded ID already in there.
Now, let me take this link and actually
use it in my table, because up above
we only defined it, we didn't actually
display it or reference it.
So, here I'll set up an HREF and I'll point
to this tempLink that was defined up on line 43,
and then I'll give the actual text
that you'll see in the table, Update.
So, this'll basically create an HREF
with the text of Update, and then
embedded is the actual tempLink
that has the command and the student ID.
All right, so that's how we pull it together,
that's how we can embed a link.
Let's go ahead and test it out and see what it...
See how it works.
So, again, I'll go back to my application.
I'll simply do just a refresh on this page.
And cool, this looks good.
So, here's our Action column and now
we have these HREF links called Update,
and if you just kind of scroll over each one
of those links in the bottom left
you'll notice that the ID changes,
and you may not be able to see it because of the video,
but what I'll do is I'll actually copy
one of these links and I'll just put it into a text editor
just so you can see what's behind there.
So, here's one of the sample links there,
so it's gonna send something to the
student controller servlet, command=LOAD, and studentId=5.
So, the really cool thing about it is that
that value of studentId will change for each student.
So, each link has a unique studentId that it's
pointing to because we built this up dynamically.
So, this is really cool.
So, we have the first part of it taken care of.
In the following video I'm gonna show you
how to update our controller servlet to actually
read the command and also read the studentId
and use that information to pre-populate the form,
but this is a good first step and we have a lot of
good things coming up in the next video,
so I will see you there.