Alright, so we've finished our first
step of updating that list of students JSP.
Now our next step is creating the update student form.
And what we wanna do with this form is actually prepopulate
the form, when we show it.
So when the user selects a student, we're gonna prepopulate
the form with that student's information.
Now there's some behind the scenes work that we need to do.
And the first thing is updating our
StudentControllerServlet.
This Servlet's gonna need to read that new LOAD command,
and route it accordingly.
And then once we have that LOAD command read, we need to
read the student id from that form.
And then, take that information and read the student
from the database or get the student from the database.
Once we have the student, then we wanna show the form
and prepopulate the form with that student's data.
Alright, so let's go ahead and open the code here for our
StudentControllerServlet.
Alright, so here's our Servlet, let's go ahead and move
down to the do get method.
Alright, so this is the do get method
where we read in the actual command.
And what we wanna do now is add support
for the LOAD command.
So we need to add a new case here,
in our switch statement for the case of LOAD.
So I'll just say case LOAD,
and then I'll call a method load student.
And I'll pass in a request and a response.
And then I'll just do a break.
So this is great, well, it's almost great.
Again, Eclipse is giving us an error message and let's
kinda hover over that error message and see what it's about.
And it's Eclipse saying, "Hey, buddy, you don't have this
method defined."
So then again, like we've already done before, we'll tell
Eclipse to go ahead and create that method for us.
So, I'll simply select that second option,
and then I'll just scroll down here.
And here's a new method that Eclipse created for me.
And again, we love it when Eclipse does work for us.
So, what I wanna do here, is I wanna remove that
Auto-generated code, and I wanna start adding my own code.
So, the first thing I know is that I need to add a throws
clause here for this method.
So I'll say, "throws Exception".
So, then I'll go ahead and write some comments as far as
what I need to do in this method.
So the first thing is getting
the student id from the form data.
The next thing is getting the student from the database.
Then we go ahead and place that student
in a request attribute.
And then finally, we send this to our JSP page.
That's our update-student-form.jsp.
So those are the steps required for us
to actually load the student.
And again, we're doing all this preliminary work,
just so we can prepopulate the form.
Alright, so I can read the student id, by simply saying
the student id equals request dot get Parameter, student id.
And that's passed over by that update link.
Then I can talk to my database util, and get the student.
So I say, the student equals
student db util dot get student.
And I'll get the student based on their id.
So I'll tell them, "Hey, give me the student for this
given student id."
Next, what I wanna do, is take that student object
and then place it in a request attribute.
Cause our JSP page can use that to prepopulate the form.
So in here I'll just give
the attribute name of, "THE_STUDENT".
And then the actual value a reference here,
it'll be the object on line 84, the student.
And, hmm, seems to have an error here.
Okay, yeah there's a typo, on line 84.
I didn't spell student properly,
so I just did a copy, paste to fix that.
So now we're good with that one.
Okay, good.
Next what we need to do is go ahead and set up a request
dispatcher to send it to that update student JSP form.
So, again this is kind of standard MVC code
that we've written before.
So I'll get request dispatcher,
on update student form dot JSP.
And then finally we'll do a forward.
So, dispatch dot forward, and then I pass in
that request, response object.
Alright, so looking pretty good here,
there's one error message here.
And I'll kind of float over to see what it says.
But basically it's Eclipse saying that, "Hey we don't have
that method defined in student db util".
Okay, great so that means we need to add the method,
to get the student from the database.
So I'll go ahead and tell Eclipse
to create that method for me.
So I'll select the second option there.
And now I'm in the student db util class.
And right now it created a basic method, and I need
to go ahead and flush it out with my own code.
So for right now, just kind of stub it out with student,
the student equals null.
And I'll simply say return the student.
And now what I wanna do here is just
put in some comments here.
Well actually I'll go ahead and create some of my
initial JDBC objects first.
So this is for the connection, my Conn.
I'll set up my statement, which is a prepared statement.
And I'll also set up a results set.
And I'll set all these values equal to null.
And then I'll sneak in another variable here,
for the student id, which we'll use a little later.
As far as ints.
Alright so let me go ahead and set up
a little try finally block here.
Alright, so I have that kind of stubbed out now.
And again following my standard procedure here,
I always write some comments just to keep myself on track,
when I get ready to start writing some code.
So we convert the student id to an int.
We get the connection to a database.
Next we'll create a SQL to get the selected student.
And then I'll go ahead and create my prepared statement.
Based on that SQL.
And then I'll go through and set the parameters here.
So it knows which student id to get.
And then finally I'll actually execute that query
and then I'll get a result set.
So then once I have the result set, then I need to process
that result set and retrieve the data from that actual
result set row.
And then in my finally block I do my normal
clean up of those JDBC objects.
We just basically close off the connection statement
and result set.
But anyway just kinda steppin' back for a bit.
These are all the major steps here that I need to
accomplish in this method, to actually
get a student from the database.
Alright well, let's get ready to write some code.
So the first thing is convertin' that student id to an int.
So we can make use of the integer
dot parse int to accomplish that.
So I just use the student id which is the string variable,
that's sent in as a method parameter.
And we convert it to an int student id.
Then I go ahead and get a connection to the database.
Data source dot get connection.
Next, I create the SQL to get the selected student.
So basically I wanna say, "Hey give me the student
that matches this given student id."
So, that's accomplished with select star from student,
where id equals the question mark.
And we'll fill that in, in a second.
Now we just go through and actually
create our prepared statement.
So my conn dot prepare statement based on that SQL string.
And next I go through and set the parameters.
So there's only one parameter, I'm simply setting the
first parameter there, that matches the student id.
And I have a couple of error messages here.
Oh, okay, great.
Unhandled exception, okay great.
So let me just scroll back up to the top of this method
here, and simply list that as throws exception.
So right here on line 114, I'll say throws exception.
And that'll resolve all the errors that were just
popping up there in that method.
So the key here is throws exception.
Alright so we can kinda get back to coding now.
(laughs)
Alright, so now we wanna go ahead and execute that statement
and it's gonna give us back a result set.
So here I'll say my rs equals
my statement dot execute query.
That's gonna return that result set.
Alright so now I have this result set.
Now I have to process it or retrieve the data from
that result set row.
And effectively what I'm gonna do here is retrieve the
data for a given student.
So here I'll just set up a little if conditional.
Say if my rs dot next.
So it basically says, "Hey, do we have any rows to process?"
And if so, then let's go ahead and grab some of that data.
So I need to get the actual student's first name, last name
and email address.
So I just use the standard technique that we've seen before.
My rs dot get string first underscore name.
And again, first underscore name is the actual column
name from the database.
And then I'll just copy, paste this
for the other fields here.
For last name and email.
So here we have last name.
Last underscore name.
Then email.
And then my rs dot get string email.
And we already have the student id.
So we don't have to query that anymore.
Great, so now using this information, I can actually
create a new student object.
And when I construct the student, I'll actually use
the student id in the constructor.
So here I say the student equals a new student and then
I'll pass in student id, comma, first name, last name
and email address.
Alright and so the key here is that we are passing
in student id, because we need that later on when
we actually do an update.
We'll actually have to know which student,
that we're updating.
So for else that means we didn't find a student.
So here I'll throw an exception.
And I'll say new exception, cannot find student id,
and I list out that actual student id.
Alright so that takes care of this part of the coding here.
So basically we retrieved the data.
If there is data we grab the first name, last name, email.
We construct an object, else we throw an exception
if we couldn't find 'em.
Alright and then the final one.
This is really easy, we simply close those JDBC objects.
I close on my conn, comma my statement, comma my rs.
And that's it.
So this is in our student db util, the method get student.
Did all the low level JDBC work to actually
grab the student from the database.
Alright so now I can move back over to my Servlet now,
and so pretty much all the low level work on
lines 83 and 84, we just accomplished that.
We did the JDBC work inside of that database util.
Alright so these are all the major steps
here for loading a student.
We read the student id from the form,
we get 'em from the database.
We place that student in a request attribute and then
we forward it over to that update student form dot JSP.
Now we haven't created the form yet.
We'll actually do that in the next video.
But at least wanted to get the preliminary work taken
care of before we make it there.
So we're in really good shape right now.
So I'll see you in the next video.
Woo hoo.