In this video, we're gonna go ahead
and create our form, and pre-populate our form with data.
So we'll actually start with this add-student-form.jsp
and I'll basically copy this form and rename it
for the update form.
So I just do a right-click and choose Copy,
and then I'll just go through and paste.
So the name of this form, here I'll call it
the update-student-form.jsp.
And once we're happy with that name, we go ahead
and click on OK.
Alright, so let's go ahead and open up
our update-student-form.jsp.
I'll just walk through this form
and just do some cosmetic changes.
I'll just say "Update Student" as far as the title,
and then for the header, here I'll say "Update Student."
So just basic cosmetic changes there.
Now moving down to line 23, we're gonna change the command.
So instead of the Add command,
we're gonna display this new command,
or we're gonna enter this new command called Update.
So we'll send over an Update command
to our student controller servlet.
So let's go ahead and set the value here
for this text field.
So this is the value that's actually displayed
when the user actually sees the form for the first time.
And for the actual value, what we'll do is
we'll actually make use of that student object
that was set by the servlet,
and we'll say "THE_STUDENT.firstname."
So basically here by saying value equals,
this will actually pre-populate the field
with the student's first name.
Now you're looking at this and you're probably wondering,
"Well, why is it THE_STUDENT?"
Let's go back and look at our servlet.
On our student controller servlet, for the load feature,
or the load method, I'll scroll down a bit.
So when we would actually load a student,
down on lines 86 and 87, that's how we actually
set the student in the request attribute.
So we'd say request.setAttribute, we'd give THE_STUDENT,
that's the attribute name, and that's the actual
attribute name that you use in the JSP page.
So THE_STUDENT is the actual attribute name,
and we'll use that in our actual form.
Alright, so that kind of clears up the attribute item.
So here, I'll use THE_STUDENT, so that's the attribute name
set by the servlet, and I'll say THE_STUDENT.firstname.
And it'll call the appropriate getter method
to get the first name.
Now I'll just copy this entry here
for each one of the other fields,
I'll do the same thing here for last name.
And I'll do a copy paste, and I will change
this field here to say lastname.
So, again, this will pre-populate the field
with the student's last name.
And I'll do a similar thing here for the email address.
So I'll say THE_STUDENT.email.
Alright, so this looks pretty good.
So basically, this section of code here's what we use
to pre-populate the form with the information
from the student.
Their first name, last name, and email address.
Actually, there's one other thing that I forgot to do here.
I need to add a new hidden field.
So let me copy line 23, and let me move down and paste
a copy of that,
and I need to set up the actual student ID,
so I need to say,
the name is studentId, and the value is THE_STUDENT.id.
What we need to do is we actually need to
track that student ID,
so when we actually do an update,
and we send it over to the servlet,
the servlet knows which student ID we need to
perform an update for.
So the ID here is actually very important.
So I'm glad I remembered to add that.
Alrighty, so we can save this,
and we can actually go through and test this form right now,
just to make sure that I can actually load
the student and pre-populate it.
So let me go ahead and run my application here.
They show the page, along with the update links.
So let me kind of focus in on one of these students,
and just test this out.
So, for this first student here, Maxwell Dixon,
let's go ahead and click the update link.
It should show the form with his information pre-populated.
Cool, this looks really, really good.
So look. Here's Maxwell Dixon.
So what happened with that update link
is that we actually retrieved the student
from the database, and then we would
actually use that information to pre-populate the form.
So this is great.
Let's try it one more time with another student.
Let's go back to our list,
and I'll zoom in here on Mary Public.
And I'll click on update, and, OK, again.
Works out just fine.
So great, so this all works out just fine.
So the whole idea of pre-populating a form,
we've accomplished this
by making use of that command equals load,
and then we pass in the appropriate student ID.
So our servlet and DB util does work on the back end,
and then it sends it over to the JSP
to pre-populate the form.
So this is really good.
I'm happy, I'm excited,
because we're making some really good progress.
So, good job so far.