Alright, so we're making good progress here.
So we just took care of step two,
where we prepopulated the form.
Now we're going to move on to step three
of updating the student controller servlet.
So we're going to write codes to handle
the request to actually update a student.
So let's go ahead and jump into Eclipse.
The first thing here is updating
our student controller servlet
but I want to take a look at that JSP page,
our update student form dot JSP,
because there's some good information in here
that can guide us for our next set of coding here.
So this is update student and this is the file
that we just worked on in the previous video.
On lines 23 and 25, we actually have two hidden fields.
So we have command equals update
and then we have student ID and we give the student dot ID.
So these are two perams that we're
sending over to the servlet.
Our servlet now needs to read that information
and process on it accordingly.
So let me go ahead and open up
my student controller servlet.
I'll expand the window here,
move down a bit to our doGet method.
So this is where we read in the command.
And we need to add support for the update command.
So basically, it's just a matter of adding a new case here.
So we saw the previous example of case of load.
Now we'll do a case of update.
So I'll say case update and for this case,
I want to update student,
pass in the request and response and then do a break.
Alright, so that's the basic layout.
But again, Eclipse has a little error message
here that's saying update student
and if we hover over this message,
it will give us the actual error.
So it says, hey this method is not defined.
And again, Eclipse is our buddy, right
so we simply say, hey Eclipse,
go ahead and create this method for me.
Woo-hoo, just love it when Eclipse creates code for us.
So here's our update student that they created.
It's dubbed out right now.
And what I want to do here, is go ahead
and start writing some code in this method.
So the first thing I know I'm going to need to do,
is actually throw an exception.
So here, I'll just say throws exception
and I'll just lay this out first,
just in case there are any errors,
we can handle for it accordingly, or actually,
throw the exception to the calling program.
Now, I always like to go through and set up comments here,
just to kind of keep me on tract
as far as code that I need to write.
And the first thing I need to do
is read the student info from the form data.
And then I need to create a new student object
based on that form data and then,
I actually perform the update on the database.
And then finally, I'll send the user
back to the list students page.
So that's my basic game plan here
for the update student method.
Alright, so let me roll my sleeves up here
and get dirty and start writing some code.
So for reading the student ID from the form
or reading the actual ID,
so I'll say integer dot parseInt.
I'll say request dot get parameter: student ID
and that's that hidden form fill
that came in from the update form.
And then I'll go through
and read all the standard information.
Read the first name by saying
request get parameter, first name.
We've seen this stuff before.
And I'll just kinda copy paste this line
for last name and email address.
So I'll update it here for last name.
And I'll also update it here for email address.
Alright, cool so that's the basic work there
for reading the student info from the form data.
So now we have everything for a student
and I can use that down here on line 91
to actually create a new student object.
So here I'll say student the student equals new student
and I just pass in those parameters:
so ID, first name, last name, and email address.
Alright, that's good.
Then using this information,
I'll actually perform an update on the database.
So I'll make use of my student Dbutil
and I'll say update student and then
I'll pass in my student object: the student.
And then finally, I'll send them back
to the list students page so list students request response.
And that's that same method we created many moons ago
and I will simply list all the students.
But again, there is an error message here
so on line 94, Eclipse says that
it can't find the method, update student.
And again, I'll say, hey Eclipse, why don't you help me out.
Why don't you go ahead and create that method
for me in that student Dbutil?
So I'll select the option and now,
I'm in student Dbutil dot java
and here is this new method
that Eclipse just created for me.
So for now, I'll say do nothing.
I'll get into the details for it later
but at least I want to have this method
defined here in this class,
just so the code will compile for my actual servlet.
So if I move back to my sevlet,
then that error message goes away.
So we're in pretty good shape.
So this is all the coding here required
for actually doing the update student
so we read to student info, create a new student object,
perform an update on the database, and then
send them back to the list students page.
In the next video, we'll actually drill down
into line 94 and we'll actually do the JDBC code
for updating the student.
And I'll cover that in the next video
so I'll see you soon.