All right, so making good progress.
We've just completed step three.
Now we're gonna focus on step four,
updating our student database util
and again, this is where we're gonna add
our low-level JDBC code
for updating the student in the database.
All right, so just moving back to our servlet here
on line 94 is where we actually have the code
where we make a call to the StudentDBUtil updateStudent
but right now that's just a placeholder
and we need to write some real code inside of that method,
so let me go ahead and navigate to that method,
so I'll simply do a right click,
and I'll say Open Declaration
and again, this is the Eclipse trick.
This will actually take us to the code here
for StudentDBUtil,
so that's where I'm at, I'm in StudentDBUtil right now
and I have just this empty shell of a method here
for updateStudent
and what I'll do is I'll go ahead
and write all my real code here
for doing all the real JDBC work for us.
And let me stretch out, get some more white space here
at the bottom.
I'll clear out all the comments there.
I know I'll have throws Execution up top,
so I'm gonna go ahead and put that in for right now.
And let me just set up some JDBC objects first
and set everything to null,
so I'll set up a connection for myConn,
I'll set up a PreparedStatement,
and that's it.
Now I'll go through and write some comments,
again just to keep myself on track.
So, the first thing I'll do
is get a connection to the database.
The next thing I'll do
is I'll create a SQL update statement.
Then I'll actually prepare that statement
and then I'll set the params for that statement
and then finally, I'll execute the SQL statement
that'll actually perform the update on the database.
So, that's kind of the main game plan here
for updating a student.
All right, so let's start cutting some code here.
So, first off I'll get the data connection,
so I'll say myConn equals dataSource.getConnection.
Now I'll go through and actually set a SQL string here,
so I'll say String sql equals update student
and I'll set first_name equals to a question mark,
last_names equals a question mark
and email equals the question mark
and again, these question marks are simply placeholders
for those prepared statements
and I'll update the student where ID equals
and that's whatever the ID that we pass in.
So, that's the SQL
and also one thing here,
make sure you have an extra white space at the end
on lines 172 and 173
'cause they're gonna concatenate this string altogether
and you need to have a space there
and so you don't run into any problems
but that's the basic SQL there
for updating a student.
So, the next thing we need to do
is prepare the statement,
so here I'll say myStatement equals myConn.prepareStatement,
I pass in that SQL that I just created
from the previous line,
so that looks good.
Now I'll go through and I'll actually set the parameters,
so again, these question marks
are parameters and they start at position one
and they go left to right,
so I simply set the first parameter
which is the student's first name
and I'll simply copy this line
and I'll paste it for the other lines
for LastName and email,
so position two is LastName
and position three is email
and again it's all one base starting at one
and then that fourth parameter,
or our fourth question mark here
is ID, so I'll say myStatement.setInt(4, theStudent.getId).
All right, so that looks good there for the params,
then finally we just execute the statement,
so I'll say myStatement.execute and that's it.
Now, I also need to put this code in a try finally block,
so let me go ahead and do the finally here
and in the finally I actually want to do a clean up
on those JDBC objects,
so I'll say close and I'll close myConn, myStatement
and there's no result set,
so I'll simply pass in null for that,
so null means results set,
but there's no results set in this example
and I have a finally but no try.
Yikes.
Yucky.
So, I need to kind of fix this code up a bit,
so let me copy this finally stuff
and cut it and move it right here,
so there's my finally
and now I need to move up top
right at 168 and do a try.
Okay, so that kind of takes care of that,
so now I have a try block at the beginning,
scroll down, end the try block on 188
and okay, so I'm okay.
So, now let me go ahead and just tab this stuff in,
there we go, that's tabbed in
and click this stuff, tab this in,
so I kind of made a mistake,
I'm having a clean up here
but anyways, we have this try block up top.
All right, actually we'll start from the top,
so we have updateStudent
and I set up my JDBC objects
and then I do the try.
We roll through and we get our database connection,
we do our SQL stuff,
prepare the statement,
set some params,
and then execute, okay, cool,
and so 188 we have our closed curly for that try
and then we have our finally block here
which we clean up
and that close curly, good.
So, that's good, so we're okay now,
we're in good shape
and also just as a good checkpoint,
make sure you have two curly braces
right after that and then you should be okay
and if there's any syntax errors,
Eclipse will let you know
but there we go, we're all kind of laid out here,
so this looks good so far.
Great, so that's our low-level JDBC code here
for updating a student in the database.
Good job.
So, now I think we can go ahead and test this thing out.
So, let's go back to our app and run it.
And our app's up and running.
Okay, great, so now we should be able to update
a student, so let's select one of these students here
and update them.
So, let's see, I'll try Maxwell Dixon.
Okay, click on Update
and I'm gonna change his last name to Apples.
So, Maxwell Apples
and then I'll hit the Save button
and I'll take a look at the list
and whoa, yeah, all right,
so his last name was updated,
so Maxwell Apples is now in our class.
Good, let's try it one more time.
Let's see, Mary Public, okay, let's change Mary Public.
So, let's go and hit the Update button here
and we'll change her last name,
instead of Public she's Private.
I don't know, being geeky
like a Java public private detective.
So, now she's Private and we'll change her email address,
mary@gmail.com,
so we're updating last name and email
and then we can go ahead and click on Save
and yeah, that looks good, Mary Private, mary@gmail.com.
Excellent, whoa.
Man, this is awesome.
Now, I'm happy, excited
but I'm thinking well, we should really check this
in the database.
We need to make sure this stuff is really out there
and there's no smoke and mirrors,
so let's go ahead and log into our database.
Let's go to our web_student_tracker
and our Tables, go to student,
select and there we go.
So, this looks good,
so there's Mary Private, mary@gmail.com,
so that's great and then the other person
we played around with was Maxwell, yeah, Maxwell Apples,
so this is great.
So, sigh of relief.
This works out just fine.
We're updating students in the database
and we kind of went through all
of the coding process for that.
That included pre-populating the form,
reading the input
and then saving it and updating it in the database,
so I'm excited now.
So, I would say good job for you,
give yourself a pat on the back
and we are making excellent progress here.
I'm excited, whoa.