In this video, I'm gonna show you how
to make use of HTML forms with JSP.
We'll actually cover the following topics.
I'll first start off with a review of HTML forms,
then I'll show you how to build an HTML form.
Next, we'll learn how to read the form data with JSP.
All right, a lot of good stuff.
We've all used HTML forms before,
if you've gone to any website where you have to login
with user ID and password.
That information was entered via an HTML form.
Also, if you've gone on any travel site
and booked an airline trip or hotel reservation,
again, all of that data was entered through an HTML form.
What we're going to do here is we're gonna learn how
to build an HTML form to read student information.
We're gonna prompt the student
for their first name and last name.
They'll enter it into a text field,
and then once they enter that data,
they'll hit the submit button.
Once they hit submit, that data will be sent over
to a JSP page for processing.
We'll have a JSP page or read the form data
for the first name and the last name,
and we'll send back the confirmation page to the browser.
I'll show you how to put all of this together.
We'll start with the form first,
and then we'll move into the actual JSP development.
All right, let's get started.
Here's the coding here for the HTML form.
Again, we want to have an HTML form
for the first name and last name,
along with the submit button.
When you build an HTML form, you start off with the form tag
and then you specify the action.
You're basically telling the system where
to send the form data.
We're telling the system here, "Send the form data
to student-response.jsp."
Next, we set up our text fields
for first name and last name.
So, for text field, we have input type="text",
we give name="firstName".
And that name's very important.
We'll need that name on the server side.
We do a similar thing here for last name.
input type="text", name="LastName".
Finally, for our submit button, we set up an input type.
We say, "input type="submit",
and then we give the value of "Submit",
so the value portion here is really just the label
that you'll see on the submit button.
Once they hit the submit button,
then that data will actually be sent over
to the appropriate JSP page for processing.
Here's the coding here for reading the form data.
Whenever we read the form data with the JSP,
it's very important that we need to know the names
of those HTML form fields.
I have these HTML form fields here on this slide
just for reference.
At the bottom, in the JSP file,
we simply want to say, "The student is confirmed",
and then we want to display the student's first name
and last name.
So we read the form data by saying "request.getParameter
and we give that form field name, ("firstName").
And then to read the last name, we do a similar thing.
request.getParameter("lastName").
We place all that inside of a JSP expression
with the angle bracket, percent, with the equal symbol.
That will allow us to read the form data in JSP.
Next, here's an alternate syntax for reading the form data.
You can make use of this dollar sign, curly brace,
and then you can say param.formFieldName.
So, a simpler way of writing this page is
The student is confirmed, and then we simply say
$, and a similar thing here,
$
This is really just a shortcut method.
It's only used for displaying form data,
so it's really just a shorthand,
simpler way of writing the code.
If you needed to read the form data
in maybe a scriplet or something,
you'd have to resort back to using the request.getParameter.
But as much as possible, I'll try
and make use of this shortcut method
in our confirmation pages.
This wraps up this portion of the video.
In the following video, I'll actually do a code demo,
and I'll take you to Eclipse, and we'll actually write
the code in Eclipse.
I'll see you in the next video.