Alright so let's go ahead
and move into Eclipse.
What I'd like to do is to continue
to use the same project as before, jspdemo.
And what I wanna do is move down to the
WebContent directory and create a new file.
So we're actually gonna create a new file
for the html form.
So I'll just do a right click,
I'll say new, file.
The name of this file, I'll call it student-form.html.
And once we're happy with the name we can
go ahead and click the Finish button.
Alright, so let's go ahead and expand the window here.
Now I'll set up my basic html tags.
And then I'll set up a header for the title of this form.
And then we'll just go in and set up
some body tags here real quick.
And then we can start building our form.
So here I'll say form action equals
student-response.jsp
so that's the jsp file we're gonna send the data to.
We haven't created the file yet, we'll create it next.
But that's the actual file that we'll send the data to.
Now I need to simply go through
and create some form fields.
So I'll set up the form field for first name.
So the input type is text
and the name is equal to first name.
And again that's the exact same name
we're gonna use on the server side in our jsp
when we read the form data.
Just set up some line breaks here.
And now I'll do a similar thing here for last name.
So input type equals text.
Name equals last name.
I'll just do a quick copy paste here on the line breaks.
And then finally to wrap it all up
I'll set up my submit button.
So I'll say input type equals submit
and then value equals submit.
So the value of submit, that's the actual
label that you'll see on the submit button.
Now I notice I have a typo on line 17.
I spelled the input type submt, I misspelled that one.
So let me fix that with an i.
Okay, good.
Now we're good to go.
Okay so this is the html form.
First name, last name, and the submit button.
Okay so now lets go ahead and create the jsp page
that'll process this.
So our student response jsp.
So new file
and I'll call it student-response.jsp.
That's the same name that I refer to in the html form.
The student-response.jsp.
And once you're happy with this name
you can go and click the Finish button.
Okay, great.
So let's go ahead and set up our basic tags again.
And set up our student confirmation.
And then take care of the body.
Alright so now this is where we need
to start reading some of the form data.
So first off I'll say "The student is confirmed"
and then I wanna display their
first name an their last name.
So I'll make use of that shortcut notation.
The dollar sign curly brace param.firstName
so its the same name from the html form
and then param.lastName.
So basically here we'll have first name,
space, last name for that student once they're registered.
Alright so let's go ahead and run the program.
So I'll move over to student-form.html.
I'll do a right click and I'll say Run As
and I'll choose Run on Server.
Okay great, so here's our form.
We can go ahead and enter some information here.
So for the first name I'll say John,
last name of Doe.
And once I'm happy with that I'll hit the Submit button.
Okay great, so here is our confirmation page.
The student is confirmed, John Doe.
So that's the result of us reading the form data
that the user entered on their html form.
So this all looks really good.
So good job.
So we were successful in reading html
form data with the jsp page.