Hello, in this video I'm gonna show you
how to build dropdown lists with HTML forms.
So, we'll cover the following topics.
First off we'll see dropdown lists in action
and then I'll show you the HTML code
to build a dropdown list
and finally, we'll pull it altogether
with a full JSP page example.
All right, so let's go ahead and get started.
So, first off, here's a dropdown list in action.
We have a student and they can select their country
and so, we can give them all the different options
of the countries here
and so, this is an example of a dropdown list
and I'll show you the HTML code
on how to build this type of dropdown list.
Okay, so let's look at the HTML code
for building a dropdown list.
So, basically you make use of a select tag,
so here we have select
and we say name equals country
and then you drop in all the different options
that you'll have here for the dropdown list,
so here we have option&gt;Brazil,
France, Germany, India and so on
and this will actually help us build the dropdown list
for our application.
And note here where we have the select name equals country,
country, that's the name of the form filler
you use in your JSP page to read the form data
and I'll show you that later in the demo.
All right, so let's pull it altogether.
So, we're going to have an HTML form
that's gonna request a student's name,
first, last and also their country.
They're gonna submit their form data
and then we're gonna have a JSP page
that'll actually process this
and we'll display the student's name
and also display the user's selected country.
So, I always like to have a to-do list,
so the first thing we're gonna do
is we're gonna create an HTML form
and then the second thing we'll do is build
the JSP confirmation page.
All right, let's move into Eclipse and try this out.
All right, so we're in Eclipse.
What I'd like to do is to continue to use
the existing project jspdemo
and what we're gonna do
is we're gonna actually gonna have a form.
So, the from is going to be very similar to the previous one
so I simply want to copy our previous form
and use that as a starting point.
So, select student-from.html,
just do a right click and choose Copy
and then right click and choose paste.
We simply want to paste a copy of this,
so I'll just do a paste.
And at this point
Eclipse will prompt you for a new name for the form,
so the name we're gonna use here
is student-dropdown-form.html,
so student-dropdown-form.html,
that's the new name of our form.
And once you're happy with the name,
go ahead and click OK.
Okay, great, so now we should have this new form here,
student-dropdown-form.html.
Let's go ahead and open this form up
and take a look at it.
And I'll expand the window here for a second.
Okay, great, so the first thing we wanna do
is one line seven we wanna change the actual JSP page
it's gonna point to.
So, we want it to point to student-dropdown-response.jsp.
Again, student-dropdown-response.jsp.
That's the new page that we're gonna create in this video
for actually processing the form data
from the dropdown list.
Now everything else here is the same.
Let's move down to line 16
and first off, let's just do some white space here
and let's add in the actual tag for that dropdown list
using the select tag,
so I'll say select names equals country
and now here I'll go through and I'll add
the different options for the countries.
So, start off with the first country here Brazil,
France,
Germany and just more of the same.
I'll just repeat this for all the other countries here,
I'll speed the video up just to list out
all the other countries here.
Okay, great, so these are all the countries
and this is our dropdown list.
So, this is great, this kind of what we wanted
to do for building the HTML dropdown list.
Good job so far.
All right, so now let's go ahead
and work on our JSP page.
Again, our JSP page is gonna be very similar
to our previous page we created,
so we're simply going to copy it,
so choose student-response.jsp,
right click and choose Copy
and then do another right click and choose Paste.
And we'll give a new name for it here,
so we'll call it student-dropdown-response.jsp,
student-dropdown-response.jsp.
We'll hit OK and now we have this new page
that was just created, student-dropdown-response.jsp.
Let's go ahead and double click this file and open it.
All right, so this had the very basic page confirmation
from the previous video
and now what we're gonna do
is just add information about reading
from that dropdown list,
that dropdown list with the name of country.
So, here I'll say the student's country
and I'll use that dollar sign, curly brace param.country
and that will read the information from that dropdown list,
so good job.
All right, so let's go ahead and try this out,
so to test it we'll select our form,
student-dropdown-form.html,
we'll do a right click
and we'll choose Run As, Run on Server.
And this will bring up the form
and we can enter the user's first name and last name,
Ajay, Rao and we'll choose his country of India
and once we're happy with everything,
we'll hit the Submit button.
Okay, great, so we have the student's name
and also note here the student's country
and that's all based on us reading that dropdown list
from the JSP page, so good job,
we were successful with that.
All right, well, this wraps up the video.
In this video I showed you how to build a dropdown list
with HTMl forms
and also how to read that form data with JSP.
Great job.