Hello.
In this video, I'm going to show you how
to to build HTML forms with radio buttons.
So we'll cover the following topics.
First off, I'll start off with a radio button demo.
Then we'll look at the actual HTML code
for building radio buttons
and finally we'll pull it all together
with a full JSP page example.
So a lot of good things here.
Let's go ahead and get started.
All right, so here's the radio button demo.
So we'll have the student's first name and last name
but now we wanna have the student
choose their favorite programming language.
So here we'll give the first name and last name.
And then they can go through and select their language.
Java, PHP, C#, or Ruby.
Once they have their favorite language selected,
then they can go ahead and hit submit
and what we'll do is we'll actually generate
a confirmation page with the language that they selected.
So here I give the student's favorite programming language
in this example, the user chose PHP.
So let's go ahead and look at the HTML here
for radio buttons.
You'll set up your input type of radio,
and then you give the name,
favorite language, and then the value "Java".
And then an actual label for the user to see.
And you repeat this for each one of the languages here
for C#, PHP, and Ruby.
So the key here is that the input type="radio".
And that will give you a radio button.
All right, so let's go ahead and pull it together
with an example.
So we'll have a student radio form where our user
will enter their information and they can choose
their favorite programming language,
they'll hit submit,
and it will go across to a JSP page
that will actually process it
and display the student's favorite programming language.
Okay, and as you know, I love to-do lists here.
So the first thing we have to do is create our HTML form
and then the second thing is create
the JSP confirmation page.
All right, so a lot of good things here.
Let's go ahead and start coding.
Okay, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
Just like all the previous videos,
we'll continue to use the same project, JSP demo.
And also like the previous video,
we're gonna make use of the student form
as our starting point.
And we're gonna simply copy and rename it.
So I'll just right click on student-form.html
I'll select copy,
and then I'll right click on it and select paste.
And when I paste it I'm gonna give it a new name.
So the new name I'll call it a student-radio-form.html
and once I'm happy with that,
I'll go ahead and click the okay button.
All right, so here's our form.
Student-radio-form.html
lets go ahead and double click this
lets expand the window here for a second
and the first thing that we need to do on line 7
is just update the response page
so the response is gonna be student-radio-response.jsp
all right, we haven't created that page yet,
that's where we'll actually send the data
when we submit the form.
All right, so a lot of this stuff is frpm before.
What I'd like to do is go ahead and enter the HTML here
for the radio buttons.
So I'll start off here with
the favorite programming language
and then I'll set up the input type
so the input type="radio"
and the name="favoriteLanguage"
so that's the actual form fill name
and then the value="Java"
so this is for this given radio button.
And I also just put the label out there to the right.
And now what I can do is just copy this
x number of times for all of the other programming languages
so I'll just kind of speed the video up here real quick
and just update it for C#, PHP, and Ruby.
But now here's the end result.
So basically I have four radio buttons here
and they're for each one of
the different programming languages.
Now the key here again is the input type="radio".
Okay so this looks good so far.
So now let's go ahead and work on our JSP page.
So again, we're simply gonna copy our student-response.jsp
from the previous video,
and we'll simply rename it.
So I just right-click,
I'll choose copy,
and then I'll do a right click,
and I'll choose paste.
And for the new name I'll call it
student-radio-response.jsp.
And then I'll select okay.
Nice. So now we should have a new page here,
student-radio-response.jsp.
Let's go ahead and double click it and open it up.
I'll expand the window here for a second.
And let's go ahead and enter just
a little line break here for it.
And then I'll simply say
The student's favorite programming language is x.
And that will be whatever the form data was supplied
so here I'll use the $
and that's it.
So that looks pretty good right now.
So this will basically read the form fill
for param.favoriteLanguage.
All right, so this look pretty good.
So let's go ahead and run this application.
So, I'll move over to our form,
student-radio-form.html
I simply do a right click
I choose run as
and I choose run on server.
Okay, great. So here's our form.
We can enter the student's first name and last name.
And then our new piece here is
the actual radio buttons here.
So they choose either one of the programming languages
and then we could actually hit submit.
Okay, great. So here's our confirmation page.
So here's the student's favorite programming language.
And in this scenario,
they chose PHP.
But basically that's the result
of that form fill param.favoriteLanguage.
So we're successful here in writing a jsp
for reading that form fill data.
Okay, great, so let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
In this video I showed you how to build HTML forms
with radio buttons
and then also how to write jsp to read that form data.
Good job.