Hey, in this video,
I'm going to show you how to use HTML forms and check boxes.
So, we'll cover the following topics.
We'll first start off with a check box demo.
And then I'll show you the actual HTML code
for creating check boxes.
And then we'll pull it all together
with a full JSP page example.
Alright, so a lot of good things in store here,
lets go ahead and get started.
Alright, so lets start off with the check box demo here.
The user can enter their first name and last name.
And now the new thing that's here,
is that they can actually choose
multiple programming languages.
So that's thanks to check boxes.
Previously they could only use radio buttons
and choose only one language,
but now they can choose multiple languages.
Which is good, gives them more flexibility.
Because we may personally like more than one language.
And once you're happy with that,
you can go ahead and hit submit.
And now, our confirmation page is a little bit different.
So now since they can choose multiple languages,
then we'll simply display a list of all of the languages
that they actually selected.
So we'll do some slightly different coding here
on our confirmation pages.
But that's the big picture anyway.
Alright, so lets go ahead and look at the code here
for HTML check boxes.
So, its very similar to radio buttons.
The only difference is the actual input type.
So instead of type radio,
we say type equals checkbox.
And other than that, everything else stays the same.
So, input type of checkbox,
name favorite language,
value of Java,
with a label off to the far right.
And you can just repeat that process
for each one of the languages, C-sharp, PHP, and Ruby.
So again, very similar.
The only thing new is the type equals checkbox.
Alright, so now that the user can check multiple boxes.
We need to change our coding up a little bit
in our JSP page.
So now on our JSP,
we won't be able to use the little shortcut syntax
of the dollar sign, curly brace, param,
because now were going to get
a lot of different values back.
So what we can do instead
is make use of the request objects.
I'll say, request dot get parameter values
and then I'll give the parameter name, favorite language.
So this get parameter values will actually return
an array of strings.
Right? That makes sense right?
Because they can choose multiple programing languages now,
so it's going to return an array of strings.
And then it will write some JSP scriptlet code,
and we'll actually loop through that array and,
you know, print out an HTML list of the data.
But anyway, things will be a little different
when we get into the coding there of the JSP,
and we'll make use of this technique for that.
Alright, so lets kind of pull it all together.
So, for this demo, our project actually,
we're going to have a student checkbox form.
They can enter their information,
choose multiple programming languages,
hit submit.
Then that will go over to a JSP.
We'll give them their confirmation information,
and then we'll loop through all languages selected,
and then display them as an HTML list.
Alright, so you know how I love to-do lists.
So, the first thing we have to do is,
create the HTML form.
And then the second thing we'll do is,
create the JSP confirmation page.
And what I'll do, I'll actually break this up
and show it in a separate video.
As far as all the Eclipse coding.
So, I'll see you in the next video.