Alright, so let's go ahead
and move into Eclipse.
And what we're gonna do, is this project
will work similar to the previous one.
We're actually gonna start with our student-form.html.
We use that as a starting point, and then
we just add new features in here for the checkbox.
So the first thing I'm gonna do with student-form.html
is I'll do a right click, and I'll choose Copy.
And then I'll, again, I'll do a right click
and I'll choose Paste.
And now, the new name here, we'll call this
student-checkbox-form.html.
So that's the new name for it.
And then once you're happy with the name, you can click OK.
Now let's go ahead and open up
this student-checkbox-form.html.
So the first thing we need to do here on line seven,
we need to change the JSP that we're gonna send the data to.
So here I call it student-checkbox-response-jsp.
That's the new JSP that we're gonna create
a little later in this video.
Now let me expand my window here.
And also let me just get some extra white space down here,
so I can have some room to play.
Add another line break.
And now I'll go through and start entering
the information for my checkbox.
So here I'll say input type="checkbox",
name="favoriteLanguage",
value="Java".
And then we put our label out to the side Java.
So again, very similar to radio buttons.
The only thing that's different here
is the input type="checkbox".
And now what I can do, is I can simply repeat this process
for all the other languages.
So I'm just gonna speed up the video here for a bit,
while I just do a copy paste, and do a quick update
for those other languages.
Alright, I'll just save my file.
So okay, this looks really good right now.
So basically, I have the four languages here,
input type of checkbox, and that works out really well.
So our html form for the checkboxes,
is pretty much taken care of for right now.
Good job.
Alright, so let's do a similar thing here
for our response page.
So again, we're gonna use that student-response.jsp
as a starting point, and then we're gonna customize it.
So I'll simply copy this file.
And then I'll right-click and I'll do a paste for it.
And the new name that we'll give here, of course,
is student-checkbox-response.jsp.
And once you're happy with that name, go ahead and click OK.
So now we have this new file here,
student-checkbox-response.jsp.
Now let's go ahead and double-click this file
and open it up.
This is the original confirmation page from before.
I'm just gonna add some line breaks here.
And I just expand the window,
so I can have more room to work with.
And so, what I need to do here,
is I need to display the list
of favorite programming languages that the user selected.
So it's gonna be an html list of data.
And I just want to get some more white space
here at the bottom.
Give me one second.
Alright, so I'll make use of an html tag &lt;ul&gt;,
for unordered list.
And I'll put in multiple list items here.
But I'll actually generate these on the fly,
using a JSP Scriptlet.
So notice the angle bracket percent,
and now I can write real Java code.
So here, what I want to do is use that request.getParameter.
And I want to getParameter, actually getParameterValues,
because it's gonna be multiple items
that are gonna be returned.
And then I'll say favoriteLanguage.
Okay, good.
Now I actually have a syntax error here,
because this method request.getParameterValues,
it returns an array, so I need to add
the square brackets here for an array, on line 14.
That took care of that error.
So now I simply need to just do a for loop
through that array and, you know, display list items here.
So I'll setup this for loop.
String tempLang, that's my temporary variable,
:langs is the actual array itself.
And then I simply do an out.println.
I just do li for list item.
And then I just append the tempLang.
And then I just close off the /li.
So this is, basically, we're generating html on the fly
with our JSP.
Which is a good little example here
of using JSP Scriptlets.
Alright, so to recap here.
We read in all the parameter values,
and then we do the for loop,
and we print out all the list items.
Alright, so this looks really good so far.
Alright, so I'll save my file.
And now let's go ahead and run it,
so let's run the form.
So, our student-checkbox-form.html.
Just do a right-click, Run As, Run on Server.
Okay, great, so here's our form.
We can enter our first name and last name.
And then we can go through and choose the languages.
So now we can choose multiple languages here.
So I'll choose Java and C# just to start.
I'll hit submit.
And here it says student is confirmed,
and hey, there's our list, Java, C#.
Which looks okay, but I noticed I didn't put my little
description at the beginning of the favorite languages.
So let me just do that really quick.
So I'm back in my JSP right now.
And I'll just say favorite programming languages.
Just text so you can see it on the actual html page.
Do my little br break there.
And save that.
Now when I go back to my forms,
click on back in the browser.
Then I can just choose
maybe a different language here, Ruby.
And hit submit.
So now we have our little header,
our little description there,
along with whatever language they selected.
And also, I can just play around with it.
I can add multiple languages here,
like maybe this PHP and Ruby.
Hit submit.
And we see those displayed here in the browser.
And then I can maybe just choose all of them,
and see if this works.
And it does, right?
So it's simply reading those values,
and doing a for loop, and walking through
all of those items.
So this is really good.
So we're, I'd say we're successful.
So we had a html form with checkboxes.
And we read the data with JSP.
Very good, good job.