Welcome back.
In this video, I'm gonna give you an overview
of JSP and Servlets.
We'll cover the following topics.
We'll first find out what is a Web Application.
Then we'll learn about JSP and Servlets
and finally, I'll show you different types of apps
you can create with JSP and Servlets.
So what we're gonna do in this course
is we're gonna build web applications.
So you may wonder, oh, what is a web application?
We'll you've used this before.
If you have gone to any e-commerce site
like Amazon or any travel site,
you've used a web app and it's basically a site
that builds HTML pages on the fly
based on your user actions.
So I'd like to show you and example of this
using one of the travel sites.
So here's expedia.com, I use this site a lot for travel.
I travel a lot from Philadelphia to India.
So, here I'll enter my, where I'm flying from,
where I'm flying to.
I'll enter some dates here for my travel,
and then the key here is that once I hit Search,
it's actually gonna generate HTML pages
for me based on my request.
All right, so these pages that you see here,
it's not a hard-coded page.
It's actually generated on the fly based on my input,
Philadelphia going to Bangalore.
All right, so you may wonder what happens behind the scenes.
Well, behind the scenes in the web browser,
you select search flights, then it goes to the web server.
What the web server would do is it'll actually
submit a request to the Database using SQL.
And then once it has results, then it'll take
that information and then send back an HTML page on the fly.
And that's the idea of a web application.
And this is actually very generic.
You can build web apps using any type of technology,
such as JSP or Servlets or dotnet technologies
or PHP technologies and so on.
But that's the basic idea.
And what I'll do in this course
is I'll show you a very high level
on how to get started with JSP for building pages.
So that's the next question here,
what are JSPs and Servlets?
We'll, a JSP and Servlet, they're basically Java code
that runs on the web server.
So, they can read user input, normally from an HTML Form.
And then they can perform the work,
maybe talking to a Database,
talking to a web service or whatever.
And finally, it'll return an HTML page
that is generated dynamically on the fly.
So, kinda pulling it together with this big picture,
our Servelts and JSPs could actually run on the web server.
So they could read information for flight information,
send information or so with the Database,
get the results and then send back an HTML page.
So, that's kinda the area of where Servlets and JSPs
can fit in your web application architecture.
All right, so here's another frequently asked question.
Well, what types of apps can we create?
Well, I always like to say that you
can create apps for any industry.
So, you can build e-commerce apps, you could build maybe
a student or employee tracking application.
If you're building like a hotel or restaurant
reservation app or a social media app,
like Twitter or Facebook.
Really, any type of app.
There's really no limit on the apps that you can create.
JSP and Servlets are the key components
of the Java Enterprise Edition.
They're the most popular pieces of technology
and I always like to say they're the bread and butter
because a lot of popular MVC frameworks
actually use JSP and Servlets.
So, for example, Spring, JSF and Struts.
They all use JSP and Servlets at the low level.
Now, when you're using these technologies,
you may not see it directly at the high level
but behind the scenes, Spring, JSF and Struts,
they all make use of JSP and Servlets.
So, they're the key components
of the Java Enterprise Edition.
So, by you understanding JSP,
this'll help you when you move forward,
if you use some of those frameworks later on in your career.
All right, so let's go ahead and wrap up this video.
So we defined what are web applications,
we saw a demo of a web app,
we also discussed JSP and Servlets,
and then finally, we discussed the various types of apps
you can create with this technology.