Hey, in this video,
I'm gonna give you an overview
of setting up your development environment.
We'll cover the following topics.
I'll discuss the required software
and we'll also go through the high-level steps.
One prerequisite is that you must have
the Java Development Kit installed.
That's the JDK, not the JRE, but the JDK.
In regards to the required software,
to build these web applications,
you need to have the following.
You need to have a Java Application Server,
and an IDE.
Regarding the Java App Server,
there's a lot of different options
like GlassFish, JBoss, WebLogic, and so on,
but we're gonna keep it simple
and make use of the Tomcat Server.
Next, for the IDE, again, a lot of different options.
We'll simply focus on using the Eclipse IDE.
What I'll do is I'll actually break these videos up.
I'll have a separate video installing
the Tomcat Java App Server, and then I'll have
a separate video on installing the Eclipse IDE.
This wraps up the video.
We covered the required software.
We also discussed the high-level steps.
Let's go ahead in the following videos.
We'll actually go through and install our Java App Server,
and we'll install the Eclipse IDE.
All right, I'll see you in the next video.