Hey, welcome back!
So let's go ahead and get our hands dirty.
So in this video, I'm gonna show you
how to install Tomcat on Microsoft Windows.
Alright, so the first thing we need to do
is we need to download Tomcat.
So in my browser, I'm gonna visit
tomcat.apache.org.
And so this'll take me to the Tomcat website.
Over on the left-hand side is a downloads section,
where we can actually download some of the software.
I'll move down to the section
for binary distributions, and I'll choose this
32-bit/64-bit Windows Service Installer.
So this is the normal MSI file.
It'll install Tomcat as a Windows service.
So I'll go ahead and select this link,
and right now my browser will start
downloading it to my file system.
Alright, great. So now we have it downloaded.
Let's go ahead and open up a Windows Explorer,
and I'll move into this "Downloads" folder,
and there's the file that was just downloaded:
Apache Tomcat. So that's the actual installer.
So let's go ahead and run this installer
just by double-clicking it.
So this'll start up the installer. I'll hit "Yes."
And here I'm at the first step of the Wizard.
I'll go ahead and click "Next." I'll agree.
And then, here we choose our components.
For the components I like to choose "Full,"
just so I can get all the examples in the host manager.
Again, a nice thing about this Tomcat installer
is that it installs it as a service,
so I'll make sure that the service thing
is enabled or checked there.
I'll go ahead and hit "Next."
By default, Tomcat listens on port 8080.
Feel free to change that, but I like to keep the defaults.
And then you can set up a administrator login.
So for now, I'll just say "admin" "admin."
Again, you can give any username and password that you want.
And then I'll hit "Next."
I'll accept the default installation here for my JRE.
I'll hit "Next."
And I'll also accept the default installation directory.
You can feel free to change this, but I'll go ahead
and keep the default installation directory for Tomcat.
And then I'll hit "Install."
And so, at this point, it'll go through
the process of installing the software.
And now it says, "Hey, the software's installed."
I'll turn off the option to show the readme.
I'll hit "Finish."
And now it'll actually start Tomcat
as a Windows service.
Alright, great. So Tomcat is started.
Let's go ahead and verify our installation.
And we can verify it by viewing a website, localhost:8080.
That's where our local Tomcat server's running right now.
So if everything works out right,
it should bring up this page that you see here.
So it'll say "Apache Tomcat."
And then, also, they even give you a message,
"If you're seeing this, you've successfully
"installed Tomcat. Congratulations!"
So we know that we're okay.
So Tomcat was installed successfully,
and Tomcat is up and running. So good job so far.
Now I'm going to show you one other thing can do
is you can actually configure Tomcat.
So you can just right-click on
the little Tomcat icon in the bottom-right.
And say right-click and hit "Configure."
And this'll bring up the configuration window for Tomcat.
So you can change, like, the display name
for the service, you can change the actual description.
At the bottom it shows you if the status,
if it's running or stopped.
You can play around with some logging stuff.
A lot of other things you can play around with.
But for right now I'll just go ahead
and keep everything as the defaults,
and I'll just hit "Cancel" right now.
Another nice thing's that you can actually
administer Tomcat via the Services control panel.
So I'll go ahead and click on "Services" here,
it'll bring it up, and we'll see in the list
we have Apache Tomcat that's listed as a service
and it's currently running.
So, just like any standard service,
you can just right-click, you can stop it,
pause it, resume it, restart it;
you can do all the normal things you can do with a service.
What I'd like to do now is actually stop Tomcat,
because we're gonna run it later via Eclipse.
So I'll go ahead and stop this service.
I'll just do a right-click, I'll hit "Stop,"
and it'll go through the process
of stopping the Tomcat server.
So right now it's not running. But don't worry.
Later on we'll actually hook up Tomcat
and Eclipse to run together,
and we'll cover that in one of the following videos.
Now, we were successful, we were able to download Tomcat
and install it, and then, also go through the process
of verifying our installation.
And then finally, we went around
and took a look at some of the configs,
and also looked at the Services control panel.
So good job so far.