Hey, welcome back.
So, let's go ahead and get our hands dirty
with setting up our development environment.
In this video I'm gonna show you how to install Tomcat
on the Mac operating system.
All right, so what we need to do is to open up a web browser
and visit the Tomcat website,
so I need to go to tomcat.apache.org.
So, this will bring me to the main Apache Tomcat website.
This is where we can actually download the software,
so over on the left-hand side
there's a Download section
and it has the different versions of Tomcat
that we can download.
At the time of this video recording
the current version is Tomcat 8,
however, there may have a new version
and you can simply download the appropriate version,
so I'll go ahead and select Tomcat 8 for this video
and this will show me the Tomcat 8 downloads.
I'll just scroll down a bit
and I'll move down to the binary distributions,
that means this is the binary code or whatever.
Since I'm doing this for a Mac
I'll go ahead and choose tar.gz,
so it's simply a zip file
that preserves the file permissions
and I'll select the link here.
My browser's going to prompt me for the actual file
and I'll say save the file and I'll hit OK
and so, this will actually download the Tomcat file
to my local computer.
All right, great, so we've actually downloaded
the file to our file system,
so let me go over and open up my finder.
Let me move into the Downloads directory
and this is where I'll find the actual file
that was just downloaded,
so here apache-tomcat-8.
Now what I need to do is actually unzip the file,
so I can actually unzip it by double clicking it,
so I'll go ahead and do that now
and now I have this folder here
for apache-tomcat-8,
so this is the unzipped version of the file.
All right, so what I normally like to do
is actually move this into another directory
so I can make use of it,
so we'll actually make use of a directory
for this training class
and I'll call it jsf-for-beginners,
so let me go and open up a new window here.
I'll move down to the bottom
and I'll say New Folder
and I'll call it jsf-for-beginners,
so this is really just like
a little empty scratch temp folder
that we're gonna use for this training class.
I'll put all of our apps in here,
all of our servers and so forth,
so just one central location.
Jsf-for-beginners.
So, it's empty now, I'll just double click moving to it
and what I'd like to do is that folder
that I just expanded up top, tomcat-8,
I'll just grab it, drag and drop it into this new folder,
jsf-for-beginners, so all I do is just copy
that expanded directory
to this new folder jsf-for-beginners.
Okay, so this looks pretty good.
All right, so now that I have a file extracted,
I actually want to verify the Tomcat installation
by actually running the server,
so what I'll do is I'll open up a terminal window here
and what I'd like to do is actually move
into that Tomcat installation directory.
So, I'll just do a CD,
I'll move into that jsf-for-beginners
that we just created
and then the apache-tomcat directory
that we just copied over.
All right, great, so I'm in the directory,
now I'll just do an ls just to see the contents
of this directory
and we'll see that this directory
has a startup.sh, this is in the bin directory,
startup.sh, this is what I'll use
to actually start the Tomcat server,
so on my command line here
I'll type in bin/startup.sh
and this will actually start the Tomcat server for me,
so we can see some logs
and then we'll see in the bottom left
Tomcat started, so this is really good,
so our server's installed
and we also started the server,
so at this point Tomcat is up and running
and it's listening for a request.
All right, great, so now that our server's running,
we can actually access our server,
so in my browser I can simply type local host:8080
and this will connect to my Tomcat server.
By default Tomcat is listening on port 8080
and that's how we connect to it,
so here we make it to a page Tomcat
with the version number and then they'll even tell you hey,
if you're seeing this page,
you've successfully installed Tomcat,
so we're in really good shape here,
so we downloaded the server,
we installed it and we also started the server
and then we accessed it via our web browser,
so we know that things are looking really good for us,
so good job so far.
And one final thing we wanna do
is actually stop the server
or shut down the server
because later on we're gonna us it via Eclipse,
so in our bin directory we can say just bin/shutdown.sh
and that will actually stop the Tomcat server
but don't worry, once we install Eclipse,
then we'll actually Tomcat from the Eclipse server.
All right, so we did a lot of good things in this video.
So, I showed you how to install the Tomcat server
on a Mac operating system.
We went through the process to actually start the server
and also accessed the server
and then finally, how to stop the server,
so we're in good books now
that we have successfully installed Tomcat.