In this video,
I'm gonna show you how to install Eclipse on the Mac.
In particular, we're going to install
the Java EE version of Eclipse.
Okay, let's go ahead and get started.
Alright, so the first thing we need to do
is download Eclipse.
So in our browser, we'll just visit eclipse.org.
This'll bring us to the Eclipse website
and over on the far right is a Download button.
Let's go ahead and click on that button,
and this'll take us to the download page.
Alright, so now we're at the download page,
let's scroll down a bit
and we wanna make use of the Eclipse IDE
for Java EE Developers,
so it's really important, Java EE version.
So let's go ahead and click on the download link here,
I'm using a Mac right now so I'll download that version.
This'll take us to the download page,
I'll go ahead and click the option here
for the download mirror.
The browser will prompt me to download the file,
I'll go ahead and click Okay.
And then we'll start downloading it to our system.
Now this will take a while,
so what I'll do is I'll kind of step away
and I'll come back once the download is complete.
Alright, so we've downloaded the file.
Now what we need to do is unzip Eclipse.
So the first thing I'll do
is I'll move into the Downloads directory,
and there's the file that we just downloaded,
the Eclipse Jave EE,
and I'll go ahead and double click this file to unzip it.
Alright, so now what I'd like to do,
now that this file is unzipped,
what I'd like to do is move it
to my jsf-for-beginners folder
that I created in a previous video.
So let me go ahead and open up a new Finder window here,
just resize the windows give me one second.
So at the bottom I have my jsf-for-beginners,
that's the one we created in our previous Mac video,
I'll go ahead and double click in there
and that's where we installed our Tomcat
from the previous video.
I'll take this Eclipse folder that I just unzipped
and I'll move it down to that jsf-for-beginners folder.
Again, this jsf-for-beginners folder
is just a little scratch sample folder
that we're going to use for our jsf class,
just to keep everything in one location.
But good, we just simply moved that from Downloads
over to our jsf-for-beginners. Good job.
Alright, so now that we have the file
in our jsf-for-beginners directory,
let's go ahead and run Eclipse.
So I'll simply select the Eclipse icon
in this Eclipse folder,
and I'll just double-click it
and this will start up Eclipse for me.
So I'll go ahead and hit Open to start it to run.
And then they're gonna prompt me for a workspace.
So our workspace is simply a folder
where we put our sample code,
normally I would keep the defaults,
but in this example I'm going to change it.
So I'm gonna click on Browse,
and I'll move over to this jsf-for-beginners directory,
and then in the bottom left
I'm gonna click on a button there for a New Folder,
and for New Folder I'll just type in the name of workspace.
So I'll create a new workspace folder here
in jsf-for-beginners.
Hit Okay, and so this is what the layout
should look like once we have that set up.
So again, you can put your workspace anywhere you like,
but I'm just putting it here in this one directory
just so it keeps track of everything else
for this jsf-for-beginners class.
Alright, so once I'm happy with that I'll go ahead
and hit on Okay, and Eclipse will start running,
and then I'll make it to the Welcome screen.
I always like to verify
that I'm using the Java EE version of Eclipse,
because it has built-in support for jsf
and I'll go ahead and close this welcome.
Over on the left hand side I have my Project Explorer,
right now it's empty, nothing's there.
So that's it.
So at this point we have Eclipse installed
and we're able to run it and everything looks really good.
Good job so far.
Alright so this wraps up the video.
In this video I showed you how to install Eclipse
on the Mac, I also showed you how to download the file,
unzip it and then launch Eclipse.