Hey, welcome back.
In this video, I'm gonna show you
how to connect Eclipse and Tomcat.
Now, the main benefit is that
we can start Tomcat from Eclipse.
Also, it'll make it very easy for us to deploy
our web applications directly to Tomcat.
Alright, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse.
What I'd like to do is move down to the bottom section,
there's a tab called servers.
I'd like to click on that tab.
Now at this point, we don't have any servers
associated with our Eclipse environment at the time.
So what we need to do is click on this link,
and we're gonna add a new server.
And we're gonna add a new server that points
to our Tomcat that we installed previously.
Alright, so here's the define new server.
What I need to do is move up
to the Apache Tomcat folder, and expand it.
Now, what I'd like to do is go ahead and click
the next button here on the screen.
And then at this point, I need to browse
and tell Eclipse where Tomcat is installed.
Alright, so wherever you have Tomcat installed,
you need to point to that directory.
I'm gonna make use of the default directory
where Tomcat is installed.
It's under program files, Apache software, Tomcat 8.
So this is the actual default directory
where Tomcat was installed.
Alright great, so once I have that selected,
I'll click on okay.
And so it should give us the full path there
for the Tomcat installation directory.
So again, I'm just using the default.
Once I'm happy with this, I'll go ahead and click on next.
This screen here talks about some other apps,
don't worry about it, just go ahead and click on finish.
And this will associate Tomcat with the Eclipse environment,
so if everything is successful, down in the bottom center,
you should see a reference for Tomcat.
Now at this point, it's stopped, we haven't started it yet.
We'll actually start it in some of the following videos
when we start creating our web applications.
Okay, great, so if your Eclipse screen looks similar
to this, that means you're successful
in setting up Tomcat within Eclipse.
Good job.