Hey, in this video
we're gonna learn about servlets in Java.
So what exactly is a servlet?
Well a servlet is basically a Java class
that's processed on the server,
so this Java class can generate HTML
that's returned to the browser,
and you can use servlets to read HTML form data,
you can make use of cookies and sessions.
At a very high level,
servlets are similar in functionality to JSPs,
but I'll talk more about that later,
so just for now,
let's kind of focus on how to build a servlet,
and we'll look at some of the coding for it.
All right, so with servlets
you're gonna process something on the server,
so you have your browser, you have your servlet,
and what the browser's gonna do is
basically send a request over to the server,
so your Java servlet will execute,
and when that servlet is executing,
it can generate some HTML content,
and then that HTML content will actually be sent
back to the browser as a response.
So again, we have HTML content that's built on the fly
by our Java servlet,
and the Java servlet is actually a Java class
that runs when we make a call to it.
All right, so now you're probably wondering,
"Okay, show me the code,"
so we can go ahead and look at the code.
So here at the top, we start off with our servlet.
The first thing you have here is an @WebServlet.
This is a Java annotation,
and we basically give a path for the servlet,
so @WebServlet("/HelloWordServlet"),
that's the path for accessing the servlet.
Then we create our servlet,
and like I said earlier, a servlet is simply a Java class.
So we create public class HelloWorldServlet,
extends HttpServlet.
So whenever we write a servlet,
we can override either the doGet method
or the doPost method.
So for this hello world example,
we'll override the doGet method.
So the doGet method, it takes two parameters.
They pass in a request object and a response object.
So when we make use of our servlet code
inside of this doGet method, we have three main steps.
So the first step is setting the content type.
So here we basically tell the browser,
"Hey, I'm gonna send you back some data,
"and this is the type of data I'm sending back."
So in this example,
I'll say response.setContentType("text/html");
Then, the next step is getting the printwriter,
so this is a special object that we can get a handle on
to actually send data back to the browser.
So here I say PrintWriter out = response.getWriter();
Then, moving ahead to Step Three,
we basically just generate our HTML content,
and this is very similar to like what JSP is.
You simply use out.println,
and you just give your HTML content.
So here I say out.println, I give the &lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;,
then I say out.println("&lt;h2&gt;Hello World&lt;/h2&gt;"),
and then I do another println with &lt;hr&gt;,
and then finally here I say
out.println("Time on the server is: ",
and I can drop in new java.util.Date(),
and then I can do a &lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;.
So basically what this will do is,
on the fly, it's gonna generate an HTML page
very similar to the screenshot we have here,
and it'll give us the time on the server,
and that's the basic idea of a servlet.
So again, similar to JSPs
in that we generate HTML on the fly,
but a tad bit different
in that we actually create a Java class first,
and then we do an out.println on all of the HTML
that we're gonna send back to the browser.
All right, so this is a lot of good stuff,
the Hello World servlet in a nutshell.
In the next video, we're actually gonna try it out,
and move into Eclipse, and start working with it.
All right, so I'll see you then.