All right, let's go ahead an move into Eclipse,
and we're gonna get our hands dirty
by creating a Hello World servlet.
So the first think I wanna do is create a new project,
so I'll say File, New, and Dynamic Web Project.
And then, for the name of the project,
I'll actually call it servletdemo.
Then I'll keep all the other defaults here,
Apache Tomcat eight, version 3.1, everything else the same,
and I'll go ahead and click on Next.
Here we'll just go ahead and keep the defaults here
for the default output server,
I'll hit Next,
and then for the Context root and Content directory
I'll keep the defaults,
and also I'll check the box here for Generate web.xml.
So the context root's the actual name of our application
once we deploy it, servletdemo.
Then I'll go ahead and hit Finish.
So now we should have a new project
out here over to the left called servletdemo.
And we have a WebContent directory,
and it's empty right now.
All right, so the first thing I wanna do here
is create a new servlet,
so I just right-click on the project,
I say New, and I move down to Servlet.
And so for this servlet, I give a Java package name,
so I'll just call it com.luv2code.servletdemo,
and that's just the name of the package
for grouping these classes together,
and then the actual class name,
I'll call it HelloWorldServlet.
And then, once I'm happy with that,
I can go ahead and click on the Next button.
Here they just have the servlet name.
I'll keep it as is.
I'll accept all the other defaults,
and I move ahead and click Next.
Here, they can tell us which methods they want to stub out,
or create for us on the fly,
so right now we'll go ahead and accept the defaults.
They're gonna create a doGet and a doPost method.
We'll go ahead and keep all the defaults here,
and we'll just hit Finish.
Okay great, so this looks similar
to the code we had in the PowerPoint slides,
but Eclipse generated a lot of this for us.
So they created a new package,
and they also have the new servlet.java file,
so this is really good.
This is a good jumpstart for us,
for our servlet development.
All right, so let's go ahead a dig into this servlet,
and just kind of see how it works here.
So first, on line 14,
we simply have our Hello World servlet,
so public class HelloWorldServlet extends HttpServlet,
and we always have that declaration there.
And then, up on line 13, we have our @WebServlet.
So this is simply an annotation that gives the actual path,
or the URL for us to actually access this servlet.
All right, so let's go ahead and look at some of the code.
There's a lot of generated code.
What I wanna do here is take a look at the doGet method,
so this is the one method that we override,
where we're gonna actually provide our response.
So when the browser makes a call to our servlet,
then it'll actually access or call this doGet method.
So this doGet method has a request and a response.
The interior there, I'm gonna remove.
That was all the auto-generated code,
and I wanna actually give my own custom code here,
so let's go ahead and write some code.
So first off, I always like to put out the comments
as far as what I need to do here.
So for Step One, I need to actually set the content type.
Then, for Step Two,
I need to actually get a handle to a printwriter
that I'll use for sending back data.
And then Step Three
is actually generating the HTML code on the fly.
So those are the three main steps
as far as what we need to do inside of this doGet method.
So let me just get some more white space here
just so we can kind of have some room to work with.
So for setting the content type,
we have two parameters coming in.
We have the request object coming in,
and that has the form data coming in from the browser.
And then the response object,
that's our handle that goes back to the browser.
So what I wanna do here is use that response object,
and set the content type.
So I say response.setContentType,
and then I make use of the content type of text/html,
so I'm telling the browser,
"Hey, I'm gonna send back text data,
"and this data is formatted as html,"
so the browser knows how to handle it,
and the browser will render it accordingly as HTML data.
The next thing I need to do is get the PrintWriter,
so I say PrintWriter out = response.getWriter();
So remember,
that response object came in as a parameter up above,
and it has our handle to communicate back to the browser.
Now I need to fix something on line 34.
We just simply need to do an import,
and I simply need to do an import on this PrintWriter
from the java.io package,
so you go ahead and click that item there,
and Eclipse will handle the imports for you automatically.
All right, good,
so now we can start doing some real work here.
So now we can actually start generating our HTML content.
So first off, I'll just do some out.printlns,
and I'll just do some normal HTML housekeeping, right,
our &lt;html&gt; tag, &lt;body&gt;,
and then I'll do a similar thing here on ending those tags,
so I'll do a &lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;.
So that's all of the normal stuff we'd have to set up,
and now at this point, it's totally up to us.
We can just start generating HTML.
We can keep it as simple,
or we can make is as fancy as we'd like here.
So here, I'm gonna do an out.println, &lt;h2&gt;,
and I'll just say Hello World.
And then I'll do another out.println,
and I'll just do a println for an &lt;hr&gt;, for horizontal rule.
And next I'll say out.println, Time on the server is,
and then I simply create a new data object.
So I'll say new java.util.Date();
This'll do the concatenation.
It'll call the two string version on the date,
and that result will be included in this HTML page
that I'm generating on the fly,
that I'm gonna send back to the browser.
So those are the three major steps there:
setting the content type, getting the printwriter,
and generating the HTML content.
And again, remember, whenever we're building servlets,
there are some special methods here: doGet and doPost.
So here we're gonna override this doGet method
and provide our functionality,
so when they access this servlet from the browser,
it's gonna automatically call the doGet method,
and that's a special method that's part of the servlet API.
All right,
so this looks really good so far for our first servlet.
Let's go ahead and try it out.
So what I can do here is I can go to the servlet class file,
I can simply run it on the server, so I do a right-click,
I choose Run As, and then I choose Run on Server.
And they'll ask me which server to run it on,
I'll choose Tomcat 8 that's already installed,
I always use this server,
and then I'll hit the Finish button.
And all right, this looks really good.
So here's the output of our servlet.
So we have Hello World, time on the server is,
and then they just drop in that time.
So this is all generated on the fly by our servlet,
and we wrote all the code to make this happen.
So this is a really good example
of just getting started very quickly with servlets,
and writing a very basic Hello World servlet.
In some of the following videos,
we'll get into more advanced things like reading form data,
overriding other methods,
and also doing some comparisons with servlets and JSPs,
but this is a really good start for right now, so good job.