Hey, so in this video we're gonna
compare servlets and JSP.
Now we've seen how we can build
applications using JSP so far in the course.
So we built JSPs to read a request
and send back a response.
And also we've just learned about
how we can use servlets to read a request
and also send back a response.
So you may wonder, well, which one
should I use?
(laughs)
It looks like you can do the same thing
with servlets and JSPs and kinda
what's the best practice, what should I do?
So basically, just a quick recap here.
JSPs is really just an HTML file with a .jsp extension.
It has some static HTML and also some JSP
to generate HTML on the fly as needed.
And also JSP's as you know, has a collection
of built-in JSP objects that you can make use of directly.
Now when we look at servlets, it's really a Java class file
so it's a like a hello world servlet.java.
It's a class that extends, we write methods,
we have to write all of the code to generate the HTML.
And also, there's some additional steps to access some
of the web objects like,
response set content type, response getwriter,
and so on, and we have to do a lot of work ourself.
So, in general it's a little easier to write code
using JSP's, but there's still a purpose
for servlets in the architecture.
So kinda speaking on that purpose,
you may wonder, which one should I use?
Well, you can use either one for building Java
web apps, so you can actually build your entire
site only using servlets.
And I actually did this back in 1998,
cause servlets was the first Java server technology
that was out, and JSP's did not exist.
So I actually built an entire site using servlets
for a major client,
or you can build the entire site using JSP's.
But now that we have the technology and it's
matured a bit, you can actually
use them to gather, and that's a best practice.
So here, we can integrate them both together
where we have the servlet that'll do the business
logic and then the JSP page will handle the
presentation view.
And this is actually a very popular design
pattern called the Model-View-Controller Design Pattern,
or MVC.
This design pattern is used by a lot of the popular
Java frame works like, Spring MVC, JSF, Struts,
and so on.
They're all based on this idea of a Model-View-Controller
Design Pattern, and they make use of servlets and
JSP'a at the lower level.
So, what I'll do is I'll have another section of
videos coming up shortly where we'll actually
go through the Model-View-Controller Design Pattern
in detail, so I'll show you how to set the servlet up,
I'll show you how to have the servlet talk to the JSP,
and how the JSP will send data back.
So, we'll get into all the gory details on how to do
MVC from scratch with servlets in JSP's.
So anyway, I just wanted to kind of address that issue
cause I know a lot of folks always ask
the difference between servlets and JSP's and
I wanted to kind of just address that.
But what I wanna do now is just kind of,
move forward a bit and we'll focus on servlets
just by itself for the next couple of videos
and then we'll come back and we'll pull it all together
with servlets and JSP's together.
So, don't worry, a lot of good things here,
and a lot of good ground to cover.
I'll see you in the next video.