Hey, in this video we're gonna learn
how to read HTML form data with servlets.
So we'll start off with a student-form.html;
that's gonna be our HTML form.
We're gonna gather the students first name and last name.
They'll hit the submit button, the request will go across
to our servlet, StudentServlet.java,
our servlet will process the request,
and then send back a response.
So that's the basic idea here
of having a servlet read form data.
All right, so let's kind of walk through this step-by-step.
So the first step is building the HTML form,
and we've seen most of this before.
So we start off with our form, and now the action
equals the student servlet; so that's the name
of the servlet that we're calling, and then we set up
method equals get because we wanna make use
of a get request to that servlet.
Then, from there, we simply set up the HTML form fields.
So we set up first name field,
last name field, and also a submit button.
So, again, we've seen a lot of this stuff before,
just a basic form that we're setting up for our example.
Now the one thing that's different here or unique
that I wanna point out here is that since this form
is gonna send the data using method equals get,
this actually calls the do get method in your servlet.
All right, so method equals get
will call the do get method in your servlet.
So you have to make sure that you override the appropriate
handler method or make sure you override the do get method.
Now the next step here is reading the form data
in the servlet, so at at the top I showed you
the first name and last name; and then at the bottom,
this is the actual servlet code.
So, again, we override the appropriate method here,
do get, they pass in a request, the request object
has your form data, or it contains the form data.
So here I simply use an out.print line,
the student is confirmed;
and here I say request.getParameter.
That allows me to read form data.
So request.getParameter on first name
and then request.getParameter for last name.
So those parameter names map
to the actual HTML form field names.
And that's basically it here for our servlet example.
What we're gonna do in the next video is we're gonna move
into eclipse, we're gonna get some hands on practice,
and we'll actually build this example from scratch.
So I'll see you in the next video.