Okay, so let's go ahead an move into Eclipse.
And what I want to do is continue
to use that servlet demo project that we had
in the previous video.
And the first thing I need to do as far as my step one
is creating the html form.
So I move to this web content directory.
I'll do a right click.
I'll choose new and file.
So the actual file that I'm gonna create here
is called student-form.html.
And once you're happy with that name
you can go ahead and click on the finish button.
This will give us a very empty file here.
Or a blank file and we need to add some data here.
So I'll first start off with my normal html housekeeping.
So, html and then the body tags,
and that's the basic stuff there.
And now what I need to do is go ahead
and create my html form.
So with this form we're gonna have
action="StudentServlet",
so we're calling this studentservlet
and we're gonna us the method="GET",
that's the http method that's gonna map over to our
do get method in our servlet.
Alright, so now let's go ahead and set up
our html form fields.
I'll start off here with the first name,
input type="text",
name="firstName".
And then I'll do a similar thing here for last name.
I'll say input type="text",
name="LastName.
So again, remember, these form field names,
these are the actual names that you'll use
in the actual servlet code for reading that data.
So you have to make sure to use the same names
in the servlet code.
I'll just copy this line break,
put it down here,
then finally, I'll just wrap it up with a submit button.
Input type="submit", value="Submit".
And that's basically it for our html forms.
It's gonna send data over to the student servlet,
and gonna use the method of get.
Alright, this looks really good, good job so far.
I'll save this file.
Now the next thing we need to do is our step two,
is actually creating the servlet.
I'll move up to this java resources directory.
I'll move down to the package that I created
in the previous video, our servlet demo package.
I'll simply right click, I'll say new, servlet.
The name I'll use for the servlet is StudentServlet.
So we'll use the same name that we reference here
in the actual html form.
And once we're happy with this, we can go ahead
and click the finish button.
Over on our far left side here, we have this new
studentservlet.java that was created by Eclipse,
and it generated a lot of good code for us
that we can start with.
It helps jump start our development process.
Up top we have this @WebServlet annotation,
so it's /servlet.
That's basically the name that we'll use
for calling that servlet.
We have out servlet class, that extends HttpServlet.
We've seen all this stuff before.
Let me just clear out some white space here.
And this is our doget method.
This is the method that's called, when the actual
html form submits the data, because they're using
the method equals get.
Let me clear out that auto-generated code,
and let me write my own code.
And just like I did before, I always like to write
some comments, just to tell myself what I need to do.
The first step is I need to set the content type.
And then step two I need to actually get the print writer.
And then finally step three is where I do my real work.
This is where I generate the html content.
Alright, good, so this is my game plan as far as
what I need to do my work.
Alright, let's go ahead and dig in.
Let's start with step one.
Set the content type.
I used a response.setContentType, and I make use
of text slash/html.
So I'm telling my browser I'm gonna send
back text html data.
Then the next step is actually getting the writer.
Here I have printwriter, out = response.getwriter.
And then I simply just do an import here
for that package, java.io,
because that's where the print writer class is defined.
Now, again, step three is where I just do all my real work,
or funnel work here, so I'll clear out some space.
And now I need to simply just do out.println,
to set up my html housekeeping for our html body.
And I'll just copy this line, and I'll do a similar thing
here for the /body, /html.
Again, just very basic html housekeeping there.
And now what I want to do is simply send back a response.
So I want to say, hey, the student's confirmed,
and I want to display their first name and last name.
I'll just write this out here in the code.
Here I have, the student is confirmed,
and now I need to display the student's first name.
I can read that from the form data,
by saying request.getparameter("firstName").
And then I'll just add some white space there
just so we have some space between the first name
and last name.
And I do a similar thing here for last name,
request.getparameter("lastName").
And that's basically it.
So lines 41 through 43, that's kind of the real work
of this example, just sending back a response.
The student's confirmed, first name, last name.
And again, we make use of that request, getparameter
to read the form data.
Just kind of stepping back a bit, here's our method.
The main method here, doget.
That html form has a method equals get,
and it's gonna call my doget method in my servlet.
This all looks really good so far, good job.
Now let's go ahead and test this one out.
The test that I actually need to view my form,
it's on the web content directory, I moved
to the studentform.html.
And then I simply right click and I choose run as,
and then run on server.
Alright great, so here's my form.
Form fields for first name and last name.
I can go and fill that out with some information,
John Doe, and once I'm happy with this,
I can go ahead and click the submit button.
Alright, I hit the submit button,
this made a call to my servlet, and my servlet responded.
It said the student is confirmed, and it displayed
the student's first name and last name.
This looks really, really good.
I mean, this is exactly what we wanted to do,
with our servlet.
In this example, our servlet read form data,
and it generated an html response.
Good job with this example.