Hey, in this video,
we're gonna discuss the differences between GET and POST.
Well, so far we've learned how to read form data,
both with JSPs and Servlets,
and we sent data over using the GET method.
Now, you also may have noticed that there's a POST method,
and wondered how that works and
how's it different from the GET method,
so we'll cover all the gory details of it
here in this video.
So, just as a recap of what we've seen so far,
we've sent data over using the GET method,
so we have our form action, and we have method=GET.
So, that's the HTML form.
Then in our Java Servlet code,
we have to override the appropriate method,
so in this case we need to override the doGet method
because they're passing in a GET request.
So here in red, we have a request.getParameter.
That's for reading the form data.
And so, we've seen this before, just kinda recap.
Now let's move forward a bit and let's look at POST method.
So, to send data over using POST,
in our form we say form action,
and then we have method="POST."
So now, in our Servlet code,
we need to override the doPost method.
Now, this doPost method has the same parameters as doGet,
it has a request and a response.
So, for the doPost method,
you simply read the form data by saying
request.getParameters, so the exact same method call
to read form data using POST.
Now, when data's being sent using the GET method,
the form data is actually appended
to the end of a URL as name/value pairs.
So, here we'll have a URL with a question mark,
and then with our field1=value1,
and with an and symbol, field2=value2
with another and symbol, and so on.
And that's basically how form data is sent
using the GET method.
Now, sending form data using a POST method,
the form data is actually passed
in the body of the HTTP request message,
so the request message has a body section,
and the name/value pairs are included
inside of the body of the POST method,
so you won't see it in the browser's URL.
All right, so you see all this stuff and you're like,
okay, well, which one should I use?
So, a recap, the GET method here
is very good for debugging
because you can see the name/value pairs
right there in the URL.
You can also manually change them if you want.
You can also bookmark the URL,
and you can also email it.
With the GET method, there's a limitation on data length,
and it varies between browsers,
so you just need to be aware of that.
You're normally safe with about 1000 characters.
Now, with the POST method, you can't really
bookmark or email the URL,
because the URL doesn't contain the data.
Remember, the name/value pairs are sent
in the body of a request message.
But a really nice thing about the POST method
is that there's no limitation on data length,
so if you have a very large form
with a lot of fields,
you can send as much data as you want to.
Also, the POST method is very good
for sending binary data.
And you're probably wondering, well,
what type of binary data?
Well, if you do an email program,
and you do a form attachment,
you can attach a binary file to the form,
and then submit it.
So that's one use case there for the POST method.
So, my normal recommendation,
for non-sensitive data, you can use the GET method.
It's very good when you're first starting out
with your application for debugging and so on.
However, if you have some sensitive data,
then I'd recommend that you use POST data.
So, here sensitive means that
the POST method can encode some of it.
It doesn't do any real heavy encryption,
but it can kinda encode it,
so this is more security by obscurity.
But for full security, for full encryption,
you would implement a secure sockets layer.
But anyway, that's just a rule of thumb
between the two.
So, GET for very simple examples,
POST if you wanna encode some of your data.
So, this basically wraps up the video.
We discussed the GET method and the POST method.
Hopefully this clarifies it for you
as far as the differences between the two,
and how you can use them in your application.