Hi. In this video, we're gonna learn
how to use Servlet Configuration Parameters.
Now, when you're developing applications,
you never want to hard code special values
in your application.
It would be great if you could put that information
in a configuration file
to make your application more flexible.
So with servlets and JSPs,
your web app can actually make use of
configuration parameters as part of
the servlet's specification
they have a standard file where you can
place this information.
It's in the WEB-INF/web.xml file.
And again, it's a standard part of the servlet's
specification where you can set your data.
So here's an example of this file, web.xml.
Here, we have a section here for context params
and this is where you define your properties
or your parameters.
So you can specify a parameter name
and a parameter value
and it's totally up to you as far as the name
and values that you specify.
So in this example, I'm gonna set up
a max shopping cart size,
and I set the value to 99.
Then I'll have another parameter here called
the param name is project-team-name,
and I give the value of The Coding Gurus.
Again, I'm just making this up.
You can have as many parameters as you'd like.
There's no limit, and you can place all this information
in this web.xml file, which is really cool.
All right, so let's look at how to actually read
these configuration parameters.
So in this servlet's source code,
either a doGet or doPost method,
we can read this information.
So remember in the bottom right,
there's this web.xml file
that has all this configuration information as xml.
We can read this information in our servlet source code.
So the first thing we need to do
is we need to get the servlet context.
So here we say ServletContext = getServletContext.
The method getServletContext
is a method we inherit from the http server.
So that's a method that we inherit that we get for free.
So to give us a ServletContext object,
this ServletContext object is basically just a helper class
that allows us to do web-related stuff.
One of those features is that it allows us
to read information from that web.xml file.
So that web.xml file is actually an xml file.
However, this ServletContext will actually read that file,
parse it, and then have this information in memory
that we can make use of.
So I can read the parameter information
by saying context.getInitParameter
and I give the parameter name.
So here I'm gonna read parameter name
max-shopping-cart-size.
It'll return this value as a string.
I can do a similar thing here for project-team-name.
So I can say context.getInitParameter("project-team-name")
and it'll return the value.
All right, now two things here on this method.
First off is that the context.getInitParameter method,
it'll always return the data as a String.
So if you want to use it as a different data type
like an image or a Boolean,
you'd have to convert it yourself.
Also, this context.getInitParameter method,
if the parameter does not exist,
this method will simply return a value of null.
Okay, so no exceptions thrown in there
will simply return a null value.
So you'll have to do some additional checks on that
for that property value.
All right, but hey, so we've read
the property values here so we have max-cart,
we have team-name, then we can display this information
in our servlet, so here I say
out.println("Max cart: give the value
and then out.println("Team name:
and then give the actual team name.
And that's basically it so that's the java code
there for reading information from that configuration file.
Reading information from that web.xml file.
All right, so good job, so what we're gonna do
in the next video is we're gonna move and save clips,
we're gonna write some code from scratch,
and we're gonna see how we can read
configuration parameters for our application.
Okay, I'll see ya in the next video.