All right, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse
and what I wanna do is continue
to use that servletdemo project
that we've been working on so far.
And what we wanna do is define
some configuration parameters,
so that's kinda our first step.
So, in web content, web inf,
there's a file here called web.xml.
let's go ahead and double click this file
and open it up.
All right, so this is our standard web XML file,
our configuration file.
There's a lot of other information in here
regarding other web app details,
but what I'll do right now is I'll simply
focus on adding some context parameters here
or some config information to this file
so I can read the data.
So, the first thing I do is I start out with a context param
and then I need to add two sub elements,
I need to add a param name.
So, here I'll call it max shopping cart size.
And then I need to provide a param value.
So, for this example we'll say our
max shopping cart size is 99.
We could always change this at a later time,
that's the whole idea of a configuration param.
All right, so, that's a param that's set up right now.
let's go ahead and add one more parameter here.
So, I'll set up another context param
and I'll give it another name,
I'll say param name
and I'll call it project team name,
and again I'm totally making up these parameter names.
You can give whatever parameter name
that you'd like along with any value.
So, here I'll say param name
and I'll call ourselves the coding gurus
'cause we're awesome, yeah.
I'm havin' some fun here.
So, anyway, that's our second parameter
we've set up, project team name,
value of coding gurus.
So, this is great.
This is our web.xml file and we can read this information
using our servlet context.
All right, so we can go ahead and save this file
and now we'll need to write a servlet
that can actually read the information
from this configuration.
So, I'll move into my Java package directory
and I will create a new servlet.
So, I'll right click,
I'll say new, servlet.
So, for this servlet here,
I'll call it TestParamServlet
and I'll keep all the other defaults here
in this screen.
And once I'm happy with this name
I'll go ahead and click on finish.
So, again, Eclipse does all the work,
they generate a servlet for us,
they help us get started,
they set up the at web servlet annotation,
and they also set up our class that extends HTP servlet.
So, again, Eclipse is doin' a lot of good stuff
for us.
Woohoo.
And what I wanna do is clear out some space here,
I need to clear my desk so I can get down
and do some work here,
and I'm gonna focus on the do get method.
This is where I'm gonna read the information
from that configuration.
And I'll get rid of that auto-generated code
because I want to write my own code from scratch.
So, again, I always like to put comments her,
so step one is us setting the content type,
step two is getting the printwriter,
and now my step three is gonna be a little different here,
so, step three is where I'm actually gonna read
the param information.
So, I'm gonna read the configuration parameters.
And then finally, step four,
I'll do the standard thing
of generating HTML content on the fly.
So, that's the basic outline here for this do get method.
Getting the content type,
getting the printwriter,
reading config params,
and then generating HTML content.
So, step one, setting content type.
I simply use the response.setcontenttype
and I give text HTML.
And then again for my printwriter
I'll say PrintWriter out equals
response.getwriter.
And I go through that standard process
of fixing the imports here,
so the import on printwriter
that's in the java.io package.
Now, step three,
this is kinda like my new part for this video,
so I'm gonna read those cont configuration parameters.
Remember, I need to make use of that servlet context,
so here I'll say servletContext
equals get servletcontext.
And remember that method getservletcontext
is actually inherited form HTP servlet.
So, that base class that our servlet inherits from,
that's where we get that method.
And over on the left I'll fix the imports here
for this servlet context.
It's in the javax.servlet package
and now I have a handle to it,
so that's great.
So, now I can really do some stuff here.
Now I have this context object,
I can actually read some information
from that config file.
So, here for reading the max cart size
I say context get init parameter
and then I give max shopping cart size.
So, that's the param name that's
in that XML configuration file.
And then my configuration file
actually has a second parameter
and that's the actual project team name.
So, again I say context get init parameter,
and I give project team name,
again the actual name from the configuration file.
All right, and that's basically it for step three,
reading the config param,
so we get the context and then we use that context
get init parameter to read the params
for a max shopping cart size
and project team name.
So, this looks good so far.
And then step four is just more of a validation for ourself,
we're simply gonna just
generate some HTML content,
so I take care of my html housekeeping up front
with HTML body
and I'll just do a copy paste
and I'll drop in the closing tags here
for slash body, slash html.
And now I simply just wanna print out those values
that I retrieved from a configuration file.
So, I'll print out the max cart size.
Oh and a small typo here,
this should be maxCartSize.
Okay, good, fixed that one.
Ooh, close.
And actually let me add a little br here,
line break,
just to separate the lines here.
And then let me just print out the team name
and that's what I read earlier in this code.
And that's kind of it.
This looks good.
So, this basically just prints out the values
that we retrieve from the configuration file.
Simply showing the output there
in our HTML.
So, this looks really good,
I'm excited about this.
Good job.
All right, so let's go ahead and test this out.
So, we can test this by running our servlet directly.
So, I can move down to this testparamservlet
and I can do a right click,
and I can choose run as,
and then run on server.
And wow, this looks really good.
So, here it said max cart of 99
and team project name of The Coding Gurus,
because we're awesome.
And that's all the information that we read
from that XML file that we set up,
our web.xml,
so it read the max shopping cart size
and also the project team name.
And our servlet read that information
and displayed the html content.
So, this is great.
This is exactly what we wanted to do.
So, I would say, mission accomplished.
Good job.