Hey, so let's go ahead and do
a project review of our application.
So our main focus was to create a full working
JSP and Servlet application that connects to a database.
And we actually covered that in the previous videos.
So we went through and set up our database environment
and then we went through and wrote
the code for listing students.
Next we learned how to add a new student,
how to update a student, and how to delete a student.
So I'd like to say mission accomplished (chuckles).
We accomplished all the major features that you need
when you build a database application.
We covered all of the good stuff.
So you also have the source code that you can download.
There's also the database scripts, along with
setup instructions, and also, this is
a really good start for your own application.
So maybe it's a school project, or maybe
you're getting up to speed for a project at the office.
A good start to help you out, so anyway,
congratulations for making it this far,
and again, mission accomplished, oorah.