Hey, in this video we're gonna cover
JSTL Internationalization.
So first off, what is internationalization?
Well, it's basically the process of designing an application
where you can adapt it to different languages
without having to make changes to your source code,
and I think you've seen some of these before.
So if you visit any travel site or hotel site,
they'll give you the option to view their information
in a different language.
So here's one of my favorite hotels in India,
the JW Marriott in Bangalore,
and up in the top right you have a link there
for the different flags of the different countries,
so you can choose that link
and then it'll allow you to view this website,
this hotel website, in a different language.
So here we can choose German,
and now they'll show you the site in German,
so all the tags, and all the labels, and so forth,
they've dropped in the German equivalent,
so if you're speaking German,
you could easily go through and book a hotel here
using this information.
And likewise, if you're traveling from a different country,
say you're coming from Spain,
then you can just simply move down and say,
"Hey, I'd like to see the site in Spanish,"
and there you go.
So note how this is really easy, really cool.
The folks that built this site,
they simply set up internationalization up front,
and then they allowed the application
to just swap in a different language
for different values accordingly.
And in the following videos,
I'll show you how you can use JSP
to actually internationalize your own website.
All right, so the term internationalization
is frequently abbreviated as I18N,
and you may wonder, well why did they come up with that?
Well, there's 18 letters
between the first I and the last n in the word,
so instead of having to write it out longhand every time,
you'll simply see folks make use of the abbreviation I18N,
and I know it's really geeky,
but I just wanted to share that with you,
'cause you'll see it a lot
in some of the documentation and journals.
So how do you do internationalization?
Well basically, instead of hard-coding text and messages
in your application,
instead what you'll do
is you'll make use of labels and placeholders.
So for greeting the user,
you'll simply have a label for greeting.
To reference their first name and last name,
you'll use labels for that.
To give them a welcome message,
you'll have a label for that.
So it's simply just a placeholder,
and then you'll supply the appropriate values and data
to insert there,
based on the language that the user has selected.
Now what you'll have to do is
for each language you're site's gonna support,
you need to create translated versions of each label.
So there's no magic here.
Java won't automatically create everything for you.
You'll have to create this special file
that will have the appropriate translations for a greeting,
or first name/last name, or the welcome message.
You'll have to create that file,
and I'll show you how to create that file
in the next set of videos.
So again, instead of hard-coding the messages
in your application,
we make use of these labels,
basically placeholders for a locale,
and a locale is basically a combination
of a language and a region.
So there's a number of different locales.
So here we have the first locale, en_US,
that's English that's based in the US,
en_GB, that's English based in the UK,
and there are differences between the two,
even though it's the same language,
depending on which country or region
that you're working with,
some things are different.
So as far as some of the differences here,
is formatting dates, numbers, and currency.
So in the US, when we display a date, short dates,
we simply use month, day, year,
however in the United Kingdom or Great Britain,
when they make use of short date, it's day, month, year,
so it's really confusing.
So those are just some of the differences, formatting dates.
Also, formatting numbers,
depending on what delimiters you'll use there,
and also formatting currency,
as far as using the actual currency symbol
for that given area.
One caveat here on the currency.
Formatting the currency
is only for giving the currency symbol,
like a dollar sign, or pound symbol, or euro symbol.
However, it will not do any currency conversion for you,
so it won't automatically connect,
and get the currency exchange, and convert it for you,
it's simply displaying formatting data.
You'll still have to convert the currency in the background
with your own Java code.
So just a heads-up there:
it's only for formatting and displaying information.
All right, so when it comes to internationalization,
JSTL has a collection of functions.
The first set of functions here is for setting the locale.
The next set is for making use of message bundles
and setting up a message bundle.
And then finally they have a collection of tags
for number and date formatting,
and we'll actually cover all of these tags
as we go through the following videos.
I'll show you how to set up a multi-lingual application,
and then we'll also make use of number and date formattings,
and so we'll provide some good coverage of these tags
in the following videos.
All right, so stay tuned,
a lot of good things in store,
and I'll see you there.
Thanks.