Hey, in this video, we're gonna cover
the JSTL Internationalization and formatting tags.
The main objective here
is that we actually wanna apply internationalization,
so we actually wanna build a multi-lingual application.
So again, we wanna build an app
where we can change to different languages
without having to modify the source code.
Here's an example of the sample app we're gonna create.
We'll show the user the basic information
using English based in the US.
Then we'll give 'em a link where they can choose,
change the language to Spanish.
And then finally, we'll give 'em another link
where they change it to view the information in German.
I'll show you how to build all of these code
in this video, and also, the following video.
Basically, what we'll do is we'll cover the overview,
like the slides and the background on it in this video.
The following video, we'll actually get our hands dirty
and write the code in Eclipse.
But don't worry, you'll see everything
on how it's all built out.
The big picture here is that we're gonna make use
of placeholders in our page.
Instead of hard coding the text,
we're gonna have placeholders,
one for greeting, first_name,
last_name, and welcome_message.
And depending on the language that we're using
or the locale that we're using,
we'll simply insert the appropriate data.
For example, if we're using Spanish,
we'll put in the Spanish greeting from Hola,
the Spanish information for first_name, last_name,
and the Spanish welcome_message of buenos dias.
And again, my rough interpretation there of Spanish,
but anyway, you get the idea,
and I'll show you how to pull all this together.
All right, and again,
you know how luv2code Chad Darby works.
I love to-do list, so the first thing we'll do
is create our resource files.
The second thing is creating our JSP page with labels.
Step three is to update the JSP page
to change the locale based on user selection.
All right, so a lot of good things here.
Let's go ahead and dig in.
All right, so step one is creating the resource files.
What we have to do
is create translated versions of our labels.
So, you'll need to make use of a separate service,
like maybe Google Translate or hire a translator.
You basically have to give
the translated versions of your labels.
Now, there's no magic here.
Java will not automatically translate your application.
You'll have to specify that translated information.
All right, now, this information is all based on locales.
So, what's a locale?
A locale is basically a combination
of the language code and the country code.
It's more than just the language
because there could be differences for a language
depending on your country.
For example, we have English based in US
and also English based in Great Britain.
And there are differences between the two
as far as the vernacular
and also, differences between formatting dates,
time, and currency, and so on.
So, locale is what we'll be looking at.
So again, locale is the combination
of language code and country code.
All right, step one, creating the resource file.
When you create the resource file,
the file must follow a specific name naming convention here.
You give your project name,
underscore, a language code,
underscore, a country code, .properties.
Here are some examples.
I have mylabels_es, for Spanish,
_ES, caps, for Spain, .properties.
So again, language code, country code.
A similar thing here for German, for Germany,
and English, Great Britain.
All right, so that's the file name.
Now, a little bit more here
on the country codes and language codes.
They're all based on ISO Standards,
so the language codes are based on ISO Standard 639-1.
It's basically the two-letter language code.
The country codes are also based on ISO Standard 3166-2,
which again is a two-letter country code.
You can follow those links there for details on codes
for your specific country and language.
All right, now, let's get down to the nitty-gritty.
Here's the file for the locale Spanish - Spain.
I need to create my file mylabels_es, for Spanish,
_ES, for Spain, .properties.
And in this file,
I need to give the appropriate information.
For label.greeting, I'll say Hola.
label.firstname, I have information there
A similar thing for label.lastname.
And finally, label.welcome for buenos dias, so on.
So, that's the idea.
Now, again, you need to manually create these files
by using either Google Translate or hiring a translator
to help you out with building up the properties file.
But again, you have to provide this data
for the Java system.
All right, so now we have
the label information taken care of,
now we need to use these labels in our JSP.
This is step two.
Basically, what we do is we make use
of the JSTL Tag Library format
and say fmt:message, and then we give the key,
and we simply give our label name.
That label name is from the properties file.
So, Label.greeting,
actually, JSP will insert that Label.greeting there
for that given locale.
Label.firstname, it will insert the information,
Label.lastname, and Label.welcome.
So again, based on the locale that the user selected,
JSP will actually substitute that value right there.
So, you'll get the information
for English or Spanish or German
or whatever country or locale that you selected
for your application.
All right, so that's the resource file,
so now, the next step, step three,
updating the JSP page to change the locale
based on the user selection.
Basically, what we'll do on our app
is that we'll put links at the top of the page
where the user can choose their language or locale.
And basically, they'll select these links
and we'll simply just send it back as a link to ourself
and we'll pass the locale as a parameter.
And then we can read that param
and then load the appropriate resource file
or resource bundle.
So, that's basically how we'll do it.
This is kind of plain vanilla.
We could dress it up, flag, images, and so on,
but here, just get the point so far.
The coding for these links here, we just set up an href,
so we have anchor href, we point to our JSP page,
and then in red, we say theLocale equals,
and then we give that locale, en_US
or ES for Spanish, or DE for German,
and that's basically it.
That sets up a link.
Now, on the next slide,
I'll show you how to pull it all together
but this part just sets up the links at the top of our page.
All right, so we have the links coming in.
So now, in this page, we're basically gonna read those links
and set the values accordingly for the locale.
We can access the link values that were set,
or selected by the user, by using param.theLocale.
On the second line here, we check the value
to see if it's not empty, then we'll use param.theLocale,
and that came from that href link.
Now, in the event that that value is empty or not available,
then our else clause here will make use
of pageContext.request.locale.
So, every HTTP web request that comes in,
the web browser will send the default locale
based on the user's operating system.
So, the bottom line here is that we'll be able to find out
what locale the user wants to use
and we'll set that as a variable.
So, c:set var="theLocale",
we'll have a reference to that
and we'll keep it in our session for later use.
Now, the next set of lines here, fmt:setLocale,
we actually set the locale and we give it a value.
So normally, folks would hard code it
with a given locale like en_US
but here, we're using it based on that variable
that we set up in the previous line.
And then finally, we tell JSP page
which resource bundle to use.
So here, we say setBundle,
we give the basename,
so that means the base name of the file,
and then JSP will append the appropriate locale
and load the appropriate properties files
that you can use in this page,
and that's all handled here.
So, that's a little magic there
as far as reading that properties file
based on the appropriate locale that the user selected.
All right, good stuff so far.
All right, so, what I wanted to do here
is I want to give you an overview
of how that development process work out.
What we're gonna do is move into the next video
and we'll actually get our hands dirty
and I'll show you how to build all of this from scratch
in the Eclipse IDE, but I at least wanted to give you
some of the theories and the concepts first
and we can actually go through
and apply it in the next video, so I'll see you there.