Alright, so let's go ahead and move into Eclipse
and get our hands dirty.
So the first thing we need to do is
create our resource files for the different locales.
So in my tagdemo project, what I'll do is I'll move down
to the Java resources directory
and basically what I wanna do here is create a new package.
This is where I'll place my files.
So I'll just basically choose the existing package here
and I'll do a right click and I'll say new, package.
Alright so they'll give me the package name to start with
and then I'll finish it up so
com.luv2code.jsp.tagdemo.i18n.resources.
So that's the package name that I wanna use for this demo.
And once you're happy with that
you can go ahead and click the finish button.
Alright, great, so we have our new package now.
What I wanna do is actually create a new file
in this package directory.
So I'll just simply do a right click,
I'll say new and I'll move down to other
because they don't show file here
so I'll just say other.
And then I'll choose, under general,
I'll choose file
and then I'll click the next button
and now I can actually enter my file name.
So the file name I wanna use here is
mylabels.properties.
And once you're happy with that name
you can go ahead and click the finish button.
Okay great, so here's our file, mylabels.properties.
So what we wanna do here is simply enter the labels
and give the appropriate values for the labels
in this file.
So I'll say label.greeting, label.firstname,
label.lastname, and label.welcome.
And again, you can choose any names you want here
for these properties.
Simply stay consistent throughout your application.
Alright, so these are the basic labels here,
I'll go ahead and save this.
Now, this is what we call the default resource file.
Notice here, it's simply called mylabels.properites,
there's no reference to a specific locale.
So basically, this file will be used if we don't have
a locale file for a given language.
So if they come through with maybe French
or Chinese or Japanese and we don't have a locale file
for that then it will simply use this default file.
So in this case it will simply default to using English
for this example.
But that's basically it, so this is our default resource
file with all of our properties.
Alright, now let's go ahead and create some resource files
for some of the other languages.
And what I'll do here is I'll simply just copy this file,
do a right click and choose copy
and then I'll simply do a right click and choose paste.
Just a very simple copy paste example here.
And now for the new file, this is gonna be for Spanish
so I'll say, "mylabels underscore es, lowercase,
"underscore ES, in caps."
So again, once you're happy with this name
you can go ahead and click on OK.
And it's important that you get the file name extension
correct because it's gonna use that locale when it
actually looks up the actual properties file.
Alright, so this is the resource file for Spanish.
Alright now, it's just a copy paste from
the previous example.
What I'm gonna do here is put in the Spanish equivalent
here for the different entries.
So for greetings we'll say, "Hola,"
for first name, "Nombre de pila,"
last name, "Apellido," and again,
my Spanish is not that great.
And then our welcome message, "Bienvenidos,"
and I'll go ahead and fill out the rest.
Okay great, so this is the basic information here
for our Spanish version.
So again, we have to manually enter this.
You can get this information via Google Translate
or talking to a friend who knows Spanish
and they can help you out
but you have to manually provide this data,
there's no magic here.
Alright, so that's there, let's copy this file
and let's paste it again because we're gonna set up
our file for German.
So I'll just do a copy paste here
and for the new name I'll say,
"mylabels underscore de, lowercase,
"underscore DE, in all caps," so that's the locale.
So the language of German and the country of Germany.
And this is all based on those language codes
and country codes that we discussed in the previous videos.
Alright so let's look at the German file here.
So, again, it's a copy paste of our Spanish file,
we simply need to change this over to use
the appropriate German equivalents.
So here for greetings it's, "Hallo,"
first name is, "Vorname."
"Nachname," for last name,
and welcome, "Willkomen," and so on.
I know a little bit of German,
I studied it in high school but I forgot a lot of it so
(laughs)
I'm not gonna try and mess it up too bad.
So anyway, here's our resource file here for German.
So again, note the file name, "mylabels underscore de,
"underscore caps DE," and again, remember the locale
is the combination of the language code
and the country code.
Okay great, so we have this lined up
and this looks good so far.
So right now we have three files,
we have our default file, that doesn't specify a locale,
we have a properties file here for Spanish,
and then we have another properties file here for German.
So, this pretty much takes care of our step one
as far as creating our resource files.
In the following videos, we'll actually make use
of these resource files in our JSP page.
And we'll cover that in the next video
but this takes care of step one as far as
creating our resource files.
So, good job so far.