Alright, so we have our
resource files taken care of.
The next step is creating the JSP page with labels.
So we're actually gonna use those labels
that we defined in our resource files.
Alright, so lets move down to our web content directory.
What we wanna do here is create a new JSP file.
So I'll simply do a right click, I'll say new...file.
And the name that I will give for the file
I'll call it i18n-messages-test.JSP.
We can go ahead and click the finish button.
Alright, so imma go ahead and expand the window here.
And i'll do my normal housekeeping work.
So first I'll drop in the taglib references
for the core tags and the formatting tags.
Now let me just fix up line one for a second.
Just throw the pre-fix down at the end.
I don't know I'd like to keep it consistent there.
Alright so those are our taglibs.
Now we'll do the normal html housekeeping.
Just html tags and our body.
Alright, So now we can start coding
and so what we're gonna do is make use
of the formatting tag. And we're gonna reference
those labels from our resource files.
So here I make use of format message.
I'll say key=label.greeting
So that's the actual entry or the properties file
that's in our resource file label.greeting
I'll just put a little line break here
to make things look pretty.
So that should give me the greeting
based on whatever resource that we're using at a given time
and then I'll just repeat that process here.
Format message key label.firstname
and then we'll just put a first name in here, John.
And again drop in another line break.
And let me just copy this first name line
and do a similar thing here for last name.
So I'll just change, instead of first name,
I'll say last name. And I'll just fix this name to be Doe.
Alright, cool.
So that takes care of first name and last name.
Now our final thing is our welcome message.
So we'll say format message and then the
key=label.welcome.
Okay, great. So this looks really good so far.
So, What we did here was we made use
of that format message tag and we give our
reference to the key and they key is the actual property
from our resource file that we're gonna reference.
So we use the key for our label.greeeting.
First name, last name, welcome.
And I can swing back over to that property
so I'll just verify that label.greeting
first name, last name, welcome.
And the key is, they each have to be consistent.
Make sure you use the same names
that you have in your properties file.
Alright, well this looks good so far.
This takes care of step two as far as
making use of our labels in our JSP page.
On the following video, we'll actually show you
how to set the low cal based on the user selection.
But this is good work so far. So, great job.