Alright, so we're making some good progress
here, so in step three, we're gonna update the JSP page
to change the Locale based on user selection,
so basically, we're gonna give them links
at the top of the page, where they can choose
English, Spanish or German,
and then will show the appropriate data, accordingly.
Alright, so let me give myself some white space, here,
and what I like to do right here,
around line eight is go ahead and add some href links,
so I set up an anchor href=i18n, messages test.jsp,
and I usually use a question mark to pass over a parameter,
and I have the Locale=en_US, so English based in the US.
This is basically just a link back to this same JSP page,
and a little later, we're gonna read that data
and process on it, accordingly,
but for now, we're just setting up the links,
so let me just copy this first link, here
and just paste it about three times,
and then I go through and change it up for
the different languages here.
So, on the second item here, this is for Spanish,
so I'll do es underscore ES, in all caps,
and for the description of the link text,
I'll say Spanish,
and in parens, I'll say ES for Espania, or Spain;
I'll do a similar thing here, for Germany,
de underscore DE, so the language is German,
and the country is Germany, DE.
Again, using those language codes
from the previous lectures;
alright, so that's basically it, here for our links,
so on our JSP page, we'll have links along the top,
where the user can select the link and change it
to a different locale, so this is good, so far.
Alright, so let's move up top and let's do some processing,
here, 'cause we need to change the locale
based on parameter input being passed in;
okay, great, so what I'm doing here,
is I'm setting up a variable, here called theLocale,
and this is a variable that I'm gonna use a little later;
the actual value for it, I make use of that param
being passed in theLocale,
so I check to see if the param is not empty;
if it's not empty, then I use that param.theLocale,
else, I make use of the locale that's passed in
via the pageContext.request,
and then, this locale variable that I'm setting up;
I make the scope=session, so that's the basic piece, there,
so now we know at least what value that they're using,
or that they've selected for the locale,
and we have it set in this variable, called theLocale.
So now, on line nine, I'll actually set theLocale
based on that information, and again, I use the dollar sign,
curly brace, the JSP expression language
to actually set theLocale, based on that param
that I just set up in line five.
And then the final thing I need to do here,
is actually set a reference to the bundles;
I need to tell it which bundle base name to use,
so for the base name, I give the actual package name
of where the file is located,
so it's com luv2code jsp tagdemo i18n.resources,
and then the actual file name,
so the last entry there is the base file name, mylabels.
And remember, we have different versions of that
mylabels file, for Spain, for Germany, and it's
a dot properties, and again, remember JSP
will handle appending the actual locale on there,
and also appending the name dot properties
on there, accordingly.
So that's all kind of built into the JSP system,
so again, just highlighting, this is the actual package name
that we created a little earlier,
and then mylabels is the actual base name of the file,
and then you have the different variations of it
based off of that.
Alright, so this looks really good so far,
with setting up our bundle;
we can go ahead and save this file, and we can go ahead
and try it out.
Alright, so let's try it out, let's move to our file, here,
i18n messages test, messages test.jsp, right click,
choose Run As, and then choose Run on Server,
and we're up and running; I noticed one, small cosmetic
thing here, that's kinda annoying me, here;
notice up top, we have our links, and then we have "Howdy"
on the same line.
I think I forgot to put in a line break or
a horizontal rule, so let me go back into this file, here,
and add that, so I'm gonna add an hr for horizontal rule,
so under my links, here on line 22, some whereabouts;
I'll hit Enter, on line 23, I'll enter an hr,
just a horizontal rule, just to give us
a nice division of labor, here.
So let's go ahead and save this file, and then I should
be able to go back to my JSP and just do a refresh on it
and see this new alignment;
so there's my file, just do a refresh on it,
and there we go, cool, alright, so that looks better.
So right now, we're looking at just the default locale,
here, that's coming through,
so nothing was selected, so it'll default
to just using English; if I choose the link for Spanish,
note the locale being passed over, as the parameter
is es_ES, so we'll see everything in Spanish, here;
as far as everything from our labels that are based
in Spanish, and then we can move forward,
and we could do a similar thing, here,
by clicking on the link for Germany.
And again, now we're seeing the information in German,
so the nice thing to notice here, is that this
all happens in the background for you;
we did the work up-front of creating those translated
resource files, but now JSP will actually handle picking out
the appropriate file and displaying
the information accordingly.
Now, there's one, little thing I want to change, here;
I actually want to tell the user what locale
they're looking at, or what language they're looking at,
'cause they may wonder "what language is that?"
So, let me move into this file; I'll enter an hr,
just a horizontal rule, and I'll just tell them
the selected locale, and then I'll make use of that variable
that we set up earlier in our file, here.
So theLocale$ curly brace, JSP expression language,
and that'll basically just display the value
of that variable that we set up a little earlier,
so I have this new code, here, it's in place;
I can go up and hit the Save button,
and now I can go back to my JSP page, and I can go through
and click on some of the links.
So, English, note the new entry, here at the bottom,
Selected locale, en_US,
go for Spanish, again, the new entry here at the bottom,
and then finally, a similar thing for German.
So, cool, that's a nice little enhancement,
just to help us out, mainly a training exercise,
but a good thing to play around with,
so I think we're pretty much done with this
internationalization exercise, so we basically have
a multilingual app, using JSP and the JSTL tags, good job.