Hey, in this video, we're gonna cover JSTL Function Tags.
Alright, so we've made a good tour so far
with Core Tags, now we'll spend some time
and we'll focus on Function Tags.
So, the Function Tags are basically a collection
of very lightweight function routines you can use.
They're divided into two main areas.
One is the Collection Length, so you can pass it
a, an array list or collection, or a string,
and it'll give you the length of that string.
Then, they also have a collection
of String manipulation tags.
So again, very lightweight stuff like
converting things to upper-case, lower-case,
trimming, splitting, joining, so on and so forth.
So I'll cover a small numnber of the tags
here in this video, and then in the following video
I'll talk about splitting and joining.
But again, I won't have time to cover every tag
in every option, so, just make use of the
resources here, look at like the JSTL JavaDoc
and the JSTL Specification for the gory details.
Now, every page that uses the function tags
they must include this reference.
So you get the taglib, with this uri,
and most commonly used prefix of fn.
And again, you have to do this
exactly the same for it to work.
Alright so let's look at an example,
and again these function tags are very simple,
very lightweight tags for doing some operations.
So the first thing I do is I set up a variable,
the var="data", and the value="Luv2code",
and then I simply wanna get the length of the string.
And so I make use of that function tag in red
fn:length, and then data.
So those will basically give me the length
of the string, so in this case,
the length of luv2code is eight,
pretty simple, very straightforward.
Alright, so let's go into Eclipse
and let's try this out.
So I'll move into that tagdemo project,
move down to WebContent, and imma create a new file here.
So I simply do a right-click, I say new, file.
Now the name of the file I'm gonna create
is called function-test.jsp.
And once you're happy with that name
you can go ahead and click on the finish button.
Alright let me expand my window here.
Let me go ahead and drop in those taglib uris.
Have a little cheat sheet where I just
copy and paste from, 'cause I wanna make sure
I get those, or copy those in the exact same way,
'cause if not I'll have problems,
and I don't like problems.
(laughs)
Alright, so we have this set up.
Let's go ahead and do some of our HTML housekeeping.
And now let's go ahead and set up a variable right now.
So like we had in the slides,
I'll set the variable data equals to
the value of Luv2code.
And now what I'm gonna do is make use
of that function tag, so I'll say
length of the string, and I just drop in
the same string $, JSP expression language,
and then I call that function.
So again I say, fn:length and then in parens
I simply pass in the variable reference here.
So I'll pass in data that I set up on line nine.
And it'll basically take that string there
and give me the length of that string of luv2code.
And also one thing to be aware of is that
occasionally Eclipse may give you an error message.
You can safely ignore it, sometimes Eclipse
has problems processing or passing, some of the
JSTL tags, so in this case you can safety ignore it.
And let's just save our file and let's go ahead and run it.
So I'll do a right-click, I'll choose Run As,
and then Run on Server, and I open up that URL
and there it is, length of the string luv2code,
is eight, so this works out really good.
Just very simple example of using
the JSTL function tags.
Now let's go back in here and try something else
or add in some more work, 'cause that was just
too simple for us almost.
(laughs)
So let me clear out, get some white space here,
let me put in some line breaks.
And what I like to do here is get the
uppercase version of the string luv2code
so put the $ in there again.
And now I'll make use of that (mumbles)
so I'll say ${
and fn:toUpperCase,
and in parens I'll put in data.
So in this example here I'm just calling that
to uppercase function, so fn:toUpperCase
and passing in data.
Alright, let's go ahead and save this,
and move back to our browser,
let's hit the little refresh icon here.
Great, this looks good, so the uppercase version
of luv2code is LUV2CODE in all caps.
Really, really good, so, good job with that.
Then again we're just having fun here
playing around with some of these JSTL functions.
So let me copy line 13 again, the line breaks,
put some more line breaks there.
So now I wanna make use of one of those functions here,
starts with, so I kinda zoom out a little bit
to give me some more room to play with.
So basically what I wanna do here is
see if a string starts with the characters luv.
So I make use of that function, starts with,
pass in data, that's the string we're testing against.
With luv, that's the string that we're looking for
to see if it starts with.
Alright, so we have this function laid out here,
starts with, and let's try it out.
So let's save the file, move back over to our browser,
click the refresh icon, and great,
so here it says the string luv2code
starts with luv, that's really good, true.
So, so anyway, just a nice little example here
of making use of some of the JSTL tags
and how you can use them in your application.
Good job.