Hey.
In this video we're gonna learn about
the JSTL function tags
for splitting and joining.
So, the split function,
it basically splits a string
into an array of substrings
based on a given delimiter.
And here's the signature for this method,
so you call split,
you pass in the data string,
you pass in the delimiter,
and it'll return you an array of strings
that are all based on that splitting of the delimiter.
So, lets look at a little code example here.
At the beginning I set up a variable called data
and I give a string value.
Here I have four cities,
Singapore, Tokyo, Mumbai, and London,
and they're all CSV
separated by a comma.
So, on the next line I actually make use
of that function split.
So, here I say C colon set var,
citiesArray,
value equals
and then inside of the quotes I make use
of the function split.
So, I'll say function split,
I give data,
that's the string from the previous line,
and then I have it split on a comma,
so I put the comma inside single quotes there.
And that'll basically split that string
from a single string to multiple strings
and a return at value as an array of strings.
Okay, stay with me here,
and it'll assign it to cities array.
So, that's how that part works out.
It takes one big string
and splits it up into an array of strings.
Now, lets take a look at the join function.
This join function goes the other way.
It basically concatenates a string array
into a single string based on a delimiter.
So, here's the signature here.
Call join, you pass in an array of strings,
comma a delimiter,
then it returns it as one big string
based on that information.
All right, so lets take a look at a code example.
So, previously we had an array of strings
called cities array,
and I simply wanna join it together.
So, here I'll make use of function colon join,
cities array comma star,
and that'll give me this variable.
And so you can see the print out here at the bottom,
it'll basically take that array,
join it together using that asteric
for the join character
and that's how that'll work out.
And we'll see a good example of this
once we move into Eclipse.
All right, so, we're in Eclipse now,
moving into that tag demo project.
Gonna move down to web content
and I'm gonna create a new file here.
And the file name that I'll give here is called
split-join-test.jsp.
And I'll go ahead and hit the finish button.
So, let me go ahead and move up here
and expand my window a bit.
Now lets go ahead and drop in our taglib references
up top like we had before.
I'll go through and just do my HTML housekeeping.
So, I'll go ahead and set up a variable for data
and I'll give it the value of Singapore,
Tokyo, Mumbai, and London.
All great cities that I've traveled to in the past.
And now what I wanna do is basically split this data.
So, I'll set up the cities array
and value equals function split data
comma the delimiter.
And the actual delimiter we'll use here is the comma symbol.
And I just close off that tag.
So, basically here I'm just doin' a split
on that data that we set up in line eight.
So, that CSV or that comma separated list here,
we're gonna split it
and then we'll get a cities array that we can use later.
And what I wanna do here is clear out some white space,
and I actually wanna go through and loop around
and print out every item in that cities array.
Just so we can verify that it is
set up in a separate array,
in its separate elements.
So, what I'll do here is I'll set up this for each loop,
the var equals tempCity and the items is citiesArray.
And I have a small typo within line 14,
let me take off that extra slash,
there we go,
now I can do my slash forEach.
Cool.
And I'm gonna loop through this citiesArray
from earlier,
and I'll simply make use of this tempCity here.
So, I'll say tempCity
dollar sign curly brace
and I'll put a br for line break.
That pretty much covers it.
So, that's our cities array up top,
and then we do the forEach
to simply loop to that array
and print everything out.
So, this looks good so far.
Lets go ahead and save this file and run it.
Right click, run as,
run on server.
Okay, great, so here's our result split demo.
Remember it was this big long string that we started with,
then we split it based on the comma
and then we can print out each element of that array.
So, a good example of using the JSTL split function.
All right, so lets go ahead and
get some white space here and some room to work with.
And I'll work on the join demo.
So, basically what I'm gonna do here
is I'm gonna join,
so I'm gonna take that cities array
and then I'm gonna join it using a star
to join it together.
So, then one big array of strings
and I'll just kind of concatenate them all together
using the star as the delimiter.
And then I'll just print out the results of joining that.
And that's basically it.
There's nothin' else we really have to do here
for this example.
All right, so let's go ahead and save this file.
Actually, I have one typo, I just found it.
I need an extra paren here.
Okay, great, so the paren, that'll set off,
okay, good, I'm okay now.
That was a good little catch there.
So, save this file,
do a refresh,
and then here's the results of joining.
So, it took that array of strings
and then it made use of that asteric symbol
to join or concatenate everything together
as a single string.
So, this was pretty good.
We went through and had a good time
to play around with some of the functions
here in the JSTL for splitting,
and also the JSTL functions for joining.
So, good job so far.