Hey.
In this video, we're gonna learn how to create
a database application using servlets and JSP.
So for our class project,
the main idea is that we're gonna build
a full working JSP and servlet application
that connects to a database.
So, we're gonna build the front end pages using JSP.
We'll build some of the back end controller code
using servlets, and we'll hook all of this into a database,
and it will actually talk to a MySQL database.
Now, I'll show you how to build all of this from scratch.
Alright, so before we get into the coding,
let's look at a quick demo of the application.
This is an application for a fictional company
called FooBar University.
We can list all of the students,
we can add a new student,
and we can also perform some actions on a student,
like updating or deleting a student.
Let's go ahead and start off with adding a student.
Here's our add student form.
We can type in a first name and last name for a student,
and then we'll give his email address, bill@foo.com.
Once we're happy with this,
we can go ahead and click on the save button.
Okay, this looks really good.
So note here, we have this new student, Bill Appleby,
and his email address is bill@foo.com.
This is great.
So, we've added a new student.
Alright, so now let's go ahead and update a student.
I'll go ahead and click the update button here.
So for Bill Appleby,
I'm simply gonna change his email address.
So instead of foo.com,
we'll change it to
bill@luv2code.com, because he loves to code.
Yeah.
Then we'll hit the save button.
Okay, so this looks good also.
Here's Bill Appleby, and note his email address,
bill@luv2code.com, so we were successful there
in updating his email address.
Now, let's try this other item here of deleting the student.
It'll first prompt you if you want to delete the student.
We'll go ahead and click on OK.
Now, note it refreshes the screen,
it deleted that user,
so Bill Appleby is no longer in our list of students.
So, the delete operation worked out just fine for us.
Alright, so that covers the main CRUD features here
for an application.
So, we'll learn how to insert, update, delete,
and list all of the students for a database,
and we'll actually learn how to do all of this from scratch
in the following videos.
But first, what I wanna do is go ahead
and take a look at the actual database.
So, we have a database out here
with the given database table.
We have a table called student.
If we simply do a query on this table,
we can see the list of students that we have.
So select rows, and it'll show us our five students.
So, these are the five students that we have out here
in our database right now.
And again, when we write all the code,
our application's gonna interact with this database table,
insert, update, and delete,
and perform queries on this table.
And again, we'll figure out all the details
on how to set this database table up,
how to populate it with data,
and then how we can manage it and use it in our application.
Alright, so we have a lot of good things in store here,
but you know me.
I love to-do lists.
So, the first thing we're gonna do
is learn how to set up our database dev environment.
Then, we'll learn how to list the students.
Next, I'll show you how to add a new student,
and then from there, we'll learn how to update a student.
And then finally, I'll show you how to delete a student.
And again, we're gonna cover all of this
step-by-step from scratch.
So, we'll cover each section here in separate videos,
and I'll walk you through all of the code.
We'll write all the code together,
and we'll test it out, and we'll make sure it works.
By the end of the video series,
we'll have a full database application
using servlets and JSP.