Hi, in this video,
I'm going to show you how to download
the JDBC source code for our project.
So, when we work on a project,
you actually have two options on how
you want to work through the code.
The first option is that you can follow along
and write the code with me.
So I have a set of starter files that you can start with,
but then the bulk of the coding you'll actually do
from scratch, so a lot of hands-on coding
and you can follow along in the videos with me.
Or, you have an option two, you can skip
writing the code. (laughs)
You can kind of just sit back and enjoy the code.
And so I have the full solution code available
so all of the final code you'll have available.
You can access it, review it,
and then deploy it to your system.
So, either way, you can write the code from scratch
with me or you can make use of option two and simply
just download all the finished code and deploy it.
So now how do you actually download the code?
Well, in this video lecture there's a View Resources button
in the upper right corner of the screen.
So you simply click that button, there's going to be
a file out there called jsp-servlet-jdbc-source-code,
and you simply download that zip file to your file system.
All right, so here's my file system,
and let's assume that I've already downloaded the code,
the browser will normally put this
into the Downloads directory, so here's my zip file
that's been downloaded by my browser,
and what I normally like to do is just create
another little training directory.
I like to call it My Java Training
and just copy that zip file over there
and then I can move it to this directory
and now I can simply unzip that zip file.
All right, great, so I've unzipped the file here.
So now I have this folder called
jsp-servlet-jdbc-source-code.
Now there's a couple of files in here.
The first one is a README.txt, just a basic about me file,
SETUP-Instructions as far as how to set up
the project and deploy it.
There's a collection of SQL scripts
for creating a user and creating our database tables.
We'll talk about those SQL scripts later.
And then here are our starter files, so our starter files
are really just a collection of some CSS files
like some cascading style sheets.
We also have some configuration information
for database connection and also our database driver.
We'll talk more about these files in some later videos,
but these are kind of the starter files
if you wanted to kind of start
from scratch working with me.
And then also again, if you don't want to write the code,
you simply want to get the final solution,
well then this is in the web-student-tracker-solution
directory, so this has all of the Java source code
that we'll create, all the completed code is there,
and also in the WebContent directory,
all of the JSP files and related web assets,
so basically everything's here.
You can grab this off the shelf as a final solution
and then take it and deploy it, so either way.
You can start from scratch or you can simply
take the solution and move on.
So the choice is yours. (laughs)
All right, so anyway, just wanted to let you know
about the files that are out there,
kind of a quick description for them,
and in some of the following videos
I'll dive deeper into this directory structure
and then we'll make use of some of the these files
to get our environment set up.
All right, good job.