Hey! In this video,
we're gonna learn how to install MySQL on Microsoft Windows.
So as far as the topics here,
the first thing we're gonna do is download MySQL,
and then we'll install MySQL,
and then finally we'll verify our installation.
Alright, so a lot of good stuff.
Let's go ahead and jump in and get started.
Alright, so what we need to do is open up a web browser,
and visit the MySQL website.
So, here in my browser I'll type in
dev.mysql.com/downloads and this will take me to the
MySQL downloads site.
Alright, once I'm at the page
I want to download the MySQL community server
and on the community server page
they have an option here for downloading it
for Microsoft Windows.
I'll go ahead and select that option for download.
This will take me to the download page
and I'll select the option here for downloading
the Microsoft Windows MSI Installer,
and I'll choose the web version.
It's a small lightweight version.
Now, normally they want you to log-in,
but in this case I'll say no thanks,
just go ahead and start my download.
Alright, so your browser will prompt you to save the file.
I'll go ahead and save the file and
let's start downloading it to my file system.
Okay, great, so it's downloaded.
We can open up our Windows Explorer,
move into the downloads folder,
and now what I want to do is simply start the installer.
So this will start up a normal
Microsoft Windows install wizard.
Alright, so the standard thing here, right?
License agreement, go ahead and check the box
I accept the agreement.
Go ahead and click next.
Here we want to keep the developer defaults,
so make no changes there, developer default.
Next, they're gonna check
some of the requirements on your system.
So, the first product listed here is the MySQL workbench.
We need to install the Microsoft Visual C++ run time
but the installer will actually do this for you.
So, we'll simply select that and we hit execute,
and it'll go out to the web and
it'll download the appropriate dependencies that you need.
So, I'll just click, click, click,
accept all the defaults as it goes through this example.
And at that point, we have everything available
for MySQL Workbench.
They'll prompt us about some of the other products,
you can just go ahead and click past that,
and then just hit execute and it'll start
downloading all the dependencies that you need.
So, this will take awhile.
I'll kind of step away and I'll come back once
everything is downloaded.
Okay, great, so we've downloaded everything.
Note here we have all green checks here
and the status is complete for everything.
So we're in good shape.
So, we can go ahead and click next.
Click next one more time.
Here, we'll set up some of the networking.
We'll just keep all the defaults.
Click next.
At this point, we need to define our root password.
So, you can give whatever you want for your root password.
You can call it fubar or whatever.
I'm gonna give a long password,
just so it comes out as a strong password,
but you can give whatever you want.
You can give a four letter password if you'd like.
They key item here is that you need
to remember that password.
Make sure you write it down. (laughs lightly)
Alright, I'll go ahead and click next.
I'll keep the defaults here.
It's gonna run MySQL as a Windows service.
I'll click execute, and it'll go off
and it'll start applying our server configurations.
I'll hit finish, I'll hit next.
And, now we're going to do a simple test
to connect to our server.
Click the check button.
Connection is successful, we're okay.
And then we hit next and finished, and next one more time.
And at this point we hit finish,
and it'll actually start up the MySQL server.
So, now what we're gonna do is verify our installation.
So, we're gonna use this MySQL workbench.
It's simply a web gooey tool.
I'm sorry, it's simply just a gooey tool,
that allows you to connect to your MySQL database.
So, here I just enter that same password
I did during installation,
and at this point I have a gooey open,
and I can actually query some of the tables.
So, MySQL always starts off with some sample tables for you.
I'm gonna access this one table called city.
And I'll just do a right click, say select rows,
and this'll give me all the rows from this sample table.
So again, really here, we're just verifying
that we can connect to the database and do a basic query.
So, this all looks really, really good.
So, our server is up and running and we can query it.