In this video, we're gonna learn
how to set up the database table for our classroom project.
So what we'll do is we'll make use of two database scripts.
The first script will create a user,
and the second script will set up
our student tracker database.
And in the following slides, I'll walk through
each one of these scripts and show you
how they work in detail.
All right, so let's go and take a look at our first script.
It's basically gonna create a new MySQL user
for our application.
The user's gonna have a user ID of webstudent
and it'll also have a password of webstudent.
All right, so let's go ahead and move into
MySQL Workbench and run this script.
So again, MySQL Workbench is basically just a GUI
for managing or administering your MySQL database.
Let's go ahead and connect to the database.
I'll use my root account, and I'll use the same
root password that I used when I installed a MySQL database.
Then I'll hit OK.
And so at this point, I'm in MySQL Workbench.
Now what I'll do is, I'll actually open that file
that we just discussed, the 01-create-user.
So I'll move up to the File menu, and I'll say
File, Open SQL Script,
and then I'll move over to
where I extracted the file, so in my case,
I have this folder called my-java-training.
And then the extract of that jsp-servlet-jdbc-source-code.
There's a folder here called sql-scripts.
The one script that I'm looking for here
is the 01-create-user.sql.
So again, this script basically creates a user.
Here we have CREATE USER 'webstudent'
IDENTIFIED BY 'webstudent'.
So we have the user ID and the password,
so that'll actually create a MySQL user for us.
And then on line three, we simply grant privileges,
so this allows the user to create more tables
and create more stored procedures and so on.
All right, so this looks good so far.
So now, to run this, I simply hit the little yellow
lightning bolt here, that will execute the SQL script.
At the bottom we'll have the little green check marks,
and that means, hey, everything's successful, we're happy.
So at this point, we have our user created.
So that looks good so far.
Now, the next part here is making use of the
02-student-tracker.sql.
What this is gonna do is it's gonna actually create
a new database table for us called student,
and then it's gonna load that database table
with some sample data.
So that's the main idea of this second script.
All right, so let's go ahead and move back
into SQL Workbench, and let's run this script.
So first, I have to open the file.
So I move back up to my File menu again,
and I'll say File, Open,
say Open SQL Script.
And in that same directory, I'm gonna look for that file,
02-student-tracker.sql,
so our same sql-scripts directory there.
All right, so that's the 02.
So let's go ahead and click Open.
All right, now, whoa.
There's a lot of stuff in this file.
Don't let this file overwhelm you.
It's simply an output of a dump.
But basically, what we're gonna do in this file
is two main things.
We're gonna create a table called student,
with the various columns, and then we'll go through
and we'll insert sample data.
So a lot of other stuff that's out there,
but the main items here, we create the table
and then we insert sample data into that table.
All right, so let's go ahead and run this one again.
So again, we make use of that little yellow lightning bolt
there on the tool bar.
We click that button there.
And that'll execute, and again, we'll see our
little green check marks here at the bottom.
So that means that, hey, this script executed successfully.
Now, over on the left-hand side, we need to do
a right-click, and then we need to say Refresh All.
So this will basically refresh the list of schemas
or tables, and we'll see our new item here.
So there we go, our web_student_tracker,
so that's our database that we've created.
And then inside of our database, we have a table
called student, right, so there's our table right there.
And the student table has four columns.
It has id, first_name, last_name and email.
So that's good.
And then, we can actually query this table
and look at the data by doing a right-click and
choosing Select Rows.
So once we do this then, here, there's our sample data.
So we added just five sample students here,
Mary, John, Ajay, Bill and Maxwell.
So this looks really good.
So we have our test user created.
We have our database table created,
and we've loaded some sample data.
So we're in really, really good shape now.
And in the following videos, we'll make use of
this database.
So, good job so far.