Hey.
In this video we're gonna learn how to set up Tomcat
for database connection pooling.
So, we start off with the following topics.
We'll discuss database connections in web apps,
we'll also learn about database connection pools.
Then we'll go through the step-by-step process
of setting up a pool in Tomcat.
And finally, we'll pull it all together
by testing our database connection pool configurations.
So a lot of great stuff in the video.
Let's go ahead and get started.
Alright, so whenever you need to connect
to a database using a web application you may think that
you only need a single database connection.
Unfortunately, this will not scale for multiple users.
This is very similar to, say for example,
you have a large number of users
and they all want to make use of one telephone.
So, your office only has one telephone
and you have 40 or 50 people
and they need to make use of the telephone
to make a phone call.
So, this wouldn't work out.
You'll have along queue and people will wait
to actually use the telephone.
So, we need to have a solution for this.
So, the best practice in the industry is
to make sure of database connection pools.
So, this will allow your app to scale
and handle multiple users quickly.
So, for all of those users who need
to make use of our application
and our Tomcat server will set up a pool of connections.
So, like a pre-configured pool of connections
that they can use and once they're done with it
they can put it back into the pool
and another user can reuse it.
So again, going back to our telephone analogy,
instead of simply having one phone in our office,
now our office may have 30 phones
or 50 phones for the various users to come in.
This'll give us high throughput and allow us
to handle more users in a shorter period of time.
Okay, so how do we set up a connection pool?
And you know how I love to do lists, I love step-by-steps.
So the first thing we need to do is
download the JDBC driver JAR file.
Then once we have that,
the next step is setting up the connection pool
in our context.xml file.
And then finally, one our thing's configured
and we can get a connection pool reference in our Java code
and I'll let you go through this step-by-step.
I'll show you have to work through it
and I will get everything configured
and we'll test everything at the end, so stay with me.
Alright so, let's take a look at step one:
downloading the JDBC driver JAR file.
In order to connect to a database you're gonna need
to have a JDBC driver for that given database.
So here we're gonna make use of mysql in the course,
so I can go through the URL listed here on mysql.com
and this will allow us to download the driver JAR file.
Once we have that JAR file downloaded,
then we can add it into a special directory
in our web app location called WEB-INF/lib.
This is a special directory where you place
any supporting JAR files
or any supporting libraries that your application will need.
So, in this case, we need to connect to the database,
so we'll place our JAR file inside of the
WEB-INF/lib directory,
and I'll show you that in the videos coming up.
Alright, step two: defining a connection pool.
So, we'll actually define the connection pool
inside of this file called context.xml.
This is a Tomcat specific file that basically tells Tomcat
how to connect to your database
and it also tells Tomcat how to configure your pool,
such as how many connections to create up front,
the minimum numbers of connections,
so on and so forth.
So, let's take a look at this file,
it's under directory WebContent/META-INF/
and the file name is context.xml.
So, since a small XML file,
we have a resource reference here in the middle.
So, the first thing you do,
is you give the actual name of the resource,
so here we have jdbc/web_student_tracker.
The name is basically the alias that we'll use later on
in our application to look up this connection pool,
so name is similar to alias.
On the next line here we tell Tomcat how we're going
to authenticate, so auth="Container" meaning that
the Tomcat server will actually handle the authentication.
Up next we have type="javax.sql.DataSource",
that's the actual name of the Java interface that we'll use
for communicating with the pool.
So, in the Java world, whenever you see DataSource,
just think connection pool.
Alright so, they use this generic term DataSource
but effectively that's the name of your connection pool.
Okay, on the next line here we discuss the actual size
of the connection pool so; maxActive="20",
so we're gonna have 20 connections in our pool
to start out with;
maxIdle="5" so you know if there are no users in our system,
we'll have at least 5 connections available;
and then the maxWait is the time in milliseconds
as for as how long someone can wait
before they get a connection.
So, right here its 10,000 milliseconds,
which translates over into ten seconds.
Alright so, that's kind of the size configuration stuff.
On the next line here-actually the next three lines-
we tell Tomcat how to connect to our database.
Alright so, we give it the username and password.
If you remember, that's the special mysql account
that we created earlier so those are our credentials.
Next, we give the actual driverClassName,
so the fully qualified name of the JDBC driver,
so we're using mysql here.
And then finally, we give the url to the database.
So our database is running on localhost
and the actual name of the database schema is called
student tracker and again we ran
some sequel code earlier
to create that database with the schema in mind,
tables and so on.
So basically, again,
this file here tells us how to connect
to mysql and also how to configure the pool,
as in regards to the actual size
or the number of connections.
Okay, great, so now that we've told Tomcat how to connect
to our database now we need
to somehow get that connection pool into our Java code.
So, using Java EE,
they have this technique called resource injection,
for your servlets,
so basically what this means is that
Tomcat will automagically set the connection pool
on your servlet.
And I'll actually show you the Java coding for it in a bit.
You simple make use of a special annotation called
a resource annotation in Tomcat
or your app server in general,
will actually set a connection pool servlet source code.
But don't worry, I'll show you all the code
and we'll kinda walk through it step-by-step
and we'll do everything from scratch.
Alright so, this kinda covers the theory.
In the following video we'll move into Eclipse
and we'll start writing some code.
So I'll see you in the next video.