Hey, in this video we're gonna go ahead
and test out our Database connection.
So, the first thing we need to do is
start off by creating a new project.
So, I'll go to the File menu
and I'll say New, Dynamic Web Project.
And the name that we'll give for this project,
we'll call it web-student-tracker.
We'll keep all the other defaults for the project,
and we'll click on the Finish button.
Alright, great, so Eclipse is gonna
create a new project for us
and it's gonna appear right here in the top left-hand.
So, we have this new project called web-student-tracker.
Which is great, so it's just a shell of a project.
There's not much there right now.
We need to go ahead and add some new information to it.
So, the first thing I want to do is
move into this WebContent directory,
because our first order of business is
to copy over the JDBC JAR file.
So, this JDBC JAR file for MySQL
will allow us to connect to the Database.
And what I'll do is
I'll actually move back to those starter files
that we had earlier in that download.
So, remember we had our download,
my stuff is in my-java-training.
Here is the extracted folders here
for jsp-servlet-jdbc-source-code.
I'm gonna move down to this folder here
called web-student-tracker-starter-files.
And I'm gonna move into the WEB-INF directory
and I'll move into the lib,
and there should be a file in here
called mysql-connector-java,
a version number, .jar.
So, that's our JDBC JAR file.
So, I simply wanna copy this file.
So, I'll do a Right-Click and I'll choose Copy.
Okay, great, so I have this file copied.
Well, now let me move back over to Eclipse.
Let's click on the WEB-INF/lib directory in my project,
and then I'll click Paste.
So, again, inside of Eclipse,
WEB-INF/lib, click on Paste.
And this should paste this new JAR file here,
so expand the folder and there it is, cool.
So, our new JAR file is part of our project now,
so this is great.
Alright, so now that I have the JAR file over here,
now what I'd wanna do is
copy over the connection pool configs.
So, I'll move back to my starter-files again,
and I'll move into this directory here
called META-INF, context.xml.
So, this context.xml, again, remember
it has our connection pool configuration information.
So, I'll go ahead and select this file, again,
do a Right-Click, we'll choose Copy.
And then once again I'll move back over to Eclipse,
I'll move into
the WebContent/META-INF directory in my project,
I'll Right-Click and I'll choose Paste.
Okay, awesome, so that's our context.xml file.
And so, I'll just Double-Click this file.
Just as a quick refresher here,
this has our Database connection information.
So, it gives us the name,
the driverClassName and url,
so on and so forth.
So, this is all set up and
things look okay so far.
Alright, so I'll go ahead and close this file.
So, now what I wanna do is actually
go ahead and get ready to write some code here.
So, the first thing I'm gonna do is create a package.
So, I'm gonna create a new package for my source code.
So, I'll move up to the Java Resources folder here
and I'll expand it.
And I'll select the src folder here,
and I'll just Right-Click and I'll say New
and I'll select New Java Package.
So, New Package.
So, this is a new package
where we're gonna place our source code.
So, the name for the package, I'll call it
com.luv2code.web.jdbc.
So, that's our package name.
And once we're happy with that,
we can go ahead and click on the Finish button.
Okay, excellent, so we have this new package.
Now what I wanna do is create a new Servlet.
So, this is a test Servlet that we're gonna create
that's gonna test our Database connection.
So, I'll say New and I'll choose Servlet.
Alright, so here's the Servlet.
So, the actual Class name I'll give,
I'll call it TestServlet.
Very simple, very straightforward.
And once you're happy here, click the Finish button.
Or actually, sorry, click the Next button.
We'll accept the default URL mappings here.
We'll click Next one more time.
And then on this dialog here,
we can uncheck some items.
So, uncheck the constructor,
and uncheck doPost.
So, your screen should look very similar to mine.
So, the one thing for Inherited,
and the one thing for doGet.
And everything else is unchecked.
And here, you can go ahead and click on Finish.
Alright, great, so now we have this very basic Servlet that
Eclipse created for us.
So, this is kinda our initial start, our initial layout.
And what we'll do here is we will go ahead and
add some code here to test out our Database connection.
So, the first thing I need to do is I need to
get a reference to the connection pool.
So, remember earlier I said that
we can make use of a Java EE feature where
the Java app Server, or Tomcat,
will actually inject the connection pool for us.
And so I'll show you how to do this.
So, we make use of this special annotation here
called @Resource.
So, we're gonna inject a resource, and we specify the name.
So, here we give name of jdbc/web_student_tracker.
And that's the same name we used in our context config file.
And now I give a field here, our data members,
I say private DataSource,
and then I'll just call it dataSource.
So, that's the actual handle
or reference to our connection pool.
Now, I'll go ahead and clean up some of the Imports here,
fix some of the errors, and so I'll
Import on javax.annotation for Resource,
select that option.
And then I'll do a similar thingy here for our DataSource.
And be careful with DataSource.
Make sure you Import javax.sql.DataSource.
There's a number of different ones out there,
make sure you get the right one,
javax.sql.DataSource.
Alright, great, now this name here for the Resource,
this is the exact same name as defined in our context.xml.
So, jdbc/web_student_tracker,
the exact same name.
You have to make sure these names match up
for Tomcat to give you the correct connection pool.
Alright, so we have all the connection pool stuff set up.
Let's go ahead and move into our doGet Method now.
Let's get ready to write some real code.
So, I'll give me some white space here
to kinda stretch out a bit.
And as you know, I always like to just
start off with writing some comments
as far as what this code's gonna actually do.
So, the first step is setting up the printwriter.
And then the second step is
getting a connection to the Database.
And then we go through and we create a SQL statement.
And then we go ahead and execute that SQL statement.
And then finally we process the result set.
So that's kinda the big idea,
the game plan for this doGet Method.
And then we'll cut the code
and we'll write all the code from scratch
on how this part works out.
Alright, so let's go ahead and dive into step one,
setting up the printwriter.
So again, this PrintWriter out is simply what we use
to send data back to the browser.
So, I say response.getWriter,
so that's my out object.
And then I also, I need to fix up the Imports here,
java.io.PrintWriter.
And then I'll also set the content type on this response,
so setContentType, and this will simply be text/plain.
'Cause right now I'm not really doing any HTML stuff,
I'm just keeping it simple for right now.
Alright, so step two is
getting a connection to the Database.
So, I'll set up some SQL objects here
and I'll set them to null
and then I'll actually get a connection.
So, I'll set up myConn = null,
I'll set up a myStmt,
and I'll also set up a ResultSet.
But right now it's null,
we haven't really assigned it to anything yet.
We'll assign it in those following steps.
And I'll go ahead and fix up the Imports.
And here I'll show you
an Eclipse trick on fixing the Imports.
They have this feature called Organize Imports.
So, I can go to Source,
and then I can choose Organize Imports.
And basically, Eclipse will go out
and try and resolve all the Imports for you,
and then it'll also ask you some questions.
So for here, for Statement, I say java.sql.Statement.
For Connection, java.sql.Connection, and hit Finish.
And then Eclipse will actually fix
all those Imports for you.
So, now we're good to go.
That's just a little Eclipse trick for you
that you can use later on.
Alright, now let's go ahead
and put this code inside of a try catch block.
So, try and then Exception,
and then I'll just say exc.printStackTrace.
This is kinda just
real quick and dirty for right now.
We'll get into all the fancy stuff in later videos,
but for now we just wanna make sure
that we can get a valid connection to a Database.
So, here I set up myConn = dataSource.getConnection(),
so I'm basically getting a connection to the Database,
and I'm actually getting that connection
from the connection pool.
Remember dataSource is the same thing as connection pool.
I'll just set up a little SQL statement here,
select * from student.
And I'll say myStmt = myConn.createStatement().
Alright, so now let's go ahead and execute that Query.
So, here I'll say myStmt.executeQuery,
I pass in the sql.
It'll return a ResultSet, so I assign it to myRs.
And remember those variables were defined
a little earlier in this code.
Now I simply need to process the ResultSet.
So, here I'll say while myRs.next(),
so while I have more rows to process,
then I'll start peeling off or accessing some of that data.
So, I'll simply get the email address for the students.
I'll say myRs.getString("email")
and assign it to a variable, alright?
And then I simply say an out.println(email).
So, this out.println will actually send the data
back to the browser.
Not to the standard out, but actually back to the browser.
So, we'll see a very simple page in the browser
that'll simply loop through each one of the emails
and simply print them out.
On line 55 where we say myRs.getString("email"),
that's simply getting the email from that given column name.
So that's the basic idea here for doing the Database work.
So, we get the connection, we create a statement,
we execute the SQL Query,
and then finally process the ResultSet.
So, that's the real brains here of this Servlet.
Well, alright, so let's go ahead and test this thing out.
So, what I'll do over on the left-hand side is
I'll kinda expand this window,
select this TestServlet,
and then I'll do a Right-Click
and I'll choose Run As,
and I'll say Run on Server.
And so it'll prompt us which Server to run on,
I'll just choose the Tomcat 8,
I'll say always use this server,
I'll click Next,
and then I can just hit Finish.
And Tomcat'll start up,
and then once Tomcat's running,
it'll show you the output here.
Wow, this looks pretty good.
So, these are the email addresses for the people,
or the students that we have in the Database.
So, we're actually connecting to the Database,
doing a Query, getting that ResultSet,
and displaying the results right here in the browser.
Now, don't worry, this is kinda very crude,
very ugly right now.
We're simply validating that we can connect to the Database.
Later in the videos we'll actually make this pretty,
we'll make use of HTML tables,
we'll put in cascading style sheets,
and we'll just make it look lovely, so don't worry.
So, let's go ahead and switch over to our MySQL tool,
just to make sure that we're looking
at the right data and stuff.
So, I'll open up MySQLWorkbench
and I'll go ahead and connect
using my root password.
And here's my table student,
and I just simply do a Right-Click here on Select Rows,
and then there we go.
So, we have these five students
with their five email addresses.
And those are actually the same email addresses
that we saw in the browser, alright?
So, our TestServlet, our Java Servlet,
is actually connecting to this MySQL Database,
grabbing the data, and then making it available.
So, this all looks really, really good.
Good job so far.